An Essay Concerning Human Understanding

Book I: Innate Notions

John Locke

Copyright © 2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are reported on, between [brackets], in normal-sized type.
First launched: July 2004 Last amended: December 2012 (I.iv.23 expanded)
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Chapter i: Introduction    1
Chapter ii: No innate ·speculative· principles in the mind    3
Chapter iii: No innate practical principles    9
Chapter iv: Further points about innate principles, speculative and practical    13

Essay I John Locke i: Introduction

Chapter i: Introduction

1. Since it is the understanding that sets man above all other animals and enables him to use and dominate them, it is certainly worth our while to enquire into it. The understanding is like the eye in this respect: it makes us see and perceive all other things but doesn’t look in on itself. To stand back from it and treat it as an object of study requires skill and hard work Still, whatever difficulties there may be in doing this, whatever it is that keeps us so much in the dark to ourselves, it will be worthwhile to let as much light as possible in upon our minds, and to learn as much as we can about our own understandings. As well as being enjoyable, this will help us to think well about other topics.

2. My purpose, therefore, is to enquire into •the origin, certainty, and extent of human knowledge, and also into •the grounds and degrees of belief, opinion, and assent. I shan’t involve myself with the biological aspects of the mind. For example, I shan’t wrestle with the question of what alterations of our bodies lead to our having sensation through our sense-organs or to our having any ideas in our understandings. Challenging and entertaining as these questions may be, I shall by-pass them because they aren’t relevant to my project. All we need for my purposes is to consider the human ability to think. My time will be well spent if by this plain, factual method I can explain how our understandings come to have those notions of things that we have, and can establish ways of measuring how certainly we can know things, and of evaluating the grounds we have for our opinions. Although our opinions are various, different, and often wholly contradictory, we express them with great assurance and confidence. Someone observing human opinions from the outside—seeing how they conflict with one another, and yet how fondly they are embraced and how stubbornly they are maintained—might have reason to suspect that either there isn’t any such thing as truth or that mankind isn’t equipped to come to know it.

3. So it will be worth our while to find where the line falls between opinion and knowledge, and to learn more about the ‘opinion’ side of the line. What I want to know is this: When we are concerned with something about which we have no certain knowledge, what rules or standards should guide how confident we allow ourselves to be that our opinions are right? Here is the method I shall follow in trying to answer that question. First, I shall enquire into the origin of those ideas or notions—call them what you will—that a man observes and is conscious of having in his mind. How does the understanding come to be equipped with them? Secondly, I shall try to show what knowledge the understanding has by means of those ideas—how much of it there is, how secure it is, and how self-evident it is. I shall also enquire a little into the nature and grounds of faith or opinion—that is, acceptance of something as true when we don’t know for certain that it is true.

4. I hope that this enquiry into the nature of the understanding will enable me to discover what its powers are—how far they reach, what things they are adequate to deal with, and where they fail us. If I succeed, that may have the effect of persuading the busy mind of man •to be more cautious in meddling with things that are beyond its powers to understand; •to stop when it is at the extreme end of its tether; and •to be peacefully reconciled to ignorance of things that turn out to be beyond the reach of our capacities.

1

Essay I John Locke i: Introduction

Perhaps then we shall stop pretending that we know everything, and shall be less bold in raising questions and getting into confusing disputes with others about things to which our understandings are not suited—things of which we can’t form any clear or distinct perceptions in our minds, or, as happens all too often, things of which we have no notions at all. If we can find out what the scope of the understanding is, how far it is able to achieve certainty, and in what cases it can only judge and guess, that may teach us to accept our limitations and to rest content with knowing only what our human condition enables us to know.

5. For, though the reach of our understandings falls far short of the vast extent of things, we shall still have reason to praise God for the kind and amount of knowledge that he has bestowed on us, so far above all the rest of creation. Men have reason to be well satisfied with what God has seen fit to give them, since he has given them everything they need for the •conveniences of life and the •forming of virtuous characters—that is, everything they need to discover how to •thrive in this life and how to •find their way to a better one.... Men can find plenty of material for thought, and for a great variety of pleasurable physical activities, if they don’t presumptuously complain about their own constitution and throw away the blessings their hands are filled with because their hands are not big enough to grasp everything. We shan’t have much reason to complain of the narrowness of our minds if we will only employ them on topics that may be of use to us; for on those they are very capable....

6. When we know what our ·muscular· strength is, we shall have a better idea of what ·physical tasks· we can attempt with hopes of success. And when we have thoroughly surveyed the powers of our own minds, and made some estimate of what we can expect from them, we shan’t be inclined either •to sit still, and not set our thoughts to work at all, in despair of knowing anything or •to question everything, and make no claim to any knowledge because some things can’t be understood. It is very useful for the sailor to know how long his line is, even though it is too short to fathom all the depths of the ocean. It is good for him to know that it is long enough to reach the bottom at places where he needs to know where it is, and to caution him against running aground....

7. This was what first started me on this Essay Concerning the Understanding. I thought that the first step towards answering various questions that people are apt to raise ·about other things· was to take a look at our own understandings, examine our own powers, and see to what they are fitted for. Till that was done (I suspected) we were starting at the wrong end—letting our thoughts range over the vast ocean of being, as though there were no limits to what we could understand, thereby spoiling our chances of getting a quiet and sure possession of truths that most concern us.... If men consider the capacities of our understandings, discover how far our knowledge extends, and find the horizon that marks off •the illuminated parts of things from •the dark ones, •the things we can understand from •the things we can’t, then perhaps they would be more willing to accept their admitted ignorance of •the former, and devote their thought and talk more profitably and satisfyingly to •the latter.

8. Before moving on, I must here at the outset ask you to excuse how frequently you will find me using the word ‘idea’ in this book. It seems to be the best word to stand for whatever is the object of the understanding when a man thinks; I have used it to express whatever is meant by ‘phantasm’, ‘notion’, ‘species’, or whatever it is that the mind

2

Essay I John Locke ii: No innate ·speculative· principles

can be employed about in thinking; and I couldn’t avoid frequently using it. Nobody, I presume, will deny that there are such ideas in men’s minds; everyone is conscious of them in himself, and men’s words and actions will satisfy him that they are in others. First, then: How do they come into the mind?

Chapter ii: No innate ·speculative· principles in the mind

1. Some people regard it as settled that there are in the understanding certain innate principles. These are conceived as primary notions [= ‘first thoughts’]—letters printed on the mind of man, so to speak—which the soul [= ‘mind’; no religious implications] receives when it first comes into existence, and that it brings into the world with it. I could show any fair-minded reader that this is wrong if I could show (as I hope to do in the present work) how men can get all the knowledge they have, and can arrive at certainty about some things, purely by using their natural faculties [= ‘capacities’, ‘abilities’], without help from any innate notions or principles. Everyone will agree, presumably, that it would be absurd to suppose that the ideas of colours are innate in a creature to whom God has given eyesight, which is a power to get those ideas through the eyes from external objects. It would be equally unreasonable to explain our knowledge of various truths in terms of innate ‘imprinting’ if it could just as easily be explained through our ordinary abilities to come to know things. Anyone who follows his own thoughts in the search of truth, and is led even slightly off the path of common beliefs, is likely to be criticized for this; ·and I expect to be criticized for saying that none of our intellectual possessions are innate·. So I shall present the reasons that made me doubt the truth of the innateness doctrine. That will be my excuse for my mistake, if that’s what it is. Whether it is a mistake can be decided by those who are willing, as I am, to welcome truth wherever they find it.

2. Nothing is more commonly taken for granted than that certain principles, both speculative [= ‘having to do with what is the case’] and practical [= ‘having to do with morality, or what ought to be the case’] are accepted by all mankind. Some people have argued that because these principles are (they think) universally accepted, they must have been stamped onto the souls of men from the outset.

3. This argument from universal consent has a defect in it. Even if it were in fact true that all mankind agreed in accepting certain truths, that wouldn’t prove them to be innate if universal agreement could be explained in some other way; and I think it can.

4. Worse still, this argument from universal consent which is used to prove that there are innate principles can be turned into a proof that there are none; because there aren’t any principles to which all mankind give universal assent. I shall begin with speculative principles, taking as my example those much vaunted logical principles •‘Whatever is, is’ and

3

Essay I John Locke ii: No innate ·speculative· principles

•‘It is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be’, which are the most widely thought to be innate. They are so firmly and generally believed to be accepted by everyone in the world that it may be thought strange that anyone should question this. Yet I am willing to say that these propositions, far from being accepted by everyone, have never even been heard of by a great part of mankind.

5. Children and idiots have no thought—not an inkling—of these principles, and that fact alone is enough to destroy the universal assent that any truth that was genuinely innate would have to have. For it seems to me nearly a contradiction to say that there are truths imprinted on the soul that it doesn’t perceive or understand—because if ‘imprinting’ means anything it means making something be perceived: to imprint anything on the mind without the mind’s perceiving it seems to me hardly intelligible. So if children and idiots have souls, minds, with those principles imprinted on them, they can’t help perceiving them and assenting to them. Since they don’t do that, it is evident that the principles are not innately impressed upon their minds. If they were naturally imprinted, and thus innate, how could they be unknown? To say that a notion is imprinted on the mind, and that the mind is ignorant of it and has never paid attention to it, is to make this impression nothing. No proposition can be said to be in the mind which it has never known or been conscious of. It may be said that a proposition that the mind has never consciously known may be ‘in the mind’ in the sense that the mind is capable of knowing it; but in that sense every true proposition that the mind is capable of ever assenting to may be said to be ‘in the mind’ and to be imprinted! Indeed, there could be ‘imprinted on’ someone’s mind, in this sense, truths that the person never did and never will know. For a man may be capable of knowing, and indeed of knowing with certainty, many things that he doesn’t in fact come to know at any time in his life. So if the mere ability to know is the natural impression philosophers are arguing for, all the truths a man ever comes to know will have to count as innate; and this great doctrine about ‘innateness’ will come down to nothing more than a very improper way of speaking, and not something that disagrees with the views of those who deny innate principles. For nobody, I think, ever denied that the mind was capable of knowing many truths. Those who think that •all knowledge is acquired ·rather than innate· also think that •the capacity for knowledge is innate. If these words ‘to be in the understanding’ are used properly, they mean ‘to be understood’. Thus, to be in the understanding and not be understood—to be in the mind and never be perceived—amounts to saying that something is and is not in the mind or understanding. If therefore these two propositions, •‘Whatsoever is, is’ and •‘It is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be’ are imprinted by nature, children cannot be ignorant of them; infants and all who have souls must necessarily have them in their understandings, know the truth of them, and assent to that truth.

6. To avoid this conclusion, it is usually answered that all men know and assent to these truths when they come to the use of reason, and this is enough to prove the truths innate. I answer as follows.

7. People who are in the grip of a prejudice don’t bother to look carefully at what they say; and so they will say things that are suspect—indeed almost meaningless—and pass them off as clear reasons. The foregoing claim ·that innateness is proved by assent-when-reason-is-reached·, if it is to be turned into something clear and applied to our present question, must mean either 1 that as soon as men come to the use of reason these supposedly innate truths

4

Essay I John Locke ii: No innate ·speculative· principles

come to be known and observed by them, or 2 that the use and exercise of men’s reason assists them in the discovery of these truths, making them known with certainty.

8. If they mean 2 that by the use of reason men may discover these principles, and that this is sufficient to prove them innate, they must be arguing for this conclusion:

Whatever truths reason can enable us to know for certain, and make us firmly assent to, are all ·innate, i.e.· naturally imprinted on the mind;

on the grounds that universal assent proves innateness, and that all we mean by something’s being ‘universally assented to’ in this context is merely that we can come to know it for sure, and be brought to assent to it, by the use of reason. This line of thought wipes out the distinction between the maxims [= ‘basic axioms’] of the mathematicians and the theorems they deduce from them; all must equally count as innate because they can all be known for certain through the use of reason.

9. How can people who take this view think that we need to use reason to discover principles that are supposedly innate?.... We may as well think that the use of reason is necessary to make our eyes discover visible objects as that we need to have (or to use) reason to make the understanding see what is originally engraved on it and cannot be in the understanding before being noticed by it. ‘Reason shows us those truths that have been imprinted’—this amounts to saying that the use of reason enables a man to learn what he already knew.

10. ·In reply to my final remark in section 8·, it may be said that maxims and other innate truths are, whereas mathematical demonstrations and other non-innate truths are not, assented to as soon as the question is put.... I freely acknowledge that maxims differ from mathematical demonstrations in this way: we grasp and assent to the latter only with the help of reason, using proofs, whereas the former—the basic maxims—are embraced and assented to as soon as they are understood, without the least reasoning. But so much the worse for the view that reason is needed for the discovery of these general truths [= maxims], since it must be admitted that reasoning plays no part in their discovery. And I think those who take this view ·that innate truths are known by reason· will hesitate to assert that the knowledge of the maxim that it is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be is a deduction of our reason. For by making our knowledge of such a principle depend on the labour of our thoughts they would be destroying that bounty of nature they seem so fond of. In all reasoning we search and flail around, having to take pains and stick to the problem. What sense does it make to suppose that all this is needed to discover something that was imprinted ·on us· by nature?

11.....It is therefore utterly false that reason assists us in the knowledge of these maxims; and ·as I have also been arguing·, if it were true it would prove that they are not innate!

12. ·Of the two interpretations mentioned in section 7, I now come to the one labelled 1·. If by ‘knowing and assenting to them when we come to the use of reason’ the innatists mean that this is when the mind comes to notice them, and that as soon as children acquire the use of reason they come also to know and assent to these maxims, this also is •false and •frivolous. •It is false because these maxims are obviously not in the mind as early as the use of reason. We observe ever so many instances of the use of reason in children long before they have any knowledge of the maxim that it is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be. Similarly with illiterate people and savages....

5

Essay I John Locke ii: No innate ·speculative· principles

13. ·All that is left for these innatists to claim is this·: Maxims or innate truths are never known or noticed before the use of reason, and may be assented to at some time after that, but there is no saying when. But that is true of all other knowable truths; so it doesn’t help to mark off innately known truths from others.

14. Anyway, even if it were true that certain truths came to be known and assented to at precisely the time when men acquire the use of reason, that wouldn’t prove them to be innate. To argue that it would do so is as •frivolous as the premise of the argument is •false. [Locke develops that point at some length. How, he demands, can x’s innateness be derived from the premise that a person first knows x when he comes to be able to reason? Why not derive something’s innateness from its being first known only when a person comes to be able to speak? (Or, he might have added even more mockingly, when a person first becomes able to walk? or to sing?) He allows some truth to the thesis that basic general maxims are not known to someone who doesn’t yet have the use of reason, but he explains this in terms not of innateness but rather of a theory of his own that he will develop later in the work. It rests on the assumption—which Locke doesn’t declare here—that to think a general maxim one must have general ideas, and that to express a general maxim one must be able to use general words. Then:] The growth of reason in a person goes along with his becoming able to form general abstract ideas, and to understand general names [= ‘words’]; so children usually don’t have such general ideas or learn the ·general· names that stand for them until after they have for a good while employed their reason on familiar and less general ideas; and it is during that period that their talk and behaviour shows them to be capable of rational conversation.

[Sections 15 and 16 continue with this theme. A typical passage is this, from section 16:] The later it is before anyone comes to have those general ideas that are involved in ·supposedly innate· maxims, or to know the meanings of the general words that stand for them, or to put together in his mind the ideas they stand for; the later also it will be before he comes to assent to the maxims.... Those words and ideas are no more innate than is the idea of cat or of weasel. So the child must wait until time and observation have acquainted him with them; and then he will be in a fit state to know the truth of these maxims.

17.....Some people have tried to secure universal assent to the propositions they call maxims by saying they are generally assented to as soon as they are proposed, and the terms they are proposed in are understood....

18. In answer to this, I ask whether prompt assent given to a proposition upon first hearing it and understanding the terms really is a certain mark of an innate principle? If so, then we must classify as innate all such propositions, in which case the innatists will find themselves plentifully supplied with innate principles—including various propositions about numbers that everybody assents to at first hearing and understanding the terms. And not just numbers; for even the natural sciences contain propositions that are sure to meet with assent as soon as they are understood: •Two bodies cannot be in the same place ·at the same time· is a truth that a person would no more hesitate to accept than he would to accept •It is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be, •White is not black, or •A square is not a circle. If assent at first hearing and understanding the terms were a mark of innateness, we would have to accept as innate every •proposition in which different ideas are denied one of another. We would have legions of innate propositions of this

6

Essay I John Locke ii: No innate ·speculative· principles

one sort, not to mention all the others.... Now, I agree that a proposition is shown to be self-evident by its being promptly assented to by everyone who hears it and understands its terms; but self-evidence comes not from innateness but from a different source which I shall present in due course. There are plenty of self-evident propositions that nobody would be so fanciful as to claim to be innate.

19. Don’t say that the less general self-evident propositions—One and two are equal to three, Green is not red, and so on—are accepted as the consequences of more general ones that are taken to be innate. Anyone who attends with care to what happens in the understanding will certainly find that the less general propositions are known for sure, and firmly assented to, by people who are utterly ignorant of those more general maxims; so the former can’t be accepted on the strength of the latter.

[In section 20 Locke considers the claim that the less general self evident truths are not ‘of any great use’, unlike the more general maxims that are called innate. He replies that no reason has been given for connecting usefulness to innateness, and that in any case he is going to question whether the more general maxims are of any great use.]

21. ·Here is another objection to inferring a proposition’s innateness from its being assented by anyone who hears it and understands its terms·. Rather than this being a sign that the proposition is innate, it is really a proof that it isn’t. It is being assumed that people who understand and know other things are ignorant of these ·self-evident and supposedly innate· principles till they are proposed to them. But if they were innate, why would they need to be proposed in order to be assented to? Wouldn’t their being in the understanding through a natural and original impression lead to their being known even before being proposed? Or does proposing them print them more clearly in the mind than nature did? If so, then a man knows such a proposition better after he has been thus taught it—·that is, had it clarifyingly ‘proposed’ to him·—than he did before. This implies that these principles may be made more evident to us by others’ teaching than nature has made them by impression; which deprives supposedly innate principles of their authority, and makes them unfit to be the foundations of all our other knowledge, as they are claimed to be....

[Section 22 briefly and unsympathetically discusses the suggestion that even before a man first has an innate maxim ‘proposed’ to him, he has an implicit knowledge of it.]

[In section 23 Locke argues that the position he is now opposing—that a proposition counts as innate if it is assented to when first proposed and understood—looks plausible only because it is assumed that when the proposition is proposed and made to be understood nothing new is learned; that assumption might lead Locke’s opponents to say that he was wrong in section 21 to say that such propositions are taught. Against this he says:] In truth they are taught, and ·in such teaching the pupils· do learn something they were ignorant of before. They have learned the terms and their meanings, neither of which were born with them; and they have acquired the relevant ideas, which were not born with them any more than their names were. [Locke then presents at some length his own view about what really happens when someone assents to a self-evident proposition; all this will be developed further in Book II.]

24. To conclude this argument about universal consent, I agree with these defenders of innate principles that if they are innate they must have universal assent. (I can no more make sense of a truth’s being innate and yet not assented to than I can of a man’s knowing a truth while being ignorant

7

Essay I John Locke ii: No innate ·speculative· principles

of it.) But it follows that they can’t be innate, because they are not universally assented to, as I have shown....

25. It may be objected that I have been arguing from the thoughts of infants, drawing conclusions from what happens in their understandings, whereas we really don’t know what their thoughts are. [Locke at some length just denies this, claiming that we do know a good deal about the thoughts of children. The section ends thus:] The child certainly knows that the wormseed or mustard it refuses is not the apple or sugar it cries for: this it is certainly and undoubtedly assured of. But will anyone say that the child has this knowledge by virtue of the principle It is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be? Someone who says that children join in these general abstract speculations with their sucking bottles and their rattles can fairly be thought to have less sincerity and truth than an infant, even if he outdoes the child in his passion and zeal for his opinion!

[Section 26 winds up that whole line of argument.]

[Section 27 advances a new argument. The innatist must allow that the truths innately implanted in our minds don’t always present themselves to our consciousness, and he is forced to explain that this happens because our innately given intellectual possessions may be smudged over, ‘corrupted by custom or borrowed opinions, by learning and education’. But if that were right, those innate truths ‘should appear fairest and clearest’ in the minds of ‘children, idiots, savages, and illiterate people’; yet in such people ‘we find no footsteps of them’.] One would think, according to the innatists’ principles, that all these native beams of light (if they existed) would shine out most brilliantly in people who are not skilled in concealing things, leaving us in no more doubt of their having them than we are of their loving pleasure and hating pain. But alas, amongst children, idiots, savages, and the grossly illiterate, what general maxims are to be found? What universal principles of knowledge? Their notions are few and narrow, borrowed only from the objects they have had most to do with, and which have most frequently and strongly impressed themselves upon their senses....

28. I don’t know how absurd my position on this may seem to logicians; and probably most people will find it, on a first hearing, hard to swallow. So I ask for a little truce with prejudice, and a holding off from of criticism, until I have been heard out in the later parts of this Book. I am very willing to submit to better judgments. Since I impartially search after truth, I shan’t mind becoming convinced that I have been too fond of my own notions; which I admit we are all apt to be when application and study have excited our heads with them....

8

Essay I John Locke Chapter iii: No innate practical principles

Chapter iii: No innate practical principles

1. It is even more obvious that no practical [= ‘moral’] principles are universally assented to than that no speculative [= ‘non-moral’] principles are. It will be hard to find any moral rule that has as much claim to immediate universal assent as ‘What is, is’ or that is as obviously true as ‘It is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be.’ So the case against the innateness of practical principles is even stronger. In saying this I don’t question their truth: the two kinds of principle are equally true, but they are not equally self-evident. The speculative maxims of which I have written are self-evident; ·you have only to bring them clearly before your mind to see that they are true·; but moral principles need to be supported by reasons; you have to use your mind on them to become certain that they are true. This, however, doesn’t detract from their truth or certainty. (Similarly, ‘The three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles’ is not as evidently true as ‘The whole is bigger than a part’, nor so apt to be assented to at first hearing; but it is true and certain all the same.) Since these moral rules can be demonstrated, it is our own fault if we don’t achieve certain knowledge of them. But the sheer fact that •many men are ignorant of them, and the fact that •others come to them only gradually, are clear proofs that moral rules are not something we can know without searching for them, and are therefore not innate.

2. If you have the slightest knowledge of the history of mankind, or have looked beyond the four walls of your own home, you must know that there are no moral principles that everyone assents to. Most people seem to agree about justice and the keeping of contracts. Indeed, this principle is thought to be respected even amongst thieves and other villains: those who have gone furthest towards losing their own humanity, it is said, still keep faith with another. So indeed they do; but they observe principles of justice merely as rules of convenience within their own communities, not as innate moral laws. It isn’t believable that someone who is ready to plunder or kill the next honest man he meets with acts fairly with his fellow highwayman because he embraces justice as a moral principle! Justice and truth are the common ties of society; and therefore even outlaws and robbers must keep faith and rules of fairness amongst themselves, for otherwise their gangs will fall apart. But will anyone say that those who live by crime allow themselves to be guided by innate principles of truth and justice?

3. You may want to say that criminals accept those principles even though they don’t act on them. Well, I have always thought that men’s actions are the best guides to their thoughts. Furthermore, it is very strange and unreasonable to suppose that there are innate practical principles that show up in what men think but don’t affect their behaviour. What makes a principle practical (rather than speculative) is its bearing upon action. Something of a practical kind that is innate in all mankind, and influences all our conduct, is a desire for happiness and an aversion to misery; but this has to do with our •wants, not with our moral beliefs. I don’t deny that there are •natural tendencies imprinted on the minds of men, so that from the moment we begin to perceive we like some things and dislike others; but that doesn’t mean that we have innately in our minds anything amounting to principles of moral knowledge....

4. Another reason for doubting that there are any innate practical principles is that I think one can fairly ask for a

9

Essay I John Locke Chapter iii: No innate practical principles

reason for any moral rule whatsoever. If such rules were innate, they would be self-evident: their truth could be seen without any kind of proofs or reasons; and so the demand for a reason would be perfectly ridiculous and absurd. Someone who asked why it is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be would be regarded as lacking in common sense, as would someone who tried to answer him. That speculative principle needs no proof except its own self-evidence: anyone who understands the words accepts the principle for its own sake, and if he doesn’t, nothing will change his mind. In contrast with that, suppose someone hears for the first time ‘One should do as he would be done unto’, and understands its meaning, might he not without any absurdity ask for a reason why? and ought not the person who proposes it be willing to supply a reason? But if it were innate, it wouldn’t need a reason and couldn’t be given one. Clearly, the truth of all these moral rules depends on some underlying rules from which they must be deduced; and this could not be so if they were innate, or even if they were merely self-evident.

5. That men should keep their promises is certainly a great and undeniable rule in morality. But if •a Christian is asked why a man must keep his word, he will answer: because God, who has the power of eternal life and death, requires him to. But if •a follower of Hobbes is asked why, he will answer: because the public requires it, and the state will punish you if you don’t. And if •one of the old philosophers had been asked, he would have answered: because breaking promises is dishonest, below the dignity of a man, and opposite to virtue, which is the highest perfection of human nature.

6. So men’s opinions concerning moral rules vary greatly, according to the different sorts of happiness they aim at. This couldn’t be so if practical principles were innate, and imprinted in our minds immediately by the hand of God. I grant that the existence of God is made clear to us in so many ways, and the obedience we owe him agrees so much with the light of reason, that a great part of mankind proclaim the law of nature; but it can’t be denied that moral rules can be generally approved of by people who don’t know that their true ground is—namely, the will and law of a God who sees men in the dark, has in his hand rewards and punishments, and has power enough to call to account the proudest offender. God has firmly joined virtue and public happiness together, and made virtuous conduct necessary to the preservation of society, and visibly beneficial to everyone the virtuous man has any dealings with; so it isn’t surprising that each person should not merely accept those rules but also recommend and praise them to other people whose observance of the rules is bound to bring advantage to him. He may, out of self-interest rather than conviction, declare the sacredness of something that he needs to have observed for his own security. This doesn’t detract from the moral and eternal obligation that these rules evidently have; but it shows that the outward acknowledgment men pay to them in their words doesn’t prove that they are innate principles. Indeed, it doesn’t even prove that men assent to them inwardly in their own minds as unbreakable rules for their own conduct....

7. For if we don’t politely believe everything that men say, but take their actions to show what they think, we shall find that they have no such inner respect for these rules, and are not so sure they are bound by them.... It may be urged that men’s consciences help to prevent them from breaking the rules, showing that there is after all an internal sense of being obliged by them.

8. To which I answer that many men can come to assent to various moral rules in the same way that they come to the

10

Essay I John Locke Chapter iii: No innate practical principles

knowledge of other things—without the rules being written on their hearts. And others may be led the same way by their education, the company they keep, and the customs of their country. Such an assent to the rules, however it is come by, will activate the conscience—which is nothing but our own opinion or judgment of the moral rightness or wrongness of our own actions. And if conscience is a proof of innateness, contraries can be innate principles; because sometimes men will conscientiously promote what others conscientiously avoid.

9. But if those moral rules were innate, and stamped on men’s minds, I can’t see how anyone should ever confidently and serenely break them. ·Yet this happens constantly·. See an army sacking a town, and look for signs of the soldier’s •obeying or •having some sense of moral principles, •feeling some touch of conscience over the outrages they are performing! Robberies, murders, rapes, are the sports of men who are not threatened with punishment and censure. Have there not been whole nations, and those of the most civilized people, amongst whom the exposing their children—leaving them in the fields to die of hunger or from wild beasts—has been the practice? [The section continues with a page and a half of even more disgusting examples.]

10. Look carefully at the history of mankind, and scan the various tribes of men, looking without prejudice at their actions, and you will be able to satisfy yourself that

There is hardly a principle of morality to be named, or rule of virtue to be thought of, that is not somewhere in the world slighted and condemned by the general fashion of whole societies of men who live by moral views and rules that are quite opposite to those of others.

An exception is provided by rules that are absolutely necessary to hold society together; but these too are commonly flouted in relations between distinct societies.

11. It may be objected that a rule’s being broken doesn’t prove that it is not known. I agree with this, in cases where men break a moral law but don’t disown it, showing by their fear of shame, blame, or punishment that they still hold it in some awe. But it is impossible to conceive that a whole nation of men should all publicly reject and renounce what every one of them, certainly and infallibly, knew to be a law (as they must if it is naturally imprinted on their minds).... Whatever practical principle is innate must be known to everyone to be just and good. It is therefore little less than a contradiction to suppose that whole nations of men should, in both speech and action, unanimously and universally give the lie to what every one of them knew for certain to be true, right, and good. So no practical rule can be supposed to be innate if in any part of the world it is transgressed universally and with public approval or without disapproval.

12. [Locke discusses, as a possible candidate for an innate moral rule, ‘Parents, preserve and cherish your children’, and reverts to the section 9 topic of the widespread breaches of this rule. Then a quite different point:] •Parents, preserve your children is so far from being an innate truth that it isn’t a truth at all: it is a •command, not a •proposition, so it cannot be true or false. To make it capable of being assented to as true, we must turn it into some such proposition as •It is the duty of parents to preserve their children. But what duty is cannot be understood without a law; and a law cannot be known or supposed without a law-maker, or without reward and punishment. So it is impossible that this or any other practical principle should be innate, i.e. be imprinted on the mind as a duty, without presupposing the innateness of the ideas of God, of law, of obligation, of punishment, and

11

Essay I John Locke Chapter iii: No innate practical principles

of a life after this.... But these are so far from being innate that they are not to be found clear and distinct in the mind of every studious or thinking man, let alone in the mind of every man who is ever born. In my next chapter I shall show that the one of them that seems most likely to be innate—I mean the idea of God—is not so.

13. From what I have said I think we may safely conclude that no principle is innate if it is in any place generally allowed to be broken, for it is impossible that men should confidently and serenely break a rule that they know (and if it were innate they would have to know) had been set by God, who would certainly punish any breach of it so severely as to make the transgression a poor bargain. [In the remainder of this long section Locke elaborates this point: if a practical principle were innate, men would have to know that it was set by God who would certainly punish breaches of it very severely; and someone who knows that about a law will certainly be deterred from breaking it. He concludes with a different point:] Don’t think that because I deny an innate law I hold that there are only man-made laws. There is a great deal of difference between an •innate law ·which I deny· and a •law of nature ·which I accept·, between •something imprinted on our minds in their very origin and •something we can come to know of through the proper use of our natural faculties. There are two extremes: •those who affirm that there are innate laws, and •those who deny that any law can be known by the light of nature, i.e. without the help of revelation; and I think they are both far from the truth.

14. The way men differ in their practical principles is so obvious as to doom all attempts to identify any moral rules as innate on the basis of their being generally accepted. I suspect that the supposition of such innate principles is merely an irresponsible free-floating opinion, because those who talk about them so confidently don’t tell us which they are, as one might reasonably expect them to do.... Since nobody, so far as I know, has yet ventured to give a catalogue of the innate practical principles, their supporters can’t blame those of us who doubt that they exist.... Very many men are so far from finding any such innate moral principles in themselves that by denying freedom to mankind and thereby making men no more than mere machines, they take away not only innate but all moral rules whatsoever, making it impossible for such rules to be believed in by those who can’t conceive how anything except a free agent can be capable of a law. Upon that ground, those who can’t reconcile morality with mechanism (which is hard to do) must necessarily reject all principles of virtue.

[In sections 15–19 Locke discusses a writing by Lord Herbert of Cherbury. After completing the previous sections, he reports, he learned that Lord Herbert had given a list of innate principles and an account of the criteria by which they can be classified as innate. Locke says that not all the items on the list satisfy all the criteria, and that they are satisfied by plenty of things not on the list. Some are criticized as vague or ambiguous, some as trivial, etc.]

20. It may be said that the innate principles of morality may be darkened in the minds of men, and eventually quite worn out, by education and custom and the general opinion of the members of one’s society. If this is true it destroys the argument from universal consent for the existence of innate principles, unless the members of this or that sect regard their agreeing on something as ‘universal consent’. People do this, presuming themselves to be the only masters of right reason, and throwing out the votes and opinions of the rest of mankind, as not worth taking into account. So this is their argument:

12

Essay I John Locke iv: More about innate principles

The principles that all mankind count as true are innate; those that men of right reason accept are the principles allowed by all mankind; we and like-minded people are men of reason; therefore, since we agree, our principles are innate;

which is a very clever way of arguing, and a short cut to infallibility! For without that ·absurd approach·, it will be very hard to understand how there can be principles that all men agree on, though they are all blotted out of the minds of many men by depraved custom, and bad education—that is principles that all men accept and many men deny! [In the remainder of the section Locke elaborates this point.]

[Sections 21–6 discuss the absolute confidence that people have in the truth of certain doctrines—different doctrines in different societies. Locke offers to explain this phenomenon, largely in terms of early education. In 23 he inserts a connection between early education and the belief that there are innate principles: ‘When people who have been so instructed grow up and reflect on their own minds, they can’t find anything more ancient there than the opinions that they were taught before their memory began to keep a record of the happenings in their lives or to note the time when any new thing appeared to them. They can’t remember any source for those opinions, and that makes them sure that the opinions were impressed on them by God and nature.’ In section 24: ‘There is scarcely anyone so floating and superficial in his understanding that he doesn’t have some revered propositions that he takes to be the principles on which he bases his reasonings, and by which he judges of truth and falsehood, right and wrong.’ In section 25 the topic is the effect of social pressure in stopping people from examining the revered propositions critically. Near the end of 26:] Anyone who takes any such supposed principles into his mind and regards them with the reverence usually paid to principles, never venturing to examine them but getting the habit of believing them because they are to be believed, can be led by his education and the fashions of his country to regard any absurdity as an innate principle.

[In section 27 Locke contends that his explanation in the preceding sections seems to be the only one that can explain why so many conflicting propositions are thought to be innate.]

Chapter iv: Further points about innate principles, speculative and practical

1. If the supporters of innate principles had thought not merely about •whole propositions but also about •the parts out of which propositions are made, they mightn’t have been so ready to believe that some principles are innate. ·That is because· if the ideas that make up those truths are not innate, the propositions made up of them can’t be so. For if the ideas are not innate, then there was a time when the mind didn’t contain those principles; in which case the principles are not innate but have some other source....

2. If we attentively consider new-born children, we find little

13

Essay I John Locke iv: More about innate principles

reason to think that they bring many ideas into the world with them. Except perhaps for some faint ideas of hunger and thirst, and warmth, and some pains, which they may have felt in the womb, they seem not to have any settled ideas at all—and especially not ideas matching the words that make up the universal propositions that are thought to be innate. We can see how they gradually come to have more ideas, which they do only by acquiring ideas that are furnished by experience and the observation of things. That might be enough to satisfy us that they—·the ideas·—are not characters stamped on the mind from birth.

3. If there are any innate principles, then surely this is one: It is impossible for the same thing to be, and not to be. But can anyone think, or will anyone say, that impossibility and identity are two innate ideas? Are they ideas that mankind have, and bring into the world with them? Are they ones that children have before they acquire any others ·from experience·?.... The words ‘impossibility’ and ‘identity’ stand for two ideas which, far from being innate or born with us, can be properly formed in our understandings only through great care and attention.... Upon examination it will be found that many grown men don’t have them.

[In section 4 Locke discusses the idea of identity, sketching some philosophical problems involving it, as evidence that the idea isn’t ‘clear and obvious to us’.]

[In section 5 he argues that these questions are not trivial, because they come into our thinking about how we shall fare on Judgment Day: am I, who now stand before God awaiting his judgment, the very same person as the one who performed such and such actions? Locke will discuss this at length in II.xxvii.]

[In section 6 Locke gives a somewhat technical reason why the ideas of whole and part cannot be innate, so that the ‘principle of mathematics The whole is bigger than a part’ cannot be innate either.]

7. That God is to be worshipped is without doubt as great a truth as any that can enter into the human mind, and deserves the first place among all practical principles. But it can’t be innate unless the ideas of God and worship are innate. But the idea the term ‘worship’ stands for is not in the understanding of children, is not a character stamped on their minds at birth; you’ll easily agree with that if you consider how few adults, even, have a clear and distinct notion of it....

8. If any idea can be imagined to be innate, the idea of God is the most likely one, for many reasons. ·But· ancient writers noted that there were atheists then, and in recent times explorers have discovered whole nations amongst whom there is to be found no notion of a God, no religion. [Through much of the section Locke evaluates the evidence for this as it relates to Brazil, China and other nations. Then:] And if we attended to the actions and speech of people closer to home, we might have reason to fear that many people in more civilized countries have no very strong and clear impressions of a God in their minds, and that preachers’ complaints of atheism are not without reason. At present ·in our part of the world· the only people who avow their atheism openly and without shame are wretches who are entirely given over to vice; but if the fear of legal or social consequences didn’t tie up people’s tongues, so that prospects of punishment or shame were taken away, many more people would proclaim their atheism as openly as their lives do.

[In sections 9–11 Locke argues that even if all mankind, at all times and places, had a notion of God, this wouldn’t be good evidence that the idea was innate. That is because ‘the visible marks of extraordinary wisdom and power appear

14

Essay I John Locke iv: More about innate principles

so plainly in all the works of the creation that any rational person who thinks seriously about them must conclude that they are the work of a God’ (9); and this belief could then spread throughout the world through communication amongst humans, so that the (supposed) universality of the idea of God could be explained in epidemiological terms (so to speak) rather than through innateness.]

12. Indeed it has been argued that •it is suitable to God’s goodness that he should imprint characters and notions of himself on the minds of men, rather than leaving them in darkness and doubt regarding a matter of such importance to them, and also to secure for himself the homage and veneration that is his due from a thinking creature such as man; and that therefore •he has done this. But if this argument has any force, it will prove much more than its friends want it to. From the premise It is suitable to God’s goodness that he should do for men all that they judge is best for them it infers God has indeed done for men all that they judge is best for them. [Locke attacks this on the ground that it implies that God has done things that he plainly has not, e.g. made all men obedient to his will. He then attacks the argument at its root.] I think it a very good argument to say:

The infinitely wise God has made it so; and therefore it is best.

But we put too much confidence of our own wisdom if we argue:

I think it best, and therefore God has made it so.

Applying this to our present topic: it is futile to argue that God has done so—·that is, has innately imprinted our minds with an idea of him·—when experience shows us clearly that he has not.... ·This isn’t to imply any lack of goodness in God·. I expect to show ·in IV.x· that a man, by the right use of his natural abilities and without any innate principles, can acquire a knowledge of a God and of other things that concern him. Once God had endowed men with the faculties of knowledge that they have, he was no more obliged by his goodness also to plant innate notions in their minds than he is obliged, after giving men reason, hands, and materials, also to build bridges or houses for them....

13. I agree that if there were any idea imprinted on the minds of men, we have reason •to expect it to be the notion of his maker, as a mark God set on his own workmanship, to keep men in mind of their dependence and duty, and •to expect that the first instances of human knowledge would involve that idea. But in fact children don’t show themselves to have any such notion until quite late, and when they do have an idea of God it reflects the opinion and notion of the child’s teacher more than it represents the true God....

[Sections 14–17 discuss at length the variety there is among different peoples’ ideas of God. A core thought in these sections is this: ‘The truest and best notions men have of God were not ·innately· imprinted, but acquired by thought and meditation and a right use of their faculties’ (16).]

[In section 18 Locke mentions a supposed ‘idea of substance’, sketching a view about it that he will develop at length in II.xxiii and elsewhere. It isn’t usefully relevant to the innateness issue.]

[In section 19 Locke repeats various anti-innateness arguments that he has already presented.]

20. Here is another argument. If there are any ideas—innate or not—in a mind at a time when it doesn’t actually think of them, they must be lodged in the memory. ·That’s the only way something can be ‘in the mind’ without being involved in thoughts that the mind is consciously having·. For such an idea to be brought into view ·in the conscious mind· it must

15

Essay I John Locke iv: More about innate principles

be remembered, and to remember something is to perceive it with a consciousness that one has known or perceived it before. Without this, whatever idea comes into the mind is •new and not •remembered, for this consciousness of its having been in the mind before is what distinguishes remembering from every other kind of mental event.... If therefore there are any innate ideas, they must be in the memory or else nowhere in the mind; and if they are in the memory they can be revived without any impression from outside; and whenever they are brought into the mind, they bring with them a perception of their not being wholly new to it.... In the light of this, consider whether there are any innate ideas in the mind before ·any are brought in by the· impression from sensation or reflection.... I would like to meet the person who, when he came to the use of reason or at any other time, remembered any such ideas, and who never in his life experienced them as new. If anyone says that there are ideas in the mind that are not in the memory ·and that the mind isn’t conscious of·, I ask him to explain himself and make what he says intelligible.

21. Here is a further reason why I doubt that any principles are innate. I am sure that the infinitely wise God made all things in perfect wisdom; and I can’t see why he should print on the minds of men some universal principles of which

•the non-moral ones that are claimed to be innate are of no great use, and •the moral ones that are claimed to be innate are not self-evident, and •nothing distinguishes those two groups from some other truths that are not said to be innate.

What reason would God have to inscribe on the mind of man messages that are no clearer than (or can’t be distinguished from) messages that came there later? If anyone thinks there are such innate ideas and propositions that are clearer and more useful than anything that comes into the mind from the outside, it won’t be hard for him to tell us which ones they are, and then we can all judge for ourselves whether they are as he says....

[Section 22 continues the attack on innateness, warning against mistaking other phenomena for innate ideas, and warning against intellectual laziness. The chief emphasis is that we have to work for knowledge, and not expect it to be handed to us on a plate, so to speak.]

23. I don’t know how much I will be blamed for doubting that there are any innate principles—blamed by men who will be apt to say that I am pulling up the old foundations of knowledge and certainty. But I think that what I am saying squares with the truth, and that it will therefore replace those old foundations by newer and more secure ones. I am certain of this: in the rest of this work I shan’t be concerned either to •depart from any authority or to •follow any authority. My only aim has been truth, and wherever that has appeared to lead my thoughts have impartially followed, without caring whether anyone else’s footsteps have gone that way before me. I have a due respect for other men’s opinions, but our greatest respect should be for truth; and I modestly suggest that we might get further in the discovery of rational and contemplative knowledge if we •sought it at its source, i.e. by examining things themselves, and •used our own thoughts rather than other men’s to find it. We have no more chance of •knowing by other men’s understandings as we have of •seeing with other men’s eyes. Our real knowledge is measured by how much truth and reason we have taken in. Floating other men’s opinions in our brains makes us not a bit more knowing, even if the opinions happen to be true.... In the sciences, what you possess is what you really know and comprehend; what you only believe and take on trust is

16

Essay I John Locke iv: More about innate principles

merely shreds; however valuable the whole fabric of which they are shreds, gathering them piecemeal won’t add much to your stock. Such borrowed wealth is like fairy-money: even if it was gold in the hand from which you received it, when you come to use it for yourself you’ll find it is nothing but leaves and dust.

24. When men have found some general propositions that couldn’t be doubted as soon as they were understood, it was a short and easy way to conclude that they are innate. This conclusion excused lazy people from the effort of further research.... Those who purported to be masters and teachers were much helped by making this the principle of principles: Principles must not be questioned! Once they had laid it down that there are innate principles, they required their followers to accept some doctrines as innate; which meant accepting them on trust, without bringing their own reason and judgment to bear on them. This posture of blind credulity makes a person easier to be governed and manipulated by those who •have the skill to inculcate principles into him and guide his thoughts, and are •in a position to do this. It is no small power that one man has over others if he has the authority to dictate principles and teach unquestionable truths, and can make them swallow as ‘innate’ something that it serves his purposes to have them believe. If these victims had ·declined to swallow, and instead had· examined how we come to our knowledge of many universal truths, they would have found the truths to result in our minds from properly attending to the nature of things themselves, and that they were discovered through the proper use of those faculties of ours that are fitted by nature to receive and judge them.

25. How the understanding goes about this—that is what I aim to show in the rest of this book. I started with an account of my reasons for doubting that there are innate principles, because this was needed in order to clear my way to the foundations that I think are the only true ones on which to base the notions we can have of our own knowledge. Because some of the arguments against innate principles arise from commonly accepted opinions, I have been forced to take some things for granted; as one can hardly avoid doing when showing the falsehood or improbability of some doctrine. What happens in intellectual controversy is like what happens in attacking towns: if the ground on which the cannons are placed is firm and serves the purpose, nobody asks who owns it! But in the remainder of this work I shall ·not be trying to pull anything down, but rather· trying—with what help I can get from my own experience and observation—to raise an edifice that is uniform and self-consistent. And I hope to erect it on such a basis that I shan’t need to shore it up with props and buttresses, leaning on borrowed or begged foundations. Even if it turns out to be a castle in the air, I shall try to make it one that is all of a piece and that hangs together. I warn the reader not to expect me to do this with undeniable and compelling demonstrations; though I could do that if I were allowed the privilege, which many allow themselves, of taking my principles for granted. All that I shall say for •the principles from which I start is that I appeal to your own unprejudiced experience and observation ·to decide· whether •they are true. This is enough for a man who claims only to be laying down candidly and freely his own views about a subject that lies somewhat in the dark, aiming at nothing but an unbiased enquiry after truth.

17

An Essay Concerning Human Understanding

Book II: Ideas

John Locke

Copyright © 2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are reported on, between [brackets], in normal-sized type.
First launched: July 2004 Last amended: August 2007
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Chapter i: Ideas in general, and their origin 18
Chapter ii: Simple ideas 23
Chapter iii: Ideas of one sense 24
Chapter iv: Solidity 24
Chapter v: Simple ideas of different senses 27
Chapter vi: Simple ideas of reflection 27
Chapter vii: Simple ideas of both sensation and reflection 27

Essay II John Locke

Chapter viii: Some further points about our simple ideas 29
Chapter ix: Perception 34
Chapter x: Retention 37
Chapter xi: Discerning, and other operations of the mind 39
Chapter xii: Complex ideas 43
Chapter xiii: Simple modes, starting with the simple modes of space 46
Chapter xiv: Duration and its simple modes 52
Chapter xv: Duration and expansion, considered together 57
Chapter xvi: Number 60
Chapter xvii: Infinity 62
Chapter xviii: Other simple modes 67
Chapter xix: The modes of thinking 68
Chapter xx: Modes of pleasure and pain 69
Chapter xxi: Power 72
Chapter xxii: Mixed modes 93
Chapter xxiii: Complex ideas of substances 97
Chapter xxiv: Collective ideas of substances 107
Chapter xxv: Relation 109
Chapter xxvi: Cause and effect, and other relations 111

Essay II John Locke

Chapter xxvii: Identity and diversity 112
Chapter xxviii: Other relations 122
Chapter xxix: Clear and obscure, distinct and confused ideas 127
Chapter xxx: Real and fantastical ideas 131
Chapter xxxi: Adequate and inadequate ideas 133
Chapter xxxii: True and false ideas 137
Chapter xxxiii: The association of ideas 141

Essay II John Locke i: Ideas and their origin

Chapter i: Ideas in general, and their origin

1. Everyone is conscious to himself that he thinks; and when thinking is going on, the mind is engaged with ideas that it contains. So it’s past doubt that men have in their minds various ideas, such as are those expressed by the words ‘whiteness’, ‘hardness’, ‘sweetness’, ‘thinking’, ‘motion’, ‘man’, ‘elephant’, ‘army’, ‘drunkenness’, and others. The first question, then, is How does he acquire these ideas? It is widely believed that men have ideas stamped upon their minds in their very first being. My opposition to this in Book I will probably be received more favourably when I have shown where the understanding can get all its ideas from—an account that I contend will be supported by everyone’s own observation and experience.

2. Let us then suppose the mind to have no ideas in it, to be like white paper with nothing written on it. How then does it come to be written on? From where does it get that vast store which the busy and boundless imagination of man has painted on it—all the materials of reason and knowledge? To this I answer, in one word, from experience. Our understandings derive all the materials of thinking from observations that we make of •external objects that can be perceived through the senses, and of •the internal operations of our minds, which we perceive by looking in at ourselves.These two are the fountains of knowledge, from which arise all the ideas we have or can naturally have.

3. First, our senses when applied to particular perceptible objects convey into the mind many distinct perceptions of things, according to the different ways in which the objects affect them. That’s how we come by the ideas we have of yellow, white, heat, cold, soft, hard, bitter, sweet, and all so on—the so-called ‘sensible qualities’. When I say the senses convey ·these ideas· into the mind, ·I don’t mean this strictly and literally, because I don’t mean to say that an idea actually travels across from the perceived object to the person’s mind. Rather· I mean that through the senses external objects convey into the mind something that produces there those perceptions [= ‘ideas’]. This great source of most of the ideas we have I call SENSATION.

4. Secondly, the other fountain from which experience provides ideas to the understanding is the perception of the operations of our own mind within us. This yields ideas that couldn’t be had from external things—ones such as ·the ideas of· perception, thinking, doubting, believing, reasoning, knowing, willing, and all the different things that our minds do. Being conscious of these actions of the mind and observing them in ourselves, our understandings get from them ideas that are as distinct as the ones we get from bodies affecting our senses. Every man has this source of ideas wholly within himself; and though it is not sense, because it has nothing to do with external objects, it is still very like sense, and might properly enough be called ‘internal sense’. But along with calling the other ‘sensation’, I call this REFLECTION, because the ideas it gives us can be had only by a mind reflecting on its own operations within itself. By ‘reflection’ then, in the rest of this work, I mean the notice that the mind takes of what it is doing, and how. (I am here using ‘operations’ in a broad sense, to cover not only the actions of the mind on its ideas but also passive states that can arise from them, such as is the satisfaction or uneasiness arising from any thought.) So that’s my thesis: all our ideas take their beginnings from

18

Essay II John Locke i: Ideas and their origin

those two sources—external material things as objects of sensation, and the operations of our own minds as objects of reflection.

5..... When we have taken a full survey of •the ideas we get from these sources, and of their various modes, combinations, and relations, we shall find they are •our whole stock of ideas; and that we have nothing in our minds that didn’t come in one of these two ways. [Locke then challenges the reader to ‘search into his understanding’ and see whether he has any ideas other than those of sensation and reflection.]

6. If you look carefully at the state of a new-born child, you’ll find little reason to think that he is well stocked with ideas that are to be the matter of his future knowledge. He gets ideas gradually; and though the ideas of obvious and familiar qualities imprint themselves before the memory begins to keep a record of when or how, ideas of unusual qualities are different. Some of them come so late that most people can remember when they first had them. And if we had reason to, we could arrange for child to be brought up in such a way as to have very few ideas, even ordinary ones, until he had grown to manhood. In actuality children are born into the world surrounded by bodies that perpetually affect them so as to imprint on their minds a variety of ideas: light and colours are busy everywhere, as long as the eyes are open; sounds and some tangible qualities engage the senses appropriate to them, and force an entrance into the mind. But I think you’ll agree that if a child were kept in a place where he never saw any colour but black and white till he was a man, he would have no ideas of scarlet or green—any more than a person has an idea of the taste of oysters or of pineapples if he has never actually tasted either.

7. How many simple ideas a person has depends ·for ideas of sensation· on what variety there is among the external objects that he perceives, and ·for ideas of reflection· on how much he reflects on the workings of his own mind. ·The focussed intensity of the reflection is relevant, because·: someone who contemplates the operations of his mind can’t help having plain and clear ideas of them, he won’t have clear and distinct ideas of all the operations of his mind and everything that happens in them unless he turns his thoughts that way and considers them attentively; any more than he can have ideas of all the details of a landscape painting, or of the parts and motions of a clock, if he doesn’t look at it and focus his attention on all the parts of it. The picture or clock may be so placed that he encounters them every day, but he’ll have only a confused idea of all the parts they are made up of, until he applies himself with attention to consider each part separately.

8. That’s why most children don’t get ideas of the operations of their own minds until quite late, and why some people never acquire any very clear or perfect ideas of most of their mental operations. Their mental operations are there all the time, like floating visions; but until the understanding turns inward upon itself, reflects on them, and makes them the objects of its own thoughts, they won’t make deep enough impressions to leave in the person’s mind clear, distinct, lasting ideas. Children enter the world surrounded by new things that constantly attract their senses, beckoning to a mind that is eager to notice new things and apt to be delighted with the variety of changing objects. So the first years are usually spent in looking outwards ·at the surroundings·; and so people grow up constantly attending to outward sensation, reflecting very little on what happens within them till they come to be of riper years—and some not even then.

19

Essay II John Locke i: Ideas and their origin

9. When does a man first have any ideas? That is the same as asking: when does a man begin to perceive? For having ideas and perception are the same thing. I know that some philosophers hold that the soul [= ‘mind’; no religious implications] always thinks, and that it has the actual perception of ideas in itself constantly as long as it exists. For them, •actual thinking is as inseparable from •the soul as •actual extension is from •the body, which implies that the question ‘When do his ideas begin?’ is equivalent to ‘When does his soul begin?’. For on their view the soul and its ideas must begin to exist both at the same time. as do body and its extension [= ‘its taking up space’].

10. How does •the soul’s beginning to exist relate to •the first rudiments of organization—or to the beginnings of life—in the body? Before it, or at the same time, or later? I leave that question to be disputed by those who have thought harder about it than I have. ·But I do have a view about how •the soul’s beginning to exist relates to •its first having ideas, or at least to the view that the two must occur together because a soul can’t exist except when it has ideas·. I confess that I have one of those dull souls that doesn’t perceive itself always to contemplate ideas; and I don’t think it’s any more necessary for the soul always to think than for the body always to move. In my view, the perception of ideas is to the soul as motion is to the body—not something that •is essential to it, but something that •it sometimes does. So even if thinking is an activity that is uniquely appropriate to the soul, that doesn’t require us to suppose that the soul is always thinking, always in action. Perhaps that is a gift possessed by God, ‘who never slumbers nor sleeps’ [Psalm 121:3], but it isn’t appropriate for any finite being, or at least not to the soul of man. We know by experience that we sometimes think; and from this we validly infer that there is in us something—·some substance·—that is able to think; but whether that substance perpetually thinks or not is a question we must answer on the basis of what experience informs us. To say that ·experience is irrelevant because· actual thinking is essential to the soul and ·thus conceptually· inseparable from it, is to assume the very thing that is in question. Such a claim needs to be supported by arguments, unless the claim is a self-evident proposition—and I don’t think anyone will contend that The soul always thinks is self-evident. [The section continues with mockery of people who purport to prove something by assuming it among the premises of their argument; and with a reply to a critic who, misunderstanding something in the first edition of the Essay, had accused Locke of thinking that when you are asleep your soul doesn’t exist.]

11. I grant that the soul in a waking man is never without thought, because that’s what it is to be awake. But I suspect that in sleeping without dreaming, the whole man is asleep—his mind as well as his body—so that in that state no thought is occurring. If the soul thinks in a sleeping man without being conscious of it, I ask whether during such thinking •the soul has any pleasure or pain, or any ability to be happy or miserable? I am sure •the man does not, any more than •the bed he lies on has pleasure or pain. For to be happy or miserable without being conscious of it seems to me utterly inconsistent and impossible. If you say that •the soul might be in any of those states while the body is sleeping, and •the unsleeping man have no consciousness of them, I reply: In that case Socrates asleep and Socrates awake are not the same person, but two persons. [Locke elaborates this in the remainder of section 11 and on through 12, relying on a view of his about personal identity that he’ll develop more clearly and at greater length in xxvii.]

20

Essay II John Locke i: Ideas and their origin

13. Thus, I think, every drowsy nod shakes the doctrine of those who teach that the soul is always thinking! Anyway, those who do at some time sleep without dreaming can never be convinced that their thoughts are for four hours busy without their knowing of it; and if they are taken in the very act, waked in the middle of those sleeping thoughts, they can give no account of it.

14. It will perhaps be said that the soul thinks even in the soundest sleep but the memory doesn’t retain those thoughts. ·This is utterly implausible·.... Who can imagine that most men, for several hours every day of their lives, think of something of which they could remember nothing at all, even if they were asked in the middle of these thoughts? Most men, I think, pass a great part of their sleep without dreaming. I knew a man who was bred a scholar, and had a pretty good memory, who told me that he had never dreamed in his life till he had a fever at the age of twenty-five. Everyone will have acquaintances who pass most of their nights without dreaming.

15. To think often, and never to retain it so much as one moment, is a very useless sort of thinking. The soul in such a state of thinking would be little better than a looking-glass which constantly receives a variety of images but retains none of them; they disappear and vanish without leaving a trace; the looking-glass is never the better for such images, nor the soul for such thoughts. ·We might also ask why it should be that all sleeping thoughts are forgotten, given that many waking ones are remembered. Here is a possible answer to that·:

In a waking man the materials of the body are used in thinking, and the memory of thoughts is retained by the impressions that are made on the brain and the traces left there after such thinking; but in the thinking of the soul that isn’t perceived in a sleeping man, the soul thinks apart, making no use of the organs of the body and so leaving no impressions on the body and consequently no memory of such thoughts.

....I answer that whatever ideas the mind can receive and contemplate without the help of the body it can also—it is reasonable to think—retain without the help of the body too. If not, then the soul gets little advantage by thinking. If •it has no memory of its own thoughts; if •it can’t lay them up for its own use, and be able to recall them at need; if •it can’t reflect on what is past, and make use of its former experiences, reasonings, and contemplations—then •what does it think for? Those who make the soul a thinking thing in this way don’t make it much nobler than do those (whom they condemn) who claim it to be nothing but very finely ground matter. Words written on dust that the first breath of wind wipes out, or impressions made on a heap of atoms or bodily fluids, are every bit as useful and ennobling as the thoughts of a soul that perish in thinking—thoughts that once out of sight are gone for ever and leave no memory of themselves behind them. Nature never makes excellent things for trivial uses or for no use; and it’s hardly to be conceived that our infinitely wise creator should bring it about that something as admirable as the power of thinking—the power ·of ours· that comes nearest to the excellence of his own incomprehensible being—is so idly and uselessly employed, at least a quarter of the time, that it thinks constantly without remembering any of those thoughts, without doing any good to itself or others or being any way useful to any other part of the creation. If you think about it, I doubt if you’ll find that the motion of dull and senseless matter is ever, anywhere in the universe, made so little use of and so wholly thrown away.

21

Essay II John Locke i: Ideas and their origin

[In section 16 Locke writes of thoughts that we do sometimes have in our sleep and remember after waking, pointing out that they are mostly ‘extravagant and incoherent’. He says that his present opponents, faced with this evidence, will have to say that the soul thinks better when employing the body that when thinking ‘apart’ from the body. He evidently thinks that this is an intolerable conclusion.]

[In sections 17–22 Locke continues to urge the empirical implausibility of the thesis that the soul always thinks, and the unreasonable dogmatism of those who insist on it as necessarily true whatever experience may say. Much of the content of these sections repeats things said earlier in the chapter. The discussion gradually moves over to Locke’s thesis that the soul thinks only when it has ideas to think with, and to his view about how ideas are acquired. And so the chapter circles back to where it was in section 9.]

23. When does a man begin to have any ideas? I think the true answer is: when he first has some sensation. Since there appear not to be any ideas in the mind before the senses have conveyed any in, I think that ideas in the understanding arise at the same time as sensation. Sensation is •an impression or motion made in some part of the body that produces •some perception in the understanding. It is about these impressions made on our senses by outward objects that the mind seems first to employ itself in such operations as we call perception, remembering, consideration, reasoning, etc.

24. In time the mind comes to reflect on its own dealing with the ideas acquired from sensation, and thereby stores up a new set of ideas that I call ideas of reflection.... The first capacity of human intellect is that the mind is fitted to receive the impressions made on it, either through the senses by outward objects, or by its own operations when it reflects on them. This is the first step a man makes towards the discovery of anything, and the basis on which to build all the notions he will ever have naturally in this world. All those sublime thoughts that tower above the clouds and reach as high as heaven itself take off from here....

25. In the getting of ideas the understanding is merely passive. It has no control over whether it will have these beginnings—these materials, so to speak—of knowledge. For many of the objects of our senses shove their particular ideas into our minds, whether we want them or not; and the operations of our minds won’t let us be without at least some obscure notions of them. No man can be wholly ignorant of what he does when he thinks. The understanding can no more refuse to have these simple ideas when they are offered to it, or alter them once they have been imprinted, or blot them out and make new ones itself, than a mirror can refuse, alter, or obliterate the images or ideas that the objects placed in front of it produce on its surface....

22

Essay II John Locke iii: Ideas of one sense

Chapter ii: Simple ideas

1. To get a better grasp of what our knowledge is, how it comes about, and how far it reaches, we must carefully attend to one fact about our ideas, namely that some of them are simple, and some complex.

The qualities that affect our senses are intimately united and blended in the things themselves, but it is obvious that the ideas they produce in the mind enter (via the senses) simple and unmixed. A single sense will often take in different ideas from one object at one time—as when a man sees motion and colour together, or the hand feels softness and warmth in a single piece of wax—and yet the simple ideas that are thus brought together in a single mind are as perfectly distinct as those that come in by different senses. The •coldness and hardness a man feels in a piece of ice are as distinct ideas in the mind as the •smell and whiteness of a lily, or as the •taste of sugar and smell of a rose. And nothing can be plainer to a man than the clear and distinct perception he has of those simple ideas, each of which contains nothing but one uniform appearance or conception in the mind, and is not distinguishable into different ideas.

2. These simple ideas, which are the materials of all our knowledge, are suggested and supplied to the mind only by sensation and reflection. Once the understanding has been stocked with these simple ideas, it is able to repeat, compare, and unite them, to an almost infinite variety, and so can make new complex ideas as it will. But no-one, however quick and clever, can invent one new simple idea that wasn’t taken in by one of those two ways. Nor can any force of the understanding destroy those that are there. Man’s power over this little world of his own understanding is much like his power over the great world of visible things, where he can only compound and divide the materials that he finds available to him, and can’t do anything towards making the least particle of new matter, or destroying one atom of what already exists....

3. God could have made a creature with organs different from ours, and more ways than our five senses to give the understanding input from bodily things. But I don’t think any of us could imagine any qualities through which bodies could come to our attention other than sounds, tastes, smells, and visible and tangible qualities. Had mankind been made with only four senses, the qualities that are now the objects of the fifth sense would have been as far from our notice, imagination, and conception as now any belonging to a sixth, seventh, or eighth sense can possibly be. (Actually, I think that perhaps we do have six senses; but I have been following the usual count, which is five; it makes no difference to my present line of thought.) Are there creatures in some other parts of this vast and stupendous universe who have more senses than we do? Perhaps. If you consider the immensity of this structure, and the great variety that is to be found in our little part of it, you may be inclined to think that there are somewhere different intelligent beings whose capacities are as unknown to you as are the senses or understanding of a man to a worm shut up in one drawer of a desk. Such variety and excellence would be suitable to the wisdom and power of our maker.

23

Essay II John Locke iv: Solidity

Chapter iii: Ideas of one sense

1. We shall get a better grasp of the ideas we receive from sensation if we classify them according to their different ways of getting into our minds.

First, some come into our minds by one sense only.

Secondly, others enter the mind by more senses than one.

Thirdly, yet others are had from reflection only.

Fourthly, some are suggested to the mind by all the ways of sensation and reflection.

We shall consider them separately, under these headings.

First, some ideas are admitted through only one sense, which is specially adapted to receive them. Thus •light and colours come in only by the eyes, all kinds of •noises, sounds, and tones only by the ears; the various •tastes and •smells by the nose and palate. If these organs, or the nerves that are the channels along which they communicate with the brain, become disordered so that they don’t perform their functions, the associated ideas have no door through which to enter, no other way to bring themselves into view and be perceived by the understanding.

The main ones belonging to touch are •heat and cold, and •solidity. Most of the others have to do with perceptible •texture, like smooth and rough, or with more or less firm •hanging together of the parts, like hard and soft, tough and brittle.

2. I needn’t enumerate all the simple ideas belonging to each sense. Indeed, I can’t do so because there are many more of them than we have names for. Kinds of smell are at least as numerous as kinds of bodies in the world, and few of them have names. We use ‘sweet’ and ‘stinking’ for them, but this amounts to little more than calling them pleasing or displeasing; the smell of a rose differs greatly from that of a violet, though both are sweet. [Similarly—Locke goes on to say—with tastes, and with colours and sounds.] In my account of simple ideas, therefore, I shall pick out only a few—mainly ones that are most important for my over-all enquiry. I shall also discuss some that tend to be overlooked, though they are very frequently ingredients in our complex ideas. I think this is the case with solidity, which is my next topic.

Chapter iv: Solidity

1. We receive the idea of solidity by the sense of touch. It arises from our experience of a body’s resisting the entrance of any other body into the place it occupies. There is no idea that we receive more constantly from sensation than solidity. Whether moving or at rest, we always feel something under us that supports us and stops us from sinking further

24

Essay II John Locke iv: Solidity

downwards; and we have daily experience of how, when holding a body between our two hands, the body absolutely prevents the hands from touching one another. My name for the property whereby one body blocks two others from touching is solidity. (Mathematicians use that term in a different sense, but mine is close enough to ordinary usage to be acceptable. If you prefer to call the property impenetrability, go ahead; but I prefer solidity for two reasons. •It is close to common speech. •The term ‘impenetrability’ seems to refer not to the property itself but to a consequence of it, and a negative one at that; whereas ‘solidity’ means something positive and points to the property itself, not a mere consequence of it.) Solidity seems to be the idea that is most intimately connected with and essential to body. senses notice it only in masses of matter that are big enough to cause a sensation in us; but once the mind has acquired this idea from such large bodies, it traces the idea further and considers it (as well as shape) in the minutest particle of matter that can exist. ·Not only can we not imagine matter without solidity, but· we cannot imagine solidity to exist anywhere except in matter.

2. Solidity is the idea [here = ‘quality’] of body whereby we conceive body to fill space. The idea of filling of space is this: we imagine a space taken up by a solid substance which we conceive it to possess in such a way that all other solid substances are excluded from it....

3. This resistance whereby a body keeps other bodies out of its space is so great that no force, however great, can overcome it. All the bodies in the world, pressing a drop of water on all sides, can never overcome its resistance until it is moved out of their way. This distinguishes our idea of solidity both from (a) pure space, which is not capable of resistance or motion, and from (b) the ordinary idea of hardness. ·I shall deal with (a) now, and with (b) in the next section. My target in (a) is Descartes, who held that whatever is extended is material, so that vacuum—understood as something extended and immaterial—is conceptually impossible. I shall discuss this at length in xiii, merely sketching my case against it here·. We can conceive two bodies at a distance as being able to meet and touch one another, without touching or displacing any other solid thing. This, I think, gives us a clear idea of space without solidity. Can we not have the idea of one single body moving without any other immediately taking its place? Clearly we can, for •the idea of motion in one body doesn’t include •the idea of motion in another—any more than •the idea of squareness in one body includes •the idea of squareness in another! I’m not asking whether in the actual state of the world it is physically possible for one body to move while no others do; answering this either way would be taking a side on the debate over whether there is a vacuum. All I am asking is whether we can have the idea of one body moving while no others do; and I think everyone will answer that we can. If so, then the place the body leaves gives us the idea of pure space without solidity, into which any other body can enter without being resisted and without displacing anything. If it is the case that when the piston in a pump is pulled up, other matter has to take its place, that comes from the world’s being full, not from the mere ideas of space and solidity.... The very fact that people argue about whether there actually is a vacuum shows that they have ideas of space without a body.

4. In contrast to solidity,....hardness consists in a firm cohesion of the parts of a mass of matter that is large enough to be perceptible, so that the whole thing doesn’t easily change its shape. Indeed, we call things ‘hard’ or ‘soft’ only in relation to the constitutions of our own bodies: we usually

25

Essay II John Locke iv: Solidity

call a thing ‘hard’ if it will cause us pain sooner than change its shape by the pressure of any part of our bodies; and ‘soft’ if an easy and unpainful touch by our bodies can make it change its shape.

The difference between hard and soft has nothing to do with solidity: the hardest stone isn’t the least bit more solid than water. The flat sides of two pieces of marble will more easily approach each other when there is only water between them than when there is a diamond between them; but that is not because the parts of the diamond are more solid than those of water. Rather, it is because the parts of the water, being more easily separable from each other, can easily slide out of the way as the pieces of marble approach. If they could be kept from moving aside in that way, they would—just as much as the diamond—for ever stop these two pieces of marble.... If you think nothing but hard bodies can keep your hands from approaching one another, try that out with the air enclosed in a football. [Locke then describes an experiment confirming what he has been saying.]

5. This idea of solidity marks off the extension of body from the extension of space. •The extension of body is just the cohesion [= ‘holding together’] or continuity of

solid, separable, movable parts;

and •the extension of space is the continuity

of unsolid, inseparable, and immovable parts.

It’s also because bodies are solid that they can bang into one another, resist one another, and change their shapes. Many of us think we have clear and distinct ideas, and that we can think of •pure space, without anything in it that resists or is pushed around by body. idea of the distance between the opposite parts of a concave surface is just as clear without as with the idea of solid parts between. And we also think we have an idea of •something that fills space, and can bump other bodies around or be bumped by them. If there are others who don’t have these two ideas distinct ·from one another· but think they are just one idea, I don’t know how to talk with them, because they and I have the same idea under different names or different ideas under the same name....

6. If anyone asks me what solidity is, I send him to his senses to be informed. Let him put a flint or a football between his hands and then try to make the palms meet, and he’ll know. If he isn’t satisfied with this explanation of what •solidity is, I promise to tell him what it is when he tells me what •thinking is, or explains to me what •extension or •motion is—a seemingly easier task. The simple ideas we have are such as experience teaches to us. If we try to go further than that, and to make them clearer in our minds ·by giving verbal definitions·, we shall have no more success than we would if we tried to tell a blind man what light and colours are, talking him into having ideas of them. I shall explain why this is so later on.

26

Essay II John Locke vii: Ideas of sensation and reflection

Chapter v: Simple ideas of different senses

The ideas we get by more than one sense are of space, or extension, shape, rest, and motion; for these are perceivable by sight and touch. And we can receive and convey into our minds the ideas of bodies’ extension, shape, motion, and rest both by seeing and feeling. I shall have more to say about these later.

Chapter vi: Simple ideas of reflection

1. After receiving ideas from outside, the mind looks in upon itself and observes its own dealings with the ideas it already has, and that gives it further ideas that are as fit to have a role in its thinking as any of those it received from outward things.

2. The main things the mind does, encountered so often that everyone who wants to can find them in himself, are

perception or thinking, and

volition or willing.

The power of thinking is called the understanding, and the power of volition is called the will; and these two powers or abilities in the mind are called ‘faculties’. I shall later discuss some of the modes [= ‘special kinds’] of these simple ideas of reflection, such as remembrance, discerning, reasoning, judging, knowledge, faith.

Chapter vii: Simple ideas of both sensation and reflection

1. Some other simple ideas convey themselves into the mind by all the ways of sensation and reflection—namely

pleasure or delight, and its opposite:

pain or uneasiness

power

existence

unity.

2. Nearly every other idea, whether of sensation or reflection, is accompanied by either delight or uneasiness. And almost any state of our senses caused from outside ourselves, and any thought of our mind within, can produce pleasure or pain in us. By the terms ‘pleasure’ and ‘pain’ I signify whatever delights or displeases us, whether it arises from the

27

Essay II John Locke vii: Ideas of sensation and reflection

thoughts of our minds or anything operating on our bodies. For whether we call it ‘satisfaction’, ‘delight’, ‘pleasure’, ‘happiness’, etc. on the one side; or ‘uneasiness’, ‘trouble’, ‘pain’, ‘torment’, ‘anguish’, ‘misery’, etc. on the other; they are merely different degrees of the same thing, and belong to the ideas of pleasure and pain, delight or uneasiness, these being the names I shall most commonly use for those two sorts of ideas.

3. The infinite wise author of our being has given us •the power to move or not move certain parts of our bodies, and through those movements to move other neighbouring bodies. And he has also given to our mind •a power often to choose which of its ideas it will think of, and which line of enquiry to pursue with consideration and attention. That is why he—·God·—has seen fit to accompany various thoughts and various sensations with a perception of delight. If delight were wholly separated from all our outward sensations and inward thoughts, we would have no reason to prefer one thought or action to another, prefer negligence to attention, or prefer movement to rest. And so we would neither stir our bodies nor employ our minds, but let our thoughts drift along without direction or design.... A man in that state, however equipped with understanding and will, would be a very idle, inactive creature, and pass his time in a lazy, lethargic dream....

4. Pain is as effective as pleasure in making us active, because we will work as hard to avoid pain as to get pleasure. It is interesting to note that pain is often produced by the same objects and ideas as produce pleasure in us.... Heat is very agreeable to us in one degree, but becomes extraordinarily painful when the temperature goes up a little. And the most pleasant of all perceptible things, light itself, causes a very painful sensation if its intensity is too great for our eyes. This shows the wisdom of our maker: when any object acts so intensely on our sense organs that it threatens to damage their delicate structures, pain warns us to withdraw before the organ is so damaged as to become useless. There is evidence that this is what pain is for. Although great light is insufferable to our eyes, yet the highest degree of darkness does them no harm and isn’t accompanied by pain. In contrast with that: we are given pain by excess of cold as well as of heat, because the two extremes are equally destructive to the bodily condition that is necessary for the preservation of life and the proper functioning of the body. It is the condition of having a moderate degree of warmth—or, if you will, a motion of the imperceptible parts of our bodies that is not too fast and not too slow.

[Section 5 suggests another reason, a theological one, why ‘God has scattered up and down various levels of pleasure and pain in all the things that surround and affect us’. Section 6 gives a theological reason for discussing this.]

7. Existence and unity are two other ideas that are suggested to the understanding by every object outside us and every idea within. When ideas are in our minds, we consider them as being actually there, i.e. as existing; and whatever we can consider as one thing, whether a real being or an idea, suggests to the understanding the idea of unity, ·i.e. oneness·.

8. Power is another simple idea that we receive from sensation and reflection. For we get the idea of power in two ways: •by observing in ourselves that we can at pleasure move various parts of our bodies that were at rest, and •by our constantly observing through our senses the effects that natural bodies can have on one another.

9. Another idea that is suggested by our senses but is more constantly offered to us by what happens in our minds, is

28

Essay II John Locke viii: More about simple ideas

the idea of succession. If we look into ourselves and reflect on what we observe there, we’ll find our ideas following one another with no interruptions throughout our waking hours.

10. I think that these are all—or anyway the most important—of the mind’s simple ideas, out of which all its other knowledge is made. They are all received through sensation and reflection.

Don’t think that sensation and reflection are too narrow to supply all the materials of the capacious mind of man, which takes its flight beyond the stars, roaming beyond the world of matter out into incomprehensible empty space. It won’t seem so strange to think that these few simple ideas suffice for the quickest thought, or largest mental capacity, if we consider how many words we can make by putting together various selections from twenty-four letters, or if we consider how the mathematicians can get an inexhaustible and truly infinite stock of material out of just one of the simple ideas I have mentioned, namely number. [In fact Locke hasn’t mentioned it yet. It will be the topic of xvi.]

Chapter viii: Some further points about our simple ideas

1. If something in nature can so affect the mind as to cause some perception in it, that perception will present itself to the mind as a positive idea, even if it is caused by a negative feature of the object.

2. Thus the ideas of heat and cold, light and darkness, white and black, motion and rest, are equally clear and positive ideas in the mind; though perhaps some of the causes producing them are mere privations [= ‘absences’, ‘negativenesses’] in the things from which our senses derive those ideas. Looking into those causes is an enquiry that belongs not •to the idea as it is in the understanding but •to the nature of the things existing outside us. These are two very different things, and we should be careful to distinguish them. It is one thing to perceive and know the idea of white or black, and quite another to examine what kind surface texture is needed to make an object appear white or black.

[In section 3 Locke develops this point a little further. In section 4 he offers a suggestion about why a negative cause sometimes ‘produces a positive idea’.]

5. I won’t try to settle here whether this suggestion is right. ·As for my point about the idea itself, as distinct from its cause·, I appeal to everyone’s own experience: the shadow of a man consists of nothing but the absence of light, but doesn’t it cause in an observer as clear and positive an idea as does the man whose shadow it is, even though he is bathed in sunshine? And the picture of a shadow is a positive thing. We do have negative names that stand directly not for positive ideas but for their absence. For example ‘insipid’, ‘silence’, ‘nothing’, and their like denote positive ideas (taste, sound, being) together with a signification of their absence.

6. So a person can be truly said to see darkness.... The causes I have here assigned for certain positive ideas are

29

Essay II John Locke viii: More about simple ideas

privative [= ‘negative’] according to the common opinion, and so I have called them; but really it is hard to be sure whether there really are any ideas from a privative cause, until we have settled whether rest is any more a privation than motion is.

7. To reveal the nature of our ideas better, and to talk about them intelligibly, it will be convenient to distinguish them •as they are ideas or perceptions in our minds, and •as they are states of matter in the bodies that cause such perceptions in us. That may save us from the belief (which is perhaps the common opinion) that the ideas are exactly the images and resemblances of something inherent in the object. ·That belief is quite wrong·. Most ideas of sensation are (in the mind) no more like a thing existing outside us than the names that stand for them are like the ideas themselves.

8. Whatever the mind perceives in itself—whatever is the immediate object of perception, thought, or understanding—I call an idea; and the power to produce an idea in our mind I call a quality of the thing that has that power. Thus a snow-ball having the power to produce in us the ideas of white, cold, and round, the powers to produce those ideas in us, as they are in the snow-ball, I call qualities; and as they are sensations or perceptions in our understandings, I call them ideas. If I sometimes speak of ‘ideas’ as in the things themselves, please understand me to mean to be talking about the qualities in the objects that produce them in us.

9. Qualities thus considered in bodies are of two kinds. First, there are those that are utterly inseparable from the body, whatever state it is in. Qualities of this kind are the ones that a body doesn’t lose, however much it alters, whatever force is used on it, however finely it is divided. Take a grain of wheat, divide it into two parts, each part has still solidity, extension, shape, and mobility; divide it again, and it still retains those qualities; go on dividing it until the parts become imperceptible, each part must still retain all those qualities.... I call them original or primary qualities of body, which I think we may observe to produce simple ideas in us, viz. solidity, extension, shape, motion or rest, and number.

10. Secondly, there are qualities that are, in the objects themselves, really nothing but powers to produce various sensations in us by their primary qualities, i.e. by the size, shape, texture, and motion of their imperceptible parts. Examples of these are colours, sounds, tastes, and so on. I call these secondary qualities. To these we can add a third sort, an example of which is the power of fire to change the colour or consistency of wax and clay. This would ordinarily be said to be only a power in ·rather than a quality of· the object; but it is just as much a real quality as the powers that I have called ‘secondary qualities’. (I call them ‘qualities’ so as to comply with the common way of speaking, and add ‘secondary’ to mark them off from the rest.) The primary qualities of fire—that is, the size, texture, and motion of its minute parts—give it a power to affect wax and clay etc.; and those same primary qualities give it a power to produce in me a sensation of warmth or burning; if the latter is a quality in the fire, why not the former also?

11. The next question is: How do bodies produce ideas in us? Obviously they do it by impact; we can’t conceive bodies to operate in any way but that.

12. External objects are not united [= ‘directly connected’] to our mind when they produce ideas in it, and yet we do somehow perceive qualities in the objects. Clearly there has to be some motion that ·goes from the object to our sense-organs, and· from there is continued by our nerves or our animal spirits to the brains or the seat of sensation, there to produce in our mind the particular ideas

30

Essay II John Locke viii: More about simple ideas

we have of them. [Locke held the then-common view that human physiology involves ‘animal spirits’. These constitute the body’s hydraulic system (Bernard Williams’s phrase)—an extremely finely divided fluid that transmits pressures through tiny cracks and tunnels.] Since the extension, shape, number, and motion of visible bodies can be seen from a distance, it is evident that some bodies that are too small to be seen individually must travel from those bodies across to the eyes, and thereby convey to the brain some motion that produces in us these ideas that we have of them.

13. We may conceive that the ideas of secondary qualities are also produced by the operation of insensible particles on our senses. Plainly there are plenty of bodies that are so small that we can’t, by any of our senses, discover the size, shape, or motion of any one of them taken singly. The particles of the air and water are examples of this, and there are others still smaller—perhaps as much smaller than particles of air and water as the latter are smaller than peas or hail-stones. Let us suppose in the meantime that the different motions and shapes, sizes and number of such particles, affecting our various sense-organs, produce in us the different sensations that we have of the colours and smells of bodies.... It is no more impossible to conceive that God should attach such ideas to motions that in no way resemble them than it is that he should attach the idea [= ‘feeling’] of pain to the motion of a piece of steel dividing our flesh, which in no way resembles the pain.

14. What I have said about colours and smells applies equally to tastes and sounds, and other such sensible qualities. Whatever reality we mistakenly attribute to them, they are really nothing in the objects themselves but powers to produce various sensations in us. These powers depend, as I have said, on those primary qualities, namely size, shape, texture, and motion of parts.

15. From this we can easily infer that the ideas of the primary qualities of bodies resemble them, and their patterns really do exist in the bodies themselves; but the ideas produced in us by secondary qualities don’t resemble them at all. There is nothing like our ideas ·of secondary qualities· existing in the bodies themselves. All they are in the bodies is a power to produce those sensations in us. What is sweet, blue, or warm in idea is nothing but the particular size, shape, and motion of the imperceptible parts in the bodies that we call ‘sweet’, ‘blue’, or ‘warm’.

16. Flame is called ‘hot’ and ‘light’; snow ‘white’ and ‘cold’; and manna ‘white’ and ‘sweet’—all from the ideas they produce in us. [We know that Locke sometimes calls qualities ‘ideas’, but that seems not to be enough to explain the oddity of the next sentence down to its first comma. The passage as given here is almost verbatim Locke; all of the oddity is there in what he wrote.] Those qualities are commonly thought to be the same in those bodies as those ideas are in us, the one perfectly resembling the other; and most people would think it weird to deny this. But think about this: a fire at one distance produces in us the sensation of •warmth, and when we come closer it produces in us the very different sensation of •pain; what reason can you give for saying that the idea of warmth that was produced in you by the fire is actually in the fire, without also saying that the idea of pain that the same fire produced in you in the same way is in the fire? Why are whiteness and coldness in snow, and pain not, when it produces each idea in us, and can do so only through the size, shape, number, and motion of its solid parts?

17. The particular size, number, shape, and motion of the parts of fire or snow are really in them, whether or not anyone’s senses perceive them. So they may be called real

31

Essay II John Locke viii: More about simple ideas

qualities, because they really exist in those bodies; but light, heat, whiteness or coldness are no more really in them than sickness or pain is in manna. Take away the sensation of them—

let the eyes not see light or colours, or the ears hear sounds; let the palate not taste, or the nose smell—

and all colours, tastes, odours, and sounds vanish and cease, and are reduced to their causes, i.e. size, shape, and motion of parts.

18. A big enough piece of manna can produce in us the idea of a round or square shape, and, by being moved, the idea of motion. This idea of motion represents motion as it really is in the moving manna; a circle or square is the same •in idea as •in existence—the same •in the mind as •in the manna—and this motion and shape really are in the manna, whether or not we notice them. Everybody agrees with this. On the other hand, manna by virtue of the size, shape, and motion of its parts has a power to produce in us the sensations of sickness and sometimes of acute pains. And everyone agrees also that •these ideas of sickness and pain are not in the manna, are only effects of its operations on us, and are nowhere when we don’t feel them. Yet it is hard to get people to agree that •sweetness and whiteness aren’t really in manna either, and are also merely the effects of the operations of manna by the motion, size, and shape of its particles on the eyes and palate.... It would be hard for them to explain why the •ideas produced by the eyes and palate should be thought to be really in the manna, while •those produced by the stomach and guts are not; or why •the pain and sickness caused by the manna should be thought to be nowhere when they aren’t felt, while •the sweetness and whiteness of it should be thought to exist in the manna even when they aren’t seen or tasted.

19. Consider the red and white colours in porphyry. Prevent light from reaching the stone, and its colours vanish, it no longer produces any such ideas in us; when light returns, it produces these appearances in us again. Can anyone think that any real alterations are made in the porphyry by the presence or absence of light; and that those ideas of whiteness and redness are really in porphyry in the light, when it obviously has no colour in the dark? The porphyry has at every time a configuration of particles that is apt to produce in us the idea of redness when rays of light rebound from some parts of that hard stone, and to produce the idea of whiteness when the rays rebound from some other parts; but at no time are whiteness or redness in the stone.

20. Pound an almond, and the clear white colour will be altered into a dirty one, and the sweet taste into an oily one. What real alteration can the beating of the pestle make in any body other than an alteration of the texture of it?

21. We are now in a position to explain how it can happen that the same water, at the same time, produces the idea of cold by one hand and of heat by the other; whereas the same water couldn’t possibly be at once hot and cold if those ideas were really in it. If we imagine warmth in our hands to be nothing but a certain sort and degree of motion in the minute particles of our nerves or animal spirits, we can understand how it is possible for the same water at the same time to produce the sensations of heat in one hand and of cold in the other (which shape never does; something never feels square to one hand and spherical to the other). If the sensation of heat and cold is nothing but the increase or lessening of the motion of the minute parts of our bodies, caused by the corpuscles of some other body, we can easily understand that if motion is greater in one hand than in the other, and the two hands come into contact with a body that

32

Essay II John Locke viii: More about simple ideas

is intermediate between them in temperature, the particles in one hand will be slowed down while those of the other will speed up, thus causing different sensations.

22. In what I have been saying I have gone a little further than I intended into physical enquiries. [That is, into questions about the biology/psychology of ideas, questions about what actually happens in the world when ideas of a certain kind occur.] But I had to throw a little light on the nature of sensation, and to provide a firm grasp of how qualities in bodies differ from the ideas they produce in the mind; for without this I couldn’t write intelligibly about ideas. I hope I shall be pardoned this little detour into natural science....

23. So the qualities that are in bodies are of three sorts. First, the size, shape, number, position, and motion or rest of their solid parts; those are in them, whether or not we perceive them; and when they are big enough for us to perceive them they give us our idea of what kind of thing it is—as clearly happens with artifacts. ·For example, we recognize a clock or a coach from how its visible parts are assembled, without need for guesswork about its submicroscopic features·. I call these primary qualities.

Secondly, the power that a body has, by reason of its imperceptible primary qualities, to operate in a special way on any of our senses, thereby producing in us the different ideas of various colours, sounds, smells, tastes, etc. These are usually called sensible qualities. ·I call them secondary qualities·.

Thirdly, the power that a body has, by virtue of the particular set-up of its primary qualities, to change the size, shape, texture or motion of another body so as to make the latter operate on our senses differently from how it did before. Thus the sun has a power to make wax white, and fire to make lead fluid. These are usually called powers.

The first of these, I repeat, may be properly called real, original, or primary qualities, because they are in the things themselves, whether or not they are perceived. It is upon different modifications of them that the secondary qualities depend. [A ‘modification’ of a quality is a special case of it, a quality that involves it and more. Squareness is a modification of shapedness, which is a modification of extendedness.]

The other two are only powers to act differently on other things, which powers result from the different modifications of those primary qualities.

24. But though the two latter sorts of qualities are merely powers, nothing else, one of the two sorts are generally thought of as something else. The second sort, namely the powers to produce ideas in us by our senses, are looked on as real qualities in the things thus affecting us. The third sort are regarded as mere powers: when we consider the sun in relation to wax that it melts or blanches, we look on the wax’s whiteness and softness not as qualities in the sun but as effects produced by powers in the sun. ·This correct understanding of the third sort of qualities is also right for the second sort·. If rightly considered, the qualities of light and warmth that are perceptions in me when I am warmed or lit up by the sun are no more in the sun than are the changes made in the wax when it is blanched or melted....

[Section 25 is a fairly long and somewhat complex explanation of why people are apt to think correctly about powers and incorrectly about secondary qualities. Section 26 winds up the chapter without adding anything except the suggestion that the second sort of qualities ‘may be called secondary qualities, immediately perceivable’, and the third sort ‘secondary qualities, mediately perceivable’.]

33

Essay II John Locke ix: Perception

Chapter ix: Perception

1. Just as perception is the mind’s first way of engaging with ideas, ·the idea of· it is the first and simplest idea we have from reflection. Some call it thinking, ·but that is a misnomer, because· in correct English ‘thinking’ stands only for operations on ideas in which the mind is active, coming to bear on something with some degree of voluntary attention. In bare naked perception, on the other hand, the mind is mostly passive, perceiving only what it can’t avoid perceiving.

2. What is perception? you’ll know the answer to that better by reflecting on what you do when you see, hear, feel, etc. or think, than by listening to anything I say. Whoever reflects on what happens in his own mind can’t miss it; and if he doesn’t reflect, all the words in the world can’t make him have any notion of it.

3. This much is certain: whatever alterations occur in the body, if they don’t reach the mind there is no perception. Whatever impressions are made on the •outward parts, if they aren’t taken notice of •within there is no perception. Fire may burn our bodies with no other effect than it makes on a piece of wood, unless the motion is continued to the brain, and there the sense of heat, or idea of pain, is produced in the mind. In that consists actual perception.

4. Your own experience will tell you that quite often your mind, while intently focussed on some things and on the ideas they involve, takes no notice of the effects that other things are having on the organ of hearing, although these effects are just like ones that ordinarily produce the idea of sound. There may be a sufficient impact on the organ, but because it isn’t observed by the mind no perception ensues. The motion that ordinarily produces the idea of sound is made in the ear, yet no sound is heard. In this case the lack of sensation doesn’t come from any defect in your organ of hearing, or from your ears’ being less affected than at other times when you do hear. Rather, it is that the physical effects aren’t taken notice of in the understanding, and so they don’t imprint any idea on the mind, and so they cause no sensation. Whenever there is sense or perception, some idea is actually produced and present in the understanding.

5. So I am sure that children, by the exercise of their senses on objects that affect them in the womb, receive a few ideas before they are born.... If I may risk a guess on a matter that isn’t very open to investigation, I think the ideas of hunger and warmth are among them—probably among the first that children have, and hardly ever part with.

6. But though we can reasonably suppose that children receive some ideas before they are born, these •simple ideas are nothing like the •innate principles that I have rejected. •The former come from states that the child’s body is in, or events that its body undergoes, while it is in the womb; which means that they depend on something exterior to the mind. In their way of being produced they differ from other sense-based ideas only in that they occur earlier. As against this, •innate principles are supposed to be of an entirely different sort—not coming into the mind through any particular events in the body, but original characters stamped onto it from the outset.

7. As there are some ideas—·like the feelings of hunger and warmth·—that we can reasonably suppose to be introduced into the minds of children in the womb, reflecting the necessities of their life in that situation, so the first ideas that

34

Essay II John Locke ix: Perception

are imprinted on them after they are born are the sensible qualities that first impinge on them. Light is a powerful example. Newly born children always turn their eyes in the direction from which the light comes, which is some evidence of how greedy the mind is to get as many ideas as it can, so long as they aren’t accompanied by pain. But children’s circumstances vary, and so the order in which they acquire ideas varies too; and this isn’t something we have much need to enquire into.

8. Speaking of adults now: the ideas we receive by sensation are often altered by judgment without our noticing it. When we see a round uniformly coloured globe—say of gold or alabaster or polished coal—it is certain that the idea it imprints on our mind is of a flat circle variously shadowed, with various degrees of light and brightness coming to our eyes. But we know how convex bodies customarily appear to us, how the reflections of light are altered by the shapes of bodies; and so our judgment acquires a habit of immediately altering the appearances into their causes. Faced with something that is really a variety of shadow or colour, it infers what the shape is; takes that variety to be a mark of that shape; and forms for itself the perception of a convex figure and a uniform colour, although the idea we receive is only a plane variously coloured, as is evident in painting.

A propos of that, I shall here insert a problem that was put to me by the learned and worthy Mr. Molineux....:

Suppose a man born blind, now adult, who has learned how to distinguish by touch between a cube and a sphere of the same metal and about the same size, so that he can tell when he handles them which is the cube and which the sphere. Now suppose the cube and sphere to be placed on a table, and the blind man be made to see. Can he by his sight, before touching them, tell which is the globe, which the cube?

To this Mr Molineux answers No. For though the man has obtained the experience of how a globe affects his ·sense of· touch and how a cube does, he still has no experience telling him that something that affects his touch thus must affect his sight so. I agree.... I leave this with you, to prompt you to consider how much you owe to experience, learning, and acquired notions, where you have thought you hadn’t the least help from them! I especially want to include this question here because Mr Molyneux tells me that when ·the first edition of· my book appeared he proposed this question to various very able men, and found hardly any that gave what he thinks is the right answer until he convinced them of it by giving reasons.

9. This ·mistake· doesn’t happen much, I think, with ideas other than those received by sight. ·Here is why it happens with them·. Sight, which is the most comprehensive of all our senses, conveys to our minds the ideas of light and colours, which we get only from that sense; and it conveys also the very different ideas of space, shape, and motion, the variations in which bring with them changes in the appearances of light and colours; and so we become accustomed to judging one by the other. When this is done with things of which we have frequent experience, it is performed so constantly and so quickly that we take an idea formed by our judgment to be a perception of our sensation; so that the latter serves only to trigger the former, and is hardly noticed in itself. Similarly, a man who reads or hears with attention and understanding takes little notice of the letters or sounds, attending only to the ideas that they rouse up in him.

[In section 10 Locke comments on our generally not noticing that we are making such a substitution. He explains it partly

35

Essay II John Locke x: Retention

as resulting from •the speed with which the substitution is performed (‘As the mind is thought to take up no space, so its actions seem to require no time’) and from •its habitualness. He compares it with our unawareness of blinking.]

11. The faculty of perception seems to me to be what distinguishes the animal kingdom from the inferior parts of nature, ·that is, from plants·. A good many plants are capable of motion: when other bodies are applied to them they briskly alter their shapes and motions, which leads to their being called ‘sensitive plants’ because their movements somewhat resemble those that an animal makes because of some sensation that it has. But in plants it is (I suppose) all bare mechanism, produced in the same kind of way as....water produces the shortening of a rope—which is done without any sensation in the subject or any having or receiving of ideas.

12. I believe that perception occurs to some extent in animals of every sort, though it may be that in some animals the inlets that nature provides for receiving sensations are so few, and the perception they are received with is so dark and dull, that it falls far short of the sharpness and variety of sensation in other animals. Still, it is sufficient for, and wisely adapted to, the state and condition of animals of that sort. So the wisdom and goodness of the Maker plainly appear in all the parts of this stupendous structure, and at all the different levels of creatures in it.

13. Judging by an oyster’s structure, I think we can reasonably conclude that it doesn’t have as many senses—or ones as keen—as men and many other animals have; and because of its immobility it wouldn’t be better off if it did. What good would sight and hearing do to a creature that couldn’t move itself towards benefit or away from harm even if it could see them at a distance? And wouldn’t keenness of sensation be an inconvenience to an animal that must lie still, where chance has once placed it, and be washed over by whatever water—cold or warm, clean or foul—that happens to come its way?

14. Still, I can’t help thinking that oysters have some small dull perception that distinguishes their state from perfect insensibility. [Locke goes on to liken this conjectured state of an oyster to the state of an extremely old man who has lost most of his memories, and is blind, deaf, and without a sense of smell.]

15. Because perception is the first step towards knowledge, and is the inlet through which all its materials come into the mind, the following is the case. •The fewer senses any man (or other creature) has, •the fewer and duller the impressions are that his senses make; and •the duller the faculties are that he brings to bear on them, •the more remote he is from having the sort of knowledge that is to be found in some men. But there are so many different levels of this (even amongst men) that we can’t know for sure where a given species of animals stands in this respect, much less where an individual animal stands....

36

Essay II John Locke x: Retention

Chapter x: Retention

1. The next faculty of the mind by which it moves closer towards knowledge is one that I call ‘retention’—the mind’s ability to keep simple ideas it has received from sensation or reflection. This is done in two ways. In the first, the idea is kept actually in view for some time—this is called ‘contemplation’.

2. The second kind of retention is the power to revive again in our minds ideas that have come to us and then disappeared. This is memory, which is the store-house (so to speak) of our ideas. Because the narrow mind of man couldn’t keep many ideas in view and under consideration at once, it needed a repository in which to store ideas that it might want to use later on. But our ideas are nothing but actual perceptions in the mind, and cease to be anything when they aren’t perceived; so that this ‘storing of ideas in the repository of the memory’ really means only that the mind has a power in many cases to revive perceptions that it has once had, with attached to them the additional perception that it has had them before. It is in this sense that our ideas are said to be ‘in our memories’, when they are actually nowhere....

3. Attention and repetition help in fixing ideas in the memory; but the ones that at first make the deepest and most lasting impression ·are the most likely to be remembered. And they· are those that are accompanied by pleasure or pain. The great business of the senses is to alert us to what hurts the body or brings advantage to it; so nature has wisely brought it about that pain accompanies the reception of certain ideas. That does the work of thinking and reasoning in children, and acts faster than thinking in adults; and so it leads both young and old to avoid painful objects, doing this with the speed that is necessary for their preservation—and settling in the memory a caution for the future.

[In section 4 Locke discusses ideas that the mind doesn’t retain in memory—because •the idea was too brief or weak or uninteresting, or •the memory itself is weak, or •the person wasn’t paying attention, or •‘through the condition of the body, or some other fault’. The section concludes:] In all these cases ideas in the mind quickly fade, and often vanish from the understanding altogether, leaving no more signs of themselves than the shadows of clouds do in flying over fields of corn; and the mind is as empty of them as if they had never been there.

5. Thus many of the ideas that were produced very early in the minds of children....if in the future course of their lives they aren’t repeated they are quite lost, with not a glimpse of them remaining. This can be observed in those who had the bad luck to lose their sight when very young, in whom the ideas of colours having been only slightly taken notice of, and have quite worn out because they haven’t been repeated.... There seems to be a constant decay of all our ideas, even of those that are most deeply embedded in the most retentive minds, so that if they aren’t sometimes renewed by repeated exercise of the senses, or reflection on the kinds of objects that at first produced them, the print wears out, and at last there remains nothing to be seen.... The pictures drawn in our minds are laid down in fading colours, and if they aren’t sometimes refreshed they vanish and disappear. I shan’t here go into the question of how far the structure of our bodies and the constitution of our animal

37

Essay II John Locke x: Retention

spirits are concerned in this, and whether the state of the brain makes the difference ·between good memories and bad, so· that in some people the memory retains the characters drawn on it like •marble, in others like •sandstone, and in others little better than •sand. It may seem probable that the constitution of the body sometimes influences ·how well· the memory ·functions·, since we often find that a disease can strip the mind of all its ideas, and the flames of a fever can within a few days burn down to dust and confusion the images which had seemed to be as lasting as if engraved in marble.

6. But concerning the ideas themselves ·as distinct from questions about the efficacy of memory·, it is easy to see that the ideas that fix themselves best in the memory and remain clearest and longest in it are the ones that are oftenest refreshed by a frequent return of the objects or events that produce them. These include the ideas that are conveyed into the mind by more ways than one. And so it is that •ideas that are of the original qualities of bodies, namely solidity, extension, shape, motion, and rest, and •ideas ·of qualities· that almost constantly affect our bodies, such as heat and cold, and •ideas that are applicable to beings of all kind, such as existence, duration, and number, which come along with almost every object that affects our senses and every thought that occupies our minds—ideas like these are seldom quite lost except by a mind that loses all its ideas.

7. In this secondary perception, so to call it, this viewing again of ideas that are lodged in the memory, the mind is often quite active, for the appearance of those dormant pictures sometimes depends on the will. The mind often sets to work searching for some hidden idea, and turns the eye of the soul (so to speak) upon it [= upon the soul and the ideas it contains?]. But sometimes ideas start up of their own accord in our minds, and present themselves to the understanding; and very often they are aroused and tumbled out of their dark cells into daylight by turbulent and tempestuous passions, because our various states bring to our memory ideas that would otherwise have lain quiet and unnoticed.

A further point should be noted concerning ideas that are lodged in the memory and later revived by the mind. It is that not only are they not new ideas, but they are not taken to be new by the mind. On the contrary, it takes notice of them as of a former impression, and renews its acquaintance with them as with ideas it had known before....

8. In a thinking creature, memory is second in importance only to perception. It matters so much that when it is lacking all our other faculties are largely useless. In our thoughts, reasonings, and knowledge we couldn’t move beyond present objects if we didn’t have the help of our memories. This help may be defective, in either of two ways.

First, the memory can’t find the idea at all, and to that extent produces perfect ignorance. For since we can know a thing only so far as we have the idea of it, when that is gone we are in perfect ignorance ·about the thing in question·.

Secondly, the memory moves slowly, and doesn’t retrieve the stored idea quickly enough to serve the present purpose. When this happens a lot, that is stupidity; and someone who through this defect in his memory doesn’t have easy access to the ideas that really are preserved in his mind—doesn’t have them ready at hand when he needs them—is hardly better off than he would be without them ·in his ‘store’·, for they give him no service.... It is the business of the memory to provide the mind with those dormant ideas that it needs at a given moment. Having them ready at hand on all occasions is what we call ‘invention’, ‘fancy’, and mental agility.

38

Essay II John Locke xi: Discerning etc.

[In section 9 Locke writes about how men differ from one another in the strength of their memories, citing Pascal, who in his prime ‘forgot nothing of what he had done, read, or thought at any time since he reached the years of reason’. He also speculates that probably all men differ in this respect from angels. He continues:] Mr. Pascal’s memory still had the narrow limits within which human minds are confined here on earth, having a great variety of ideas only in succession and not all at once. Different grades of angels may have broader views, some of them being able to retain together, and constantly set before them as in one picture, all their past knowledge at once. This would be a great advantage to the knowledge of a thinking man; so it may be one of the ways in which the knowledge of unembodied Spirits greatly surpasses ours.

10. Various non-human animals seem to have to a great degree this capacity for laying up and retaining the ideas that are brought into the mind. To take one example out of several: when birds learn tunes, the attempts one can observe in them to get the notes right convinces me that they have perception and retain ideas in their memories, and use them as patterns. It seems to me impossible that they should try to conform their voices to notes (as they plainly do) of which they had no ideas. Admittedly, ·a sound might affect a bird’s behaviour in a purely mechanical manner, without involving anything mental, e.g. any perception. For example·, a sound might mechanically cause a certain motion of the animal spirits in the brains of those birds while the tune is actually playing; and that motion might be continued on to the muscles of the wings, so that the bird is mechanically driven away by certain noises, because this tends to its preservation. But that ·mechanistic, non-mental approach· couldn’t explain why a sound should mechanically cause a motion of the bird’s vocal organs that would reproduce the notes of a sound it had heard earlier; for such imitation couldn’t be conducive to the bird’s preservation. [Locke adds another bit of supposed evidence that in learning a tune a bird relies on its memory.]

Chapter xi: Discerning, and other operations of the mind

1. Another faculty we may take notice of in our minds is that of discerning and distinguishing ideas from one another. It isn’t enough to have a confused perception of some thing in general—·that is, taking in nothing beyond the bare fact of its being a thing·. If the mind didn’t have different perceptions of different objects and their qualities, it would be capable of very little knowledge, even if the bodies affecting us were as busy as they actually are, and the mind were continually employed in thinking. This capacity for distinguishing one thing from another is the source of the obvious and certain truth of various propositions, including some very general ones, that have been taken for innate truths. Innatists have been led to their view for want of any other explanation of why those propositions are universally accepted. ·I am

39

Essay II John Locke xi: Discerning etc.

undercutting them by providing another explanation, an alternative to the hypothesis of innate imprinting·. The acceptance of those propositions depends on the mind’s ability to discern ·or distinguish·—its ability to perceive two ideas to be the same, or to be different.....

2. I won’t go into the question of how far failures in accurately discriminating ideas from one another comes from •defects in the organs of sense, or •lack of sharpness, nimbleness or focus in the understanding, or •the way some people are apt to blunder hastily to conclusions. I merely note that this is one of the operations that the mind can observe in itself when it looks inward. It is so important to other knowledge that to the extent that this faculty is dull, or isn’t rightly used for distinguishing one thing from another, to that extent our notions are confused and our reason and judgment are disturbed or misled. Whereas •having our ideas in the memory ready at hand is having mental agility, •having them unconfused, and being able to tell one thing from another even when the difference is small, is much of what makes up exactness of judgment and clearness of reason. From this we can perhaps give some reason for the well known fact that people with a great deal of wit and prompt memories don’t always have the clearest judgment or deepest reason. •Wit lies mostly in nimbly putting one idea together with another idea that it resembles or in some other way goes with, thereby making up pleasant pictures and agreeable visions in the imagination; whereas •judgment lies quite on the other side, carefully separating from one another ideas that differ from one another, however slightly, so as not to be misled by a similarity into mistaking one thing for another. [Locke develops this contrast, saying that the appreciation of wit does not require, and indeed is inimical to, examination ‘by the severe rules of truth and good reason’.]

3. The chief aid to our distinguishing well amongst our ideas is their being clear and determinate. When they are so, we won’t be led into confusion or mistake when, as sometimes happens, the senses convey ideas from the same object differently on different occasions, and so seem to err. Sugar may taste sweet to a man when he is healthy, and bitter when he is in a fever; but the idea of bitter in his mind is as clear, and as distinct from the idea of sweet, as if he had tasted only gall. [The section continues with other examples.]

4. Comparing ideas with one with another, in respect of extent, degrees, time, place, or any other details, is another operation that the mind performs with its ideas. On it are based all the many ideas that fall under the heading relation. I shall return to them later [xxv]. [For Locke, a ‘comparison’ of one thing with another needn’t be a likening of them; often it is some other kind of considering them together.]

5. It isn’t easy to determine how far non-human animals have this capacity ·for comparing·. I imagine they don’t have it any great degree; for though they probably have various ideas that are distinct enough, yet it seems to me to be the prerogative of human understanding, when it has distinguished any ·pair of· ideas well enough to perceive them to be perfectly different and therefore to be two, to cast about and consider how and in what respects they can be compared—·that is, how they can be related to one another·. I think, therefore, that non-human animals compare their ideas only in coping with their physical environment. We are probably safe in conjecturing that they don’t at all have the other power of comparing—the one that men have, and that belongs to general ideas and is useful only in abstract reasonings.

6. The next operation we can observe the mind performing with its ideas is composition, in which the mind puts together

40

Essay II John Locke xi: Discerning etc.

several simple ideas it has received from sensation and reflection, combining them into a complex one. Under the heading ‘composition’ we may also include enlarging, in which we put together several ideas of the same kind. Thus by adding several units together, we make the idea of a dozen; and putting together the repeated ideas of yards, we make that of a mile.

7. In composition also, I suppose, lower animals come far short of man. They do take in and retain together various combinations of simple ideas. The shape, smell, and voice of a man may make up his dog’s complex idea of him, or rather are so many distinct marks by which it recognizes him; but I don’t think that the dog puts these ideas together to make a complex idea. Even where we think a non-human animal has a complex idea, perhaps it is only one simple idea that directs the animal in the knowledge of various things that it doesn’t distinguish visually as much as we imagine it does. I have been credibly informed that a bitch will nurse, play with, and be fond of young foxes, as much as of her puppies and in place of them, if only you can get them just once to suckle from her long enough for her milk to go through them. [The section adds evidence that lower animals can’t count.]

8. When children have through repeated sensations got some ideas fixed in their memories, they gradually begin to learn the use of signs. And when they acquire the skill to apply their organs of speech to producing articulate sounds, they begin to use words to signify their ideas to others. They borrow some of these verbal signs from others; but they also make some of their own, as we can observe from the new and unusual names children often give to things when they first use language.

9. So words are used to stand as outward marks of our internal ideas, which are taken from particular things; but if every particular idea that we take in had its own special name, there would be no end to names. To prevent this, the mind makes particular ideas received from particular things become general; which it does by considering them as they are in the mind—mental appearances—separate from all other existences, and from the circumstances of real existence, such as time, place, and so on. This procedure is called abstraction. In it, an idea taken from a particular thing becomes a general representative of all of the same kind, and its name becomes a general name that is applicable to any existing thing that fits that abstract idea. Such precise naked appearances in the mind, without considering •how or •from where or •in company with what others it acquired them, the understanding stores away for use as standards: it will classify real things into •sorts on the basis of their agreement with these patterns ·or standards·. The abstract ideas have names commonly attached to them, so that they also serve as patterns for applying •words, labels, to the things that they enable us to sort. Thus you observe the same colour today in chalk or snow that you yesterday saw in milk; your mind considers that appearance alone, makes it a representative of all of that kind and gives it the name ‘whiteness’; and by that sound you signify the same quality, wherever it is imagined or met with. This is how universals, whether ideas or words, are made.

10. It is doubtful that non-human animals compound their ideas much; I am sure that they have no power of abstracting at all, and that the having of general ideas is what sharply distinguishes humans from other animals, and is an excellence of which the others are in no way capable. Obviously, we see no traces in their behaviour of their using general signs ·to stand· for universal ideas; which gives us reason to think they can’t abstract, or make general ideas.

41

Essay II John Locke xi: Discerning etc.

11. Their having no use or knowledge of general words can’t be explained as resulting from their lack of appropriate vocal organs; for we find that many of the lower animals can make such sounds, and pronounce words distinctly enough, but they never mean anything general by them. And conversely, men who through some physical defect can’t utter words still manage to express their universal ideas by signs that they use instead of general words; and we see that non-human animals can’t do that. I think we may take this to be what essentially differentiates men from other animals, a difference that wholly separates them by what eventually comes to be a vast distance. ·It has often been thought that the crucial difference is that men alone can reason, but that isn’t right·. For if lower animals have any ideas at all and aren’t bare machines (as some think they are), we can’t deny that they have some reason. It seems to me as obvious that some of them sometimes reason as that they have sense; but when they reason it is only with particular ideas, just as they received them from their senses ·and not subjected to abstraction·....

[Sections 12-13 discuss the relations between the mental capacities discussed in this chapter and different kinds of mental deficiency in humans. The following passage in 13 will be referred to in xxxiii.4:] A man who is very level-headed and has a good mind most of the time may in one kind of context be as frantic as any in the mad-house. This can happen because—either through •some sudden very strong impression, or through •his long fixing his mind on thoughts of one kind—incoherent ideas have been cemented together ·in his mind· so powerfully as to remain united ·there·. [The section concludes:] The difference between idiots and madmen seems to be this: madmen put wrong ideas together and so make wrong propositions, but argue and reason correctly from them; but idiots make few if any propositions, and reason hardly at all.

14. The faculties and operations of the mind ·that I have described in this chapter· are exercised on •all the mind’s ideas, of whatever kind, but my examples have mainly involved •simple ideas. I have gone from my account of simple ideas ·in chapters ii-viii· directly to my account ·in chapters ix-xi· of these faculties of the mind, before coming to what I have to say about •complex ideas. I have three reasons for taking the topics in that order. First, Some of these faculties are at first employed principally on simple ideas; so ·in following my order· we can follow nature in its ordinary method, and thereby track and reveal the faculties in their rise, progress, and gradual improvements.

Secondly, simple ideas are usually much more clear, precise, and distinct than complex ones; so by observing how the faculties of the mind operate on them we can •better grasp how the mind abstracts, names, compares and employs its other operations—•better, that is, than if we also brought in complex ideas, with which we are much more liable to make mistakes.

Thirdly, these very operations of the mind relating to ideas received from sensations are themselves, when reflected on, another set of ideas—·some of them simple ideas·—derived from that other source of our knowledge which I call •reflection; which makes it appropriate to deal with them immediately after the simple ideas of •sensation. As for compounding, comparing, abstracting, etc., I have said very little about them, because I shall have occasion to treat them at more length in other places [in III].

15. I have given a short and (I think) true account of the first beginnings of human knowledge: where the mind gets its first objects [here = ‘ideas’] from, and how it goes about storing

42

Essay II John Locke xii: Complex ideas

those ideas out of which all the knowledge it is capable of is to be made. I must appeal to experience and observation to decide whether my account is right. The best way to reach truth is to examine things as they really are, and not to steer by fancies that we have worked up for ourselves or have been taught by others to imagine.

16. ·Reverting now to my thesis that ideas enter the mind only through sensation and reflection·: This is the only way I can find for ideas to be brought into the understanding. If other men are sure that they have innate ideas, the rest of us can’t deny them the privilege that they have over us, ·namely, of knowing what goes on in their own minds·. I can only speak of what I find in myself, which fits the account I have given. If we examine the whole course of men in their various ages, countries, and educations, what we shall find seems to depend on the foundations that I have laid.

17. I don’t claim to teach, only to enquire. So let me say it again: external and internal sensation [= ‘sensation and reflection’] are the only routes I can find for knowledge to enter the understanding. These alone, as far as I can discover, are the windows through which light is let into this dark room. The understanding strikes me as being like a closet that is wholly sealed against light, with only some little openings left to let in external visible resemblances or ideas of things outside. If the pictures coming into such a dark room stayed there, and lay in order so that they could be found again when needed, it would very much resemble the understanding of a man, as far as objects of sight and the ideas of them are concerned.

Those are my guesses concerning the means by which the understanding comes to •have and •retain simple ideas and their modes, along with •some other operations on them. I now proceed to examine some of these simple ideas and their modes in more detail.

Chapter xii: Complex ideas

1. So far we have considered only •ideas that the mind receives passively, namely •the simple ones that come to it from sensation and reflection. The mind can’t make any such simple idea for itself, and can’t have any idea that doesn’t wholly consist of them. But while the mind is wholly passive in the reception of all its simple ideas, it acts in various ways to construct other ideas out of its simple ones, which are the materials and foundations of all the rest. The acts in which the mind exerts its power over its simple ideas are chiefly these three: 1 Combining several simple ideas into one compound one; that is how all complex ideas are made. 2 Bringing together two ideas, whether simple or complex, setting them side by side so as to see them both at once, without uniting them into one; this is how the mind gets all its ideas of relations. 3 Separating them from all other ideas that accompany them in their real existence; this is called abstraction, and it is how all the mind’s general ideas are made.

43

Essay II John Locke xii: Complex ideas

This shows that the power a man has, and his exercise of it, are pretty much the same in the intellectual world as in the material one. In neither realm has he any power to make or destroy any raw materials; all he can do is either to •unite them together, or •set them side by side, or •wholly separate them. (·For example, he cannot make or destroy rocks, but he can assemble them to make a wall, or dismantle a wall that has been made from them·.) I shall begin with uniting, and shall come to the other two in due course.

As simple ideas are observed to exist in various combinations united together, so the mind has a power to consider several of them united together as one idea; not only in combinations that exist in external objects, but also in ones the mind makes up. Ideas thus made up of several simple ones I call complex. Examples are ·the ideas of· beauty, gratitude, a man, an army, the universe. These are all complex ideas made up of simple ones, but the mind can if it wishes treat each of them by itself as one unified thing, signified by one name.

2. By being able to repeat and join together its ideas, the mind has great power to vary and multiply the objects of its thoughts, infinitely beyond what sensation or reflection provides it with.... The basic raw materials of all its compositions are simple ideas received from those two sources—the mind has no other way of getting any—but once it has acquired these simple ideas it can by its own power put together the ideas it has, making new complex ones that it never received united in that way.

3. Complex ideas, however compounded and decompounded, are infinitely numerous and endlessly various. Still, I think they can all be brought under three headings: 1 Modes. 2 Substances. 2 Relations.

4. First, modes are complex ideas that don’t contain within them the supposition of •existing by themselves, but are considered as •dependences on or states of substances. Examples are the ideas signified by the words ‘triangle’, ‘gratitude’, ‘murder’, etc. (·These words stand for dependences on substances because: if there is a triangle that is because something is triangular, if gratitude occurs that is because someone is grateful, if there is a murder that is because someone murders someone.·) Forgive me if I am here using the word ‘mode’ in somewhat a different sense from its ordinary one. When presenting a view that involves notions different from any that people commonly have, one must either invent new words or use old ones with somewhat new meanings; and in the present case the latter is perhaps the more tolerable of the two procedures.

5. Two sorts of modes deserve to be considered separately. •Some are only variations or different combinations of the same simple idea, not mixed in with any other. For example, the ideas of dozen and score are nothing but the ideas of so many distinct units added together. I call these simple modes, because they are contained within the bounds of one simple idea. ·It should be remembered that a simple mode is, like all modes, a complex idea·. •Others are made up of simple ideas of different kinds, put together to make one complex one. Examples are beauty (a certain composition of colour and figure, causing delight to the beholder), and theft (the concealed change of the possession of something without its owner’s consent, which obviously combines several ideas of different kinds). I call these mixed modes.

6. Secondly, the ideas of substances are combinations of simple ideas that are taken to represent distinct particular things existing by themselves. In such combinations the supposed or confused idea of substance, such as it is, is

44

Essay II John Locke xii: Complex ideas

always the first and chief. Thus if to the idea of substance we join the simple idea of a certain dull whitish colour, and ·ideas of· certain degrees of weight, hardness, ductility, and fusibility, we have the idea of lead; and a combination of the ideas of a certain shape with mobility, thought, and reasoning, joined to substance, makes the ordinary idea of a man. Ideas of substances also fall into two sorts: •ideas of single substances as they exist separately, for example the idea of a man or of a sheep; and •ideas of several of those put together, such as the idea of an army of men, or of a flock of sheep. An idea of the latter collective kind—an idea, that is, of several substances put together—is as much one single idea as is the idea of a man.

7. Thirdly, the last sort of complex idea is the one we call relation, which consists in considering and comparing one idea with another. I shall discuss these different kinds in their order, ·taking simple modes in chapters xii-xxi, complex or ‘mixed’ modes in xxii, substances in xxiii-xxiv, and relations in xxv-xxviii·.

[In section 8 Locke makes some wind-up remarks about the intellectual riches that we can get by operating, in the ways he has described, on the simple ideas we get from our outer and inner senses. He remarks that he’ll illustrate this in his treatments of ‘the ideas we have of space, time, and infinity and a few others that seem the most remote from’ simple sense-based ideas.]

45

Essay II John Locke Chapter xiii: Simple modes of space

Chapter xiii: Simple modes, starting with the simple modes of space

1. I have often mentioned simple ideas, the materials of all our knowledge, focussing on how they come into the mind. Now I shall discuss some of them with a different focus: this time it will be on how they relate to ideas that are more compounded, looking into the different modifications of the same idea—modifications that the mind either finds in real things or makes up on its own initiative. [A ‘modification’ of a quality is a special case of it, so squareness is a modification of rectangularity (see viii.23); and by a natural extension of that usage, the idea of squareness can be called a modification of the idea of rectangularity.] Those modifications of a single simple idea (which I call simple modes) are as perfectly different and distinct ideas in the mind as those that are utterly unalike or even contrary to one another. For •the idea of two is as distinct from that of one as blueness is from heat or as either of those is from any number; yet •it is made up only of repetitions of the simple idea of a unit. Repetitions of this kind joined together make the distinct simple modes of a dozen, a gross, a million.

[Section 2 merely repeats the point Locke has made in v, that ‘we get the idea of space both by our sight and touch’.]

3. Space considered in terms purely of length between any two things, without considering anything else between them, is called distance; if considered in terms of length, breadth, and thickness I think it may be called capacity. The term extension is usually applied to it whatever manner it is considered in, ·whether in terms of one or two or three dimensions·.

4. Each different distance is a different modification of space; and each idea of any distance is a simple mode of this idea.... We have the power of repeating any idea we have of some distance, and adding it to the first idea as often as we like, without being ever able to come to any stop. That lets us enlarge it as much as we like, which gives us the idea of immensity [= ‘infinite size’].

5. There is another modification of this idea, which is nothing but the relation that the parts of a boundary have to one another. In perceptible bodies whose surfaces come within our reach, this relation is revealed by the sense of touch; and the eye learns about it from bodies and from ·expanses of· colours whose boundaries are within its view. •Observing how the boundaries terminate either in straight lines that meet at discernible angles or in crooked lines in which no angles can be perceived, •and considering these as they relate to one another in all parts of the boundaries of any body or space, the mind has the idea that we call shape, which presents it with infinite variety. For besides the vast number of different shapes that really exist in coherent masses of matter, the mind has the power to make perfectly inexhaustible additions to its stock of ideas, by varying the idea of space and thereby making new compositions. It can multiply shapes ad infinitum, by repeating its own ideas and joining them as it pleases.

[Section 6 continues with the theme of our freedom to make ideas of any shapes we like, whether encountered in reality or not; and adds that we can also form ideas of lengths or distances that are as long or as short as we please.]

7. Another idea that belongs in here is the one we call place. Whereas in simple space we consider the relation of distance between any two bodies or points, in our idea of place we consider the relation of distance between •some thing and

46

Essay II John Locke Chapter xiii: Simple modes of space

•any two or more points that are considered as staying at the same distance from one another and thus as staying at rest. When we find a thing at the same distance now as it was yesterday from two or more points that haven’t changed their relative distance in the interim, we say it has ‘kept the same place’; whereas if it has perceptibly altered its distance from either of those points we say that it has ‘changed its place’....

8. ·The idea of a thing’s place is relative, in a manner I now explain·. If we find the chess-men on the same squares of the board that they where when we left them, we say they are all in the same place, or unmoved, even if the board has been carried from one room into another. That is because we relate them only to the parts of the chess-board, which stay at the same distance from one another. The board, we also say, is in the same place as before if it remains in the same part of the cabin, even if the ship has been sailing on; and the ship is said to be in the same place if it keeps the same distance from the parts of the neighbouring land, even though the earth has rotated. So chess-men, board, and ship have each changed place in respect of more distant bodies that have kept the same distance from one another....

9. This modification of distance that we call place was made by us for our own use, and we fit it to our convenience. When men speak of the ‘place’ of a thing, they do it by reference to those adjacent things that best serve their present purpose, ignoring other things that might be better determinants of place for another purpose. When we are playing chess, it wouldn’t suit our purpose to locate the pieces in relation to anything except the squares on the board; but quite different standards apply when the chess-men are stored in a bag and someone asks ‘Where is the black king?’ and the right answer is ‘In the captain’s cabin’. Another example: when someone asks in what place certain verses are, he doesn’t want an answer that names a town or a library or a shelf; he wants an answer such as: ‘They are at about the middle of the ninth book of Virgil’s Aeneid’, which remains true however often the book has been moved....

10. Because our idea of place is merely that of a thing’s relative position, we can have no idea of the place of the universe, though we can of any part of it. We have no idea of any fixed, distinct, particular beings, in reference to which we can imagine the universe to be related by distance. On the contrary, beyond it there is only one uniform space or expansion in which the mind finds no variety, no marks. To say that the world is somewhere means merely that it does exist.... Someone who could find out and form a clear idea of the place of the universe would be able to tell us—·as in fact obviously nobody can·—whether the universe moves or stands still in the undifferentiated emptiness of infinite space!....

11. Some philosophers—·led into this by Descartes·—maintain that body and extension are the same thing. One might think they have changed the meaning of one of the words; but I doubt that, because they have so severely condemned others for relying on uncertain meanings and on the deceitful obscurity of doubtful or meaningless words. Well, then, if they mean by ‘body’ and ‘extension’ the same as other people do, namely:

body: something that is solid and extended, whose parts are separable and movable in different ways;

extension: the space that lies between the extremities of those solid cohering parts, and which is possessed by them [these are Locke’s exact words],

then they are confounding two very different ideas with one another. Isn’t it clear to us all that the idea of space is as

47

Essay II John Locke Chapter xiii: Simple modes of space

distinct from that of solidity as it is from the idea of scarlet colour? Solidity can’t exist without extension; but neither can scarlet colour exist without extension; this doesn’t prevent the ideas from being distinct from one another. Many ideas require, as necessary to their existence or conception, other ideas, ones that are entirely distinct from them. Motion can’t be or be conceived without space, but motion is not space. Equally distinct from one another, I think, are the ideas of space and solidity ·and, therefore, the ideas of space and of body. That follows because·: solidity is so inseparable an idea from body that the latter depends on the former for its filling of space, its contact, impact, and communication of motion on impact. If we can—·as some Cartesians do·—infer that •mind is different from body from the premise that •thinking doesn’t include the idea of extension in it, we should be able by parity of argument to conclude that •space is not body, because •it doesn’t include the idea of solidity in it. Here are three reasons why body and extension are two distinct ideas.

12. First, extension doesn’t include solidity or resistance to the motion of body, as body does.

13. Secondly, the parts of pure space are inseparable from one another; so that the continuity can’t be broken up—either really or in thought. One couldn’t possibly break up a region of space into two separated parts, with two surfaces where there had been a continuity; and the very thought of such a separation is impossible, being inconsistent with the idea of pure space.

I am not denying that one can consider a portion of space—say a cubic foot of it—without considering the rest; but that is a partial consideration, not a mental separation, which is something different.... One may consider light in the sun without its heat, or mobility in a body without its extension, without thinking of their separation—·that is, without thinking of the sun as cold or of the body as unextended·....

14. Thirdly, the parts of pure space are immovable, which follows from their being inseparable, because motion is nothing but change of distance between any two things, and this can’t happen between parts that are inseparable.

Thus the established idea of simple space distinguishes it plainly and sufficiently from body, since its parts are inseparable, immovable, and without resistance to the motion of body ·whereas none of these is true of body·.

15. If anyone asks me, What is this space you speak of? I will tell him when he tells me what his extension is. For to say, as is usually done, that being extended is having parts outside parts [Locke puts it in Latin] is to say only that extension is extension. I learn nothing about the nature of extension when I am told ‘Being extended is having extended parts that are exterior to extended parts’. Compare ‘What is a fibre?’ is a thing made up of several fibres!’....

16. Those who contend that space and body are the same challenge us with a dilemma ·that they learned from Descartes·. Either space is something or it is nothing; if we say it is nothing, then ·they reply that in that case two bodies cannot be separated by it, because· if there is nothing between two bodies they must touch one another. But if instead we say that space is something, they demand that we tell them whether it is body or mind. I answer their question with a question: who told them that there could be nothing but solid beings that can’t think, and thinking beings that aren’t extended?....

17. If someone asks (as people usually do) whether space with no body in it is substance or accident [here = ‘property’], I

48

Essay II John Locke Chapter xiii: Simple modes of space

answer: I don’t know, and I shan’t be ashamed to admit my ignorance until the challengers show me a clear distinct idea of substance. ·I shall stay with ‘substance’ for the next three sections, returning to space in section 21a·.

18. I do my best to avoid the fallacies that we tend to fall into when we take words for things. It doesn’t help our ignorance when we pretend to have knowledge by making meaningless noises. Made-up names don’t alter the nature of things, and unless they stand for definite ideas they don’t enable us to understand things either. Those who lay so much stress on the sound of the two syllables substance should ask themselves what is going on when they apply this word to •the infinite incomprehensible God, to •finite spirits, and to •body. Do they apply it in the same sense? Does it stand for the same idea when each of those three so-different beings are called substances? If it is, does it follow that God, spirits, and body, agreeing in the same common nature of substance, differ only in having different modifications of it, comparably with how a tree and a pebble are alike in having the common nature of body and differ only in having different modifications of it. That would be very hard to swallow. If instead they say that they apply ‘substance’ to God, finite spirit, and matter in three different meanings, expressing three different ideas, they ought to make known what those distinct ideas are, or at least to give them three different names, to prevent the confusion and errors that will naturally follow from the promiscuous use of such a suspect term. So far from its having three different meanings, in ordinary usage ‘substance’ scarcely has one that is clear and distinct!....

19. The philosophers who first rushed into the notion of accidents, as a sort of real beings that needed something to inhere in, were forced to find out the word ‘substance’ to support them. [In this context an ‘accident’ is a property-instance. Locke is accusing his opponents of some such thought as this: ‘In this ball that I hold in my hand there is sphericity, rubberiness, softness, a certain smell, and so on; that is, there are this ball’s instances of those general properties; but there must also be something that has them, something that they are properties of. That must be a substance.’] Consider the poor Indian philosopher who imagined that the earth also needed something to hold it up. If only he had thought of this word ‘substance’, he wouldn’t have needed to find an elephant to support the world and a tortoise to support the elephant: the word ‘substance’ would have met his needs! That would have been as good an answer to his question as it is to the question of our European philosophers who ask what supports a thing’s accidents, and answers that it is ‘substance’. We have in fact no idea of what substance is, but only a confused obscure one of what it does, ·namely, it supports accidents·.

[In section 20 Locke continues his attack on ‘substance’, ending with this sarcastic jibe against the view that accidents must inhere in a substance:] If the Latin words inhaerentia and substantia were put into the plain English that translates them—‘sticking on’ and ‘under-propping’—it would be easier for us to see the very great clearness there is in the doctrine of substance and accidents, and show how useful they are in deciding of questions in philosophy.

21a. [Through a mistake in the original work, this section and the next were both labelled ‘21’.] Returning now to our idea of space ·and to the wrongness of identifying it with our idea of body·: I think everyone will agree that there is not an infinite extent of matter (‘body’) in the universe. Well, then, if a man were placed by God at the edge of the world of bodies, could he stretch his hand beyond his body? If he could, then he would put his arm where there had previously been space without

49

Essay II John Locke Chapter xiii: Simple modes of space

body; and if he spread the fingers of his outstretched hand, there would be space between them without body. If on the other hand he couldn’t stretch out his hand, that would have to be because of some external obstacle; and then I ask whether that obstacle is substance or accident, something or nothing? When they (·the Cartesians·) have settled that, they will be able to settle what it is that •can be between two bodies at a distance and •is not body itself and •has no solidity. Anyway, this line of thought ·about nothing·:

If a body is put in motion and nothing hinders it (as would be the case beyond the utmost bounds of all bodies), it can continue to move,

is at least as good as this one:

If there is nothing between two bodies, they must touch one another.

·Really the former is better than the latter, for· •pure space between two bodies is sufficient to block the inference to their being in contact with one another, whereas •bare space in the way isn’t sufficient to stop motion. In fact, these men must either admit that they think body to be infinite (though they don’t like saying this aloud) or else affirm that space isn’t body after all. A thoughtful person can no more have the thought of a boundary to space than he can think of a limit to time; if anyone’s idea of eternity is infinite, so is his idea of immensity; either time and space are both finite or they are both infinite.

21b. Furthermore, those who assert the impossibility of space existing without matter must not only make body infinite but must also deny that God has a power to annihilate a part of matter. Presumably no-one will deny that God could put an end to all motion, keeping all the bodies in the universe completely immobile for as long as he pleased. Well, then, if you allow that God could, during such a period of universal rest, annihilate the book you are now reading, you must also admit the possibility of a vacuum, for the space that was filled by the annihilated book would still exist, and would be a space without body. For the surrounding bodies, being perfectly still, make a diamond-hard wall through which no other body can possibly get in.

Indeed, the supposition of plenitude—·i.e. that the universe is full·—has the consequence that if a particle of matter is removed another particle must move in to take its place. But ·plenitude is only an unsupported supposition, which· needs some better proof than a supposed matter of fact which experiment can never establish. ·And it can’t be accepted on conceptual rather than matter-of-fact grounds, for· our own clear and distinct ideas plainly satisfy us that there is no necessary connection between space and solidity, since we can conceive the one without the other. [Locke then repeats a point from iv.3: anyone who joins in the debate over plenitude as a matter-of-fact issue thereby commits himself to having distinct ideas of space and of matter or body.]

22. Without thinking about the edge of the material world, and without appeal to God’s omnipotence, we get evidence for the existence of a vacuum from the motion of bodies that we see in our own neighbourhood. I defy anyone to divide a solid body so as to make it possible for the solid parts to move up and down freely every way within the bounds of that surface, without leaving in it an empty space as big as the smallest part into which he has divided the body. [Locke goes on to say, with some eloquence, that this reasoning applies at any size-level you care to choose.]

23. But my topic was the question whether the idea of space or extension is the same as the idea of body; and to answer No to this it isn’t necessary to prove the real existence of a

50

Essay II John Locke Chapter xiii: Simple modes of space

vacuum. All that is needed is that we have the idea of it, and it is plain that men have that—·i.e. the idea of vacuum, or space without body·—when they argue about whether or not there is a vacuum. If they didn’t have the idea of space without body, they couldn’t make a question about its existence....

[In section 24 Locke offers a suggestion about why the Cartesians made their mistake. (The better Cartesians, that is; he is rude about the others.) By sight and by touch, he says, the extension of bodies is forced in on us all the time, so it has come to dominate the thinking of the Cartesians, seducing them into thinking that none of the other properties of bodies could exist in the world except as properties of extended things. He concludes:] If they had reflected on their ideas of •tastes and smells, as much as on those of •sight and touch, they would have found that the former didn’t include in them any idea of extension. Extension is just one affection [= ‘property’] of body—one among others—and it is discoverable by our senses, which are hardly acute enough to look into the pure essences of things. ·The Cartesian view, remember, is that extension is the whole essence of body·.

[Section 25 presents a mild philosophical joke: the sort of thinking the Cartesians seem to have done should lead one to conclude that ‘unity is the essence of every thing’ because every thing is an instance of it—i.e. is one.]

[In section 26 Locke repeats his main case against the Cartesian view. He also mentions, but doesn’t answer, the question of whether space is •‘only a relation resulting from the existence of other beings at a distance’ or whether instead it is •a kind of container. He declines to take sides on that question. He ends by suggesting some terminology, including this:] To avoid confusion it might be helpful if the word ‘extension’ were applied only to matter, or the distance between the boundaries of particular bodies, and the term ‘expansion’ were used for space in general, with or without solid matter possessing it....

28. ·That last suggestion points to a more general issue that will loom large in Book III, but which warrants one section here·. Knowing precisely what our words stand for would, I imagine, quickly end this dispute and very many others. For I am inclined to think that when men come to examine their simple ideas they find them generally to agree, though in conversation they may confuse one another by using different names. I imagine that men who abstract their thoughts ·from the words in which they express them·, and examine well the ideas of their own minds, can’t differ much in their •thinking, however much they may puzzle one another with •words, which they use according to the ways of speaking of the various schools or sects they grew up in. Though amongst unthinking men who don’t scrupulously and carefully examine their own ideas, and don’t peel them off from the words men use for them, but rather confound them with words, there is bound to be endless dispute, wrangling, and jargon; especially if they are learned bookish men who are devoted to some sect, and have learned to parrot its way of talking. But if any two thinking men really had different ideas, I don’t see how they could converse or argue one with another.

Don’t misunderstand me. The sort of ideas I am speaking of don’t include every floating imagination in men’s brains. It isn’t easy for the mind to put off those confused notions and prejudices it has absorbed from custom, carelessness. and ordinary talk. It requires trouble and concentration for the mind to examine its ideas far enough to resolve them into the clear and distinct simple ideas out of which they have been compounded, and to see which of its simple ones have a necessary connection with which others....

51

Essay II John Locke xiv: Duration and its simple modes

Chapter xiv: Duration and its simple modes

1. There is another sort of distance or length the idea of which we get not from the permanent parts of space but from the fleeting and perpetually perishing parts of succession. This we call duration; its simple modes are the different lengths of it of which we have distinct ideas—hours, days, years, etc., and time and eternity.

2. A great man—·St. Augustine·—when asked by someone what time is, answered: ‘When you don’t ask me, I know what it is’ [Locke gives this in Latin], which amounts to this: ‘The more I set myself to think about it, the less I understand it.’ This might lead one to think that time, which reveals all other things, is itself not to be discovered. Duration, time, and eternity are plausibly thought to have something very abstruse in their nature. But if we trace these ideas right back to their origins in sensation and reflection, one of those will be able to make these ideas as clear and distinct to us as many others that are not thought to be so obscure. ·Among other things·, we shall find that the idea of eternity itself is derived from the same origin as the rest of our ideas.

3. To understand time and eternity correctly, we should attend to the nature of our idea of duration, and to how we came by it. Anyone who observes what happens in his own mind must realize that there is a sequence of ideas constantly following one another in his mind, as long as he is awake. Reflection on these appearances of various ideas one after another in our minds is what provides us with the idea of succession; and the distance between two any parts of that sequence, or between the appearance of any two ideas in our minds, is what we call duration. For while we are thinking, or while we receive successively various ideas in our minds, we know that we exist; and so we call the existence (or the continuation of the existence) of ourselves our ‘duration’. We also speak of the duration of other things that coexist with our thinking.

4. We don’t perceive duration except when we attend to the sequence of ideas that take their turns in our understandings; which convinces me that our notion of succession and duration comes from reflection. [When Locke writes a phrase like ‘a succession of ideas’, this text replaces ‘succession’ by ‘sequence’. In phrases like ‘our notion of succession’, the word ‘succession’ is left alone.] When the sequence of ideas ceases, our perception of duration ceases with it—as everyone finds from his own experience of sleeping for any period of time, long or short. While he is sleeping and not thinking, he has no perception at all, and the duration of his sleep is quite lost to him; there seems to him to be no ·temporal· distance from the moment he stops thinking to the moment he starts again. I am sure that it would be just like that for a man awake, if he could keep only one unvarying idea in his mind. We do in fact see that someone who fixes his thoughts very intently on one thing, not attending much to the sequence of ideas that pass in his mind, lets slip out of his account a good part of that duration and thinks the time that has passed is shorter than it really is. [Locke adds the point that even a sleeping man retains a sense of time passing if he dreams; which he takes as confirmation of his view.]

5. Someone who has in this way acquired the notion or idea of duration, can apply it to things that exist while he isn’t thinking; just as someone who has acquired the idea of extension from bodies through his sight or touch can apply

52

Essay II John Locke xiv: Duration and its simple modes

it to distances where no body is seen or felt. That enables a man to judge how much time has passed while he was asleep and not dreaming. Having observed the revolution of days and nights, and found the length of their duration to appear regular and constant, he can suppose that this revolution went on in the same way while he was sleeping as it did at other times, and this will give him a measure of how long he slept. But if Adam and Eve (when they were alone in the world), instead of their ordinary night’s sleep, had passed a whole twenty-four hours in one continued sleep, the duration of those twenty-four hours would have been irrecoverably lost to them.

6. If you think that we get the notion of succession from •sensation rather than •reflection, then consider this: the motion of external bodies produces an idea of succession in your mind only to the extent that it produces there a continued series of distinguishable ideas. A man becalmed at sea may look on the sun, or the sea, or his ship for a whole hour, during which time two and perhaps three of those objects have moved, but because •he hasn’t perceived their motion he doesn’t get from them any sense of duration, ·i.e. of time passing·. But if during this hour of quiet he has been thinking, •he will perceive the various ideas of his thoughts appearing one after another in his own mind, and thereby find succession where he could observe no motion.

7. I think this is why very slow uniform motions are not perceived by us. In such a case, the change of relative distance is so slow that it causes no new ideas in us—or only ones that are widely separated in time—and so we don’t have a constant series of new ideas following one another immediately in our minds, and thus have no perception of motion....

8. On the other side, things that move very swiftly are also not perceived to move. It is because they don’t affect the senses distinctly with the distinguishable distances of their motion [the last five words are Locke’s], and so don’t cause any sequence of ideas in the mind. When we see a thing moving around in a circle in less time than our ideas ordinarily succeed one another in our minds, we don’t perceive it to move, and see it rather as a perfect unbroken circle of that matter or colour, and not a part of a circle in motion.

9. I conjecture (you decide for yourself) that while we are awake our ideas succeed one another in our minds at certain distances, somewhat like the images inside a lantern that are turned around by the heat of a candle. Their appearance in sequence may be sometimes faster and sometimes slower, but I guess that it doesn’t vary much in a waking man. There seem to be limits to how quickly and to how slowly ideas can succeed one another in our minds.

10. My reason for this odd conjecture is my observation that in the impressions made on any of our senses we can perceive succession only within limits. If the sequence of impressions is exceedingly fast, the •sense of succession is lost, even in cases where it is obvious that there is a •real succession. Suppose that a cannon-bullet shoots across a room, on its way ripping off someone’s leg: it couldn’t be clearer that it must successively strike the two sides of the room, and that its damage to the victim must occur between those two events. And yet I don’t think that anybody who felt the pain of such a shot and heard the blows against the two walls would perceive any succession in these events. A stretch of time like this, in which we perceive no succession, is what we call an instant. It is that which takes up the time of only one idea in our minds.

11. This also happens when the motion is very slow, not

53

Essay II John Locke xiv: Duration and its simple modes

providing the mind with a constant series of fresh sensory ideas as fast as the mind is capable of receiving them. In these cases, •other ideas of our own thoughts can insert themselves into our minds between •the ideas offered to our senses by the ·slowly· moving body. So the sense of motion is lost. Although the body really does move, its •changes of perceivable distance from some other bodies is slower than the rate at which •ideas of our own minds—·ideas of reflection·—naturally follow one another in sequence. The thing therefore seems to stand still; as is evident in the hands of clocks and shadows of sun-dials, and other constant but slow motions....

12. It seems to me, then, that the constant and regular succession of ideas in a waking man is the measure and standard—so to speak—of all other successions. [The remainder of this section repeats the content of sections 10 and 11. Locke will take up temporal measurement in section 17 and run with it to the end of the chapter.]

13. Someone may say: ‘If the ideas of our minds constantly change and shift in a continual succession, it would be impossible for a man to think long about any one thing.’ If this means that a man can’t have one single idea for a long time alone in his mind, with no variation, I agree that it isn’t possible. The only reason I can give for this opinion is an appeal to experience; and I invite you to try whether you can keep one unvaried single idea in your mind, without any other, for a considerable period of time. ·I can’t give a deeper and more explanatory reason for my view, because I lack the knowledge that this would require·. I don’t know how the ideas of our minds are made, or what they are made of, or what lights them up for us, or how they come to make their appearances.

[In sections 14–15 Locke predicts the difficulties that will confront anyone who accepts his ‘try it for yourself’ challenge. Section 16 repeats the thought of section 6, namely that the motions of bodies support our idea of succession only through the succession of ideas they cause in us.]

17. Once the mind has acquired the idea of duration, the next thing it is natural for it to do is to get some measure of this common duration, by which to judge its different lengths and think about the order in which various events occur. Without this, much of our knowledge would be confused, and much of history would be useless. When duration is considered as broken up into measured periods, the proper name for it is ‘time’.

18. To measure extension we need only to apply our standard or measure to the thing we are measuring—·for example, laying a tape-measure along a length of cloth·. But in measuring duration we can’t do that, because no two parts of a sequence can be laid alongside one another. And nothing can measure duration except duration (just as nothing can measure extension except extension); but we can’t keep by us any standing unvarying measure of duration, as we can of certain lengths of extension, marked out in durable material things. All we are left with for a convenient measure of time is the dividing up of long periods into apparently equal portions, ·these being measured· by constantly repeated kinds of event. Portions of duration that aren’t thought of as distinguished and measured by such periods aren’t strictly speaking instances of time, and we reflect this in phrases like ‘before all time’ and ‘when time shall be no more’.

[Sections 19–20 make and defend the following point: Although in our civilisation we measure time by movements, e.g. those of the earth around the sun, it is a mistake to think—as some philosophers have—that time and motion are

54

Essay II John Locke xiv: Duration and its simple modes

essentially tightly linked to one another. All the measuring of time requires is regular periodic events of some kind; they need not be movements. Locke gives examples of other standards for the measurement of time.]

21. ‘Without a regular motion such as the sun’s’, it may be demanded, ‘how could it ever be known that such periods were equal?’ I answer that the equality of any other periodic events could be known in the same way that days were known or presumed to be equal at first—namely, through judging them in terms of the contemporaneous series of ideas that had passed in men’s minds. [Locke develops this point in a long discussion of which the following episodes are especially notable.] We must carefully distinguish duration itself from the measures we make of it. Duration in itself is to be considered as going on in one constant, equal, uniform course; but none of our bases for measuring it can be known to do so.... If anyone should ask us how we know that the two successive swings of a pendulum are equal, it would be hard to satisfy him that they are infallibly so.... Since no two portions of a sequence can be brought together, it is impossible ever certainly to know their equality. All we can do for a measure of time is to take such ·kinds of events· as have continual successive appearances at seemingly equidistant periods. And of this seeming equality we have no measure except the sequence of our own ideas, with some confirmation from other probable reasons, to persuade us of their equality.

[In section 22 Locke criticises the view that ‘time should be defined to be the ‘measure of motion’, bringing against it the points made in sections 19–20, and adding one further point, namely that •time has no more right to the label ‘measure of motion’ than •space has.]

[In section 23 Locke contends that there is no necessity about any of the measures of duration that we happen to use—minutes, hours, days, etc. We could adopt any others that satisfied the requirement of ‘regular periodical returns’.

24. Once the mind has acquired a measure of time such as the annual revolution of the sun, it can apply that measure to durations in which that measure didn’t exist..... The idea of duration equal to an annual revolution of the sun is as easily applicable in our thoughts to duration where no sun or motion was, as the idea of a foot or yard, taken from bodies here, can be applied in our thoughts to distances beyond the confines of the world, where are no bodies at all.

[Section 25 expands this point a little.]

26. If it is objected that in my account of time I have illegitimately assumed that the world is neither eternal nor ·spatially· infinite, I answer that my present purposes don’t require me to argue that the world is finite in duration and extension. That it is so is at least as conceivable as that it isn’t, so I am as entitled to assume the finiteness of the world as anyone is to suppose the contrary. ·As regards conceivability·: I am sure that anyone who tries it will easily conceive in his mind the beginning of motion, and so may come to a stop—a go-no-further—in his consideration of motion; but he can’t in the same way conceive a beginning of all duration. So also in his thoughts he can set limits to body, but not to space. The utmost limits of •space and •duration are beyond the reach of thought, as are also the utmost limits of •number—and all for the same reason, as we shall see later.

27. The origin of our idea of time also gives us the idea of eternity. Here is how. Having acquired the idea of succession and duration in the manner I have described, and having

55

Essay II John Locke xiv: Duration and its simple modes

from the revolutions of the sun acquired the ideas of certain lengths of duration, we can in our thoughts add such lengths of duration to one another as often as we please, and apply the results of that addition to durations past or future. We can continue to do so without bounds or limits, proceeding ad infinitum.This lets us apply the length of the sun’s annual motion to a duration before there was any sun or any motion; which is no more difficult or absurd than to apply my notion of one hour, based on the moving of a shadow on a sun-dial, to the duration of the burning of a candle last night, which is now absolutely separate from all actual motion. All this requires is the thought that if the sun had been shining on the dial at that time, its shadow would have moved from one hour-line to the next while the candle’s flame candle lasted.

[In sections 28–9 Locke develops the idea that we can have the thought of determinate periods of time before there were any events by which to measure it. The crux is this, from 29:] For measuring the duration of anything by time, the thing need not be co-existent with any motion that we use for temporal measurement, or indeed with any periodic revolution ·of a kind we could use for such measurement·. All we need is to have the idea of the length of some regular periodical appearances, an idea that we can in our minds apply to durations with which the motion or appearance never co-existed.

30.....I can imagine that light existed three days before the sun existed and moved, by having this thought:

The duration of light before the sun was created was of a length such that: if the sun had been moving then as it does now, it would have been equal to three of its daily revolutions.

....In this way I can have the thought of something’s being the case a minute, an hour, a day, a year, or a thousand years before there were any moving bodies ·or any other regular periodic events·. For I need only to consider duration equal to one minute, and then I can add one minute more, ·and so on· until I come to sixty; and by the same way of adding minutes, hours, or years,....I can proceed ad infinitum. That involves supposing •a duration that exceeds as many such periods as I can count, however long I go on; and I think that is the notion we have of •eternity. The infiniteness of eternity involves the same idea as we have for the infiniteness of number, to which we can add for ever without end.

31. And thus I think it is plain that we get our ideas of duration, and our measures of it, from the two fountains of all knowledge that I have spoken of—reflection and sensation. [Then Locke swiftly recapitulates the six main topics of this chapter: idea of succession, idea of duration, measure of duration, thought of determinate lengths of duration when no measure exists, idea of eternity, idea of ‘time in general’.]

56

Essay II John Locke xv: Duration and expansion

Chapter xv: Duration and expansion, considered together

1. Though I have dwelt pretty long on the topics of space and duration, I shall stay with them, comparing them with one another. They are important, and also in some ways abstruse and peculiar; and we may be helped to get a clear understanding of them by considering them together. I shall use the term ‘expansion’ for the most general and abstract notion of space, because ‘extension’ for some people involves some thought of extended bodies.... In both expansion and duration the mind has the common idea of continued lengths, capable of greater or less quantities; for we have as clear an idea of •how an hour differs from a day as we have of •how an inch differs from a foot.

2. The mind, having acquired the idea of the length of any part of expansion, can repeat it as often as it wants, moving out to the distance of the sun or of the remotest star. In moving out in this way the mind encounters nothing to stop its going on, inside the material world or beyond it. We can easily in our thoughts come to •the end of solid extension: •the outer edge of all body we can easily arrive at ·in our thought·. But when the mind is there, it finds nothing to hinder it from moving on into the endless expansion beyond; of that it can’t even conceive any end. Don’t say ‘Beyond the bounds of body there is nothing at all’, unless you are willing to confine God within the limits of matter....

3. Similarly with duration: having acquired the idea of some length of duration, the mind can double, multiply, and enlarge it—beyond the existence of all bodies and all the measures of time taken from the great bodies of the world and their motions. Yet everyone readily admits that although we rightly make duration boundless we cannot extend it beyond all being. We all agree that God fills eternity; and (·returning for a moment to the last topic of section 2·) it is hard to find a reason for anyone to doubt that God likewise fills immensity. His infinite being is certainly as boundless in one way as in the other; and to say that where there is no body there is nothing at all is, I think, to give too much importance to matter.

[In section 4 Locke says that many people who are sure that time is infinite hesitate to say the same about space, and he suggests a reason. It is because we think of both time and space—or, more strictly, duration and expansion—as states of properties of some being, some thing; where duration is concerned, the thing can be God; but we don’t think of God as extended, and so where space is concerned we are apt to think that it stops where matter stops because beyond the edge of the material world there is no thing for space to be an attribute of. Here Locke interpolates some thoughts about a likeness between the Latin roots of the words for ‘enduring’ and for ‘hard’. Then, returning to his main thought in this section:] But be that as it may, it is certain that anyone who pursues his own thoughts will find that they sometimes launch out beyond the extent of body into the infinity of space or expansion, the idea of which is distinct and separate from body and all other things.

5. Time in general is to duration, as place is to expansion. Time and place are such portions of those boundless oceans of eternity and immensity as have been set out and distinguished from the rest, as it were by land-marks. [The remainder of this section elaborates that a little.]

57

Essay II John Locke xv: Duration and expansion

6. ‘Time’ and ‘place’, taken thus ·to stand· for determinate distinguishable portions of those infinite abysses of space and duration that are supposed to be marked off from the rest by known boundaries, have each of them a double meaning.

First, time in general is commonly taken for that part of infinite duration that is measured by, and co-existent with, the motions of the great bodies of the universe. In that sense time begins and ends when this sensible world begins and ends—see iv.18. Place is also sometimes taken for that portion of infinite space that is occupied by the material world, and is thereby distinguished from the rest of expansion (though this is better called ‘extension’ than ‘place’)....

7. Secondly, sometimes ‘time’ is used in a broader sense, and is applied not only to parts of that infinite duration that were really distinguished and measured out by periodical motions of bodies that we use as our measures of time, but also to other portions of it that we suppose to be equal to certain lengths of measured time—thus considering them as bounded and determined ·even if they were really not so·. In this spirit we might say ‘Angels were created 7640 years before the world was’, thereby marking out as much of that undifferentiated duration as we suppose would have allowed 7640 annual revolutions of the sun if it moved at its actual rate. Likewise we sometimes speak of place, distance, or volume in the great emptiness beyond the edge of the world, when we pick out in thought an amount of it that could contain a body of any assigned dimensions, such as a cubic foot; or suppose a point in it at such-and-such a distance from a given part of the ·material· universe.

8. Where? and When? are questions that can be asked about any finite existent, and we always answer them in terms (·for Where?·) of relations to some known parts of •this perceptible world and (·for When?·) of relations to certain periods marked out to us by the motions observable in •it. Without some such fixed parts or periods, our finite minds would be lost in the boundless invariable oceans of duration and expansion. [Locke then adds details to this comparison between expansion and duration, space and time.]

9. Space and duration are greatly alike in another way, namely that although they are rightly counted as •simple ideas, every distinct idea we have of either of them involves some •composition ·because· it is the very nature of each to consist of parts. Still, they are entitled to count as simple ideas, because their parts are all of the same kind, involving no mixture of any other idea. If the mind could (as with number) reach the thought of a part of extension or duration that is too small to be divided, that would be the indivisible unit or idea by repetition of which the mind would make its more enlarged ideas of extension and duration. But since the mind can’t form an idea of any space without parts, it instead makes use of common measures such as inches and feet, and repeats them to get ideas of larger extents. ·And similarly with time·. [Locke continues with remarks about the ‘obscure and confused’ ideas that we have of very large or very small amounts of space or time. (The idea of ten million cubic miles isn’t clear, though its ten million component is so.) He observes that we have a rough and ready idea of a minimum amount of time or of space—namely the smallest amount of which we can form a clear and distinct idea.]

[In section 10 Locke likens expansion to duration in this: both have parts, but it makes no sense to think of either of them as being taken apart.]

11. Here is a manifest difference between expansion and duration. The ideas of •length that we have can be turned

58

Essay II John Locke xvi: Number

in every direction, and so make shape, and breadth, and thickness; whereas •duration is like the length of one straight line, extended ad infinitum, and not capable of multiplicity, variation, or shape. Duration is something of which all things, while they exist, equally partake. For this present moment is common to all things that are now in being, and contains that ·present· part of their existence,....and we may truly say that they all exist in the same moment of time.

Whether angels and Spirits have any analogy to this in respect to expansion is beyond my comprehension. understandings and comprehensions are suited to our own survival and the purposes of our own lives, but not to the reality and extent of all other things. So it is nearly as hard for us to conceive of any real being with a perfect negation of every kind of expansion as it is to have the idea of a real being with a perfect negation of every kind of duration. So we don’t know ·and can’t even think about· what •Spirits have to do with space, or how they relate to one another in it. All that we know is that each •body possesses its own portion of it, according to the extent of its solid parts, excluding all other bodies from that portion of space for as long as it is there.

12. Duration—and time, which is a part of it—is the idea we have of perishing distance, of which no two parts exist together, but follow each other in sequence; and expansion is the idea of lasting distance, all of whose parts exist together, and are not capable of succession. [By ‘perishing distance’ Locke seems to mean the ever-shrinking temporal distance between the present time and some future event.] ·Because our idea of duration is as it is·, we can’t get our minds around the thought of a being that •now exists tomorrow, or that •now has more than the present moment of duration. Yet we can conceive God’s eternal duration as being far different from ours and any other finite being’s. knowledge and power don’t range over all past and future things; our thoughts are only of yesterday, and we don’t know what tomorrow will bring. We can never bring anything back once it is past; and we can’t make present what is yet to come. What I say here about us I say of all finite beings. Even ones that far exceed man in knowledge and power are still no more than the meanest creature in comparison with God. Something finite, however great and grand it is, stands in no proportion to what is infinite. Because God’s infinite duration is accompanied by infinite knowledge and infinite power, he sees all things past and to come; and they are no more distant from his knowledge than the present. And there is nothing that he can’t make exist whenever he likes. For the existence of all things depends on his good pleasure, so all things exist at every moment that he thinks fit to have them exist.

A final remark: expansion and duration contain each other: every part of space is in every part of duration, and every part of duration is in every part of expansion. In all the great variety of our thoughts, this combination of two distinct ideas seems to have almost no equal. It may be worth thinking about further.

59

Essay II John Locke xvi: Number

Chapter xvi: Number

1. Among all the ideas that we have, none is •suggested to the mind by more ways, and none is •more simple, than the idea of unity or one. It •hasn’t a trace of variety or composition in it; and •every object that our senses are brought to bear on, every idea in our understandings, every thought of our minds, brings this idea along with it. This makes it the most intimate to our thoughts, and also the most universally applicable idea that we have. For number applies itself to men, angels, actions, thoughts, everything that exists or can be imagined.

2. By repeating this idea in our minds, and adding the repetitions together, we come by the complex ideas of its modes. [Here and in many later passages, ‘mode’ means what ‘modification’ meant earlier, e.g. in xiii.1, namely ‘special case’, so that two is a mode of number.] Thus by adding one to one we have the complex idea of a couple; by putting twelve units together we have the complex idea of a dozen; and so on for any other number.

3. The simple modes of number are the most distinct of all our ideas. Every least variation—namely, of one unit—makes each combination as clearly different from its nearest neighbour as it is from the most remote: two is as distinct from one as from two hundred.... This is not so with other simple modes, where it can be hard and perhaps impossible for us to distinguish between two nearby ideas even though they are really different. Who will undertake to find a difference between the white of this paper and that of the next degree ·of whiteness· to it? Who can form distinct ideas of every difference in size, however small?

4. Demonstrations with numbers may not be more evident and exact than demonstrations with extension, but they are more •general in their use and more •determinate in their application. Or so I am inclined think, because each mode of number is so clearly distinct from all others, even close ones, whereas with extension not every equality and excess is so easy to observe or measure. With number we have the idea of a unit, but with extension our thoughts can’t arrive at any determined smallness beyond which it can’t go, comparable with a unit.... No-one can specify an angle that is the next biggest to a right angle!

5. By repeating the idea of a unit, joining it to another unit, we make one collective idea marked by the name ‘two’. If someone can do this, and can carry the procedure further by adding one to each collective idea that he reaches, and also gives a name to every number whose idea he comes to, then he can count.... He can add one to one, and so to two, and so go on with his tally, taking with him the distinct names belonging to every ·stage in the· progression; and so he is capable of all the ideas of numbers for which he has names. Perhaps not of ideas for which he doesn’t have names; because the various simple modes of numbers have no variety, and can’t differ from one another in any way except as more or less, so that names or marks for each separate combination seem more necessary than with any other sort of ideas. For without such names or marks we can seldom make use of numbers in calculating, especially in cases involving a great multitude of units. When such a multitude is assembled ·in thought· without a name or mark to distinguish that precise collection, it will hardly be kept from collapsing into a confused heap.

60

Essay II John Locke xvi: Number

6. I think this is why some Americans [= ‘American Indians’] with whom I have spoken, though otherwise quick and intelligent, didn’t have our ability to count to 1000, and had no distinct idea of that number, though they could calculate very well up to 20. Their language was scanty, being accommodated only to the few necessities of survival in a simple way of life that didn’t involve either trade or mathematics; so it contained no word to stand for 1000. When I spoke to them about those greater numbers, they would show the hairs of their head, to express a great multitude that they couldn’t number. [After giving another example, Locke speaks of the possibility of our wanting to think about higher numbers than we usually do, and thus needing names for them. He proposes that as well as ‘million’ we adopt ‘billion’, ‘trillion’, ‘quadrillion’ and so on, up to ‘nonillion’—and further if we need to. His billion is a million millions.]

[In section 7 Locke discusses children, who, at a time when they have a great deal of intellectual capacity, can’t count or handle particular numbers in other ways; and some adults who ‘through the default of their memories’ have a life-long inability to cope with higher numbers. He concludes:] To calculate correctly, one must do two things: 1 distinguish carefully two ideas that differ from one another only by one unit; 2 retain in memory the names or marks of the several combinations, from a unit up to that number—not confusedly and at random, but in the exact order in which the numbers follow one another. If one goes wrong in either of these, the whole business of numbering will be disturbed, the ideas necessary for distinct numeration won’t be achieved, and one will be left only with the confused idea of multitude.

8. Number is what the mind makes use of in measuring things. The main things that are measurable are expansion and duration; and our idea of infinity, even when applied to those—·in the ideas of •infinite expansion and •infinite duration·—seems to be nothing but the infinity of number. What else are our ideas of •eternity and •immensity but the repeated additions of certain ideas of imagined parts of duration and expansion, with ·help from· the infinity of number, in which we can come to no end of addition? ·Regarding that last point·: Let a man collect into one sum as great a number as he pleases, its size doesn’t lessen even slightly his power of adding to it, or bring him any nearer the end of the inexhaustible stock of number, where there still remains as much to be added as if none were taken out. This addition—or addibility, if you wish—of numbers which is so apparent to the mind is, I think, what gives us our clearest and most distinct idea of infinity. More about that in the next chapter.

61

Essay II John Locke xvii: Infinity

Chapter xvii: Infinity

1. If you want to know what kind of idea it is that we name ‘infinity’, you can’t do better than to consider •what the idea of infinity is most immediately applied to by the mind, and then •how the mind comes to form this idea.

Finite and infinite seem to me to be viewed by the mind as modes of quantity, and to be attributed primarily and initially only to things that have parts, and can be augmented or diminished by the addition or subtraction of parts, however small. Such are the ideas of space, duration, and number, which we have considered in xiii-xvi. No doubt we must accept that the great God is incomprehensibly infinite; but when we apply ‘infinite’ to that first and supreme being, we do it primarily in respect to when and where he exists, ·in the judgment that he exists always and everywhere·; and we apply infinity more figuratively (I think) to his power, wisdom, and goodness, and other attributes, which are in their own natures inexhaustible and incomprehensible, etc. When we call them ‘infinite’ we have no other idea of this infinity except what carries with it some reflection on, and imitation of, that number or extent of the acts or objects of God’s power, wisdom, and goodness. I make no claim about how these attributes are in God, who is infinitely beyond the reach of our narrow capacities. They certainly contain in them all possible perfection. But this, I say, is how we conceive them, and these are our ideas of their infinity.

2. Finite and infinite, then, are viewed by the mind as modifications of expansion and duration. Next we must consider how the mind comes by these ideas. There is no great difficulty about finite. The obvious portions of extension that affect our senses carry the idea of finite with them into the mind; and the ordinary periods (hours, days, years) whereby we measure time and duration are bounded lengths, ·and thus finite·. What is difficult is to grasp how we come by those boundless ideas of eternity and immensity, since the objects we interact with fall so far short—immeasurably short—of that largeness.

3. Someone who has an idea of some stated length of space finds that he can repeat it, going from the idea of one foot (say) to that of two feet, and that by further addition he can go to three feet, and so on without ever reaching an end of his addition. This holds good whether he started with the idea of a foot, or of a mile, or of the diameter of the earth. Whatever he starts with, and however often he multiplies it, he finds that however far he has gone he has no more reason to stop—and isn’t one jot nearer the end—than he was when he set out. From this he takes the idea of infinite space.

4. That account of the source of the idea of infinite space doesn’t settle whether there actually exists a boundless space answering to the idea, because our ideas aren’t always proofs of the existence of things. Still, since the question of space’s infinity has come up here, I remark that we are apt to think that space is actually boundless; the idea of space or expansion naturally draws us in that direction. Whether we consider it as the extension of body or as existing by itself without any solid matter occupying it, the mind can’t possibly find or suppose any end of it, or be stopped anywhere in its progress in this space. Any boundary to the world of bodies—even one with diamond-hard walls—is so far from stopping the mind’s further progress in space and extension that it actually helps it to continue. When we reach the utmost extremity of body, what do we find that can put a

62

Essay II John Locke xvii: Infinity

stop, and satisfy the mind that it is at the end of space when it perceives that it is not—when, indeed, it is satisfied that body itself can move into it [= into the space outside the present material boundary]? Here is why. A body can move through empty space within the world of bodies; indeed it can’t move anywhere except into empty space (·see xiii.22·). It is clear and evident that if a body can move into an empty space interspersed amongst bodies, it must be equally possible for it to move into empty space beyond the outer boundaries of the world of bodies. That is because idea of empty pure space is exactly the same within as beyond the limits of all bodies, and there is nothing to hinder body from moving into it in either case. Thus, wherever the mind places itself by any thought, either in among bodies or far away from them, it can’t find any end anywhere in this uniform idea of space; and so it has to conclude, by the very nature and idea of each part of space, that space is actually infinite.

[Section 5 gives a similar account of how we ‘come by the idea of eternity’ or infinite duration. The question of whether any real thing lasts for ever, Locke says, isn’t answered merely by our having an idea of eternity. He holds that if something exists now, then something has existed for eternity, but he will discuss this ‘in another place’ (IV.x.2–3). and won’t discuss it here.]

6. If we get our idea of infinity from our ability to repeat our own ideas without end, you may wonder why we don’t attribute infinity to ideas other than those of space and duration. Other ideas can be as easily and as often repeated in our minds as can those of space and duration; but nobody ever thinks of infinite sweetness, or infinite whiteness, although we can repeat the idea of sweet or white as frequently as those of a yard or a day. Here is my answer. All the ideas that are considered as having parts, and can be increased by adding equal or lesser parts, give us through their repetition the idea of infinity; because this endless repetition generates a continued enlargement that cannot come to an end. But with other ideas it is not so. [Locke defends this by canvassing the possibilities for what goes on when one tries to add one idea of whiteness to another. The reason why they don’t allow of endless additions, he says, is that the idea of whiteness involves degrees but not parts. He concludes:] Those ideas that don’t consist of parts can’t be augmented to whatever proportion men please, or be stretched beyond what men have received by their senses; but space, duration, and number, being capable of increase by repetition, leave in the mind an idea of endless room for more. The latter ideas alone lead our minds towards the thought of infinity.

7. Although our idea of infinity arises from thoughts about quantity, when we join infinity to any supposed idea of quantity, and so think about an infinite quantity—an infinite space, or an infinite duration—we fall into great confusion. That is because our idea of infinity is an endlessly growing idea, while any idea the mind has of a quantity terminates in that very idea (which can’t be greater than itself); so when we try to combine them in the thought of an infinite quantity we have to adjust a standing measure to a growing volume. So I think there is serious reason to distinguish the idea of •the infinity of space from the idea of •a space that is infinite. The former is nothing but •a supposed endless progression of the mind over whatever repeated ideas of space it pleases; but to have actually in the mind the idea of •a space that is infinite is to suppose that the mind has already passed over and actually viewed all those repeated ideas of space. Even an endless repetition can never go through them all; so to suppose that one has done so is a plain contradiction.

63

Essay II John Locke xvii: Infinity

8. This may become clearer if we apply it to numbers. [Locke then presents a line of thought like that of section 7, leading to the conclusion that we have a clear and legitimate idea of the infinity of number(s) but that it is absurd to think that we can have an ‘actual idea of an infinite number’. He applies this also to ‘infinite duration’, and repeats it for ‘infinite space’. A typical episode is this:] However large an idea of space I have in my mind, it is no larger than it is at this instant when I have it, though I am capable of doubling it an instant later, and so on ad infinitum.

[In sections 9–11 Locke argues—amplifying a hint he gave in xvi.8—that when we think about the infinity of space or of duration, what we are engaged with is ‘the infinity of number applied to determinate parts of which we have distinct ideas’. thought of eternity is that of a duration that is infinitely many years long; our thought of ‘immensity’ is that of a region whose volume is infinitely many cubic yards.]

12. In any mass of matter our thoughts can never arrive at the ultimate division, so there is an apparent infinity to us in that also. It too involves the infinity of number, but with the difference that it is like division rather than addition. Still, it does involve proceeding ad infinitum, with new numbers—·smaller and smaller fractions·—all the way. A similarity: just as we can’t by addition reach the idea of an infinitely great space, so by division we are unable to reach the idea of an infinitely small body; because our idea of infinity is (so to speak) a growing or fugitive idea, always in a boundless progression, stopping nowhere.

13. Although hardly anyone is so absurd as to claim to have the positive idea of an actual infinite number,....there are people who imagine they have positive ideas of infinite duration and space. I think it would be enough to destroy any such ·purported· positive idea of something infinite to ask its owner whether he could add to it; that would easily show his mistake.... An infinite idea of space or duration must be made up of infinite parts; so ·the thought of· its infinity must consist in ·the thought of· its having parts •whose number can always be further added to; it doesn’t involve •an actual positive idea of an infinite number. It is evident that by adding together finite things (and all the lengths of which we have positive ideas are finite) we can never produce the idea of infinite in any way except the way we do with number....—adding more and more units of the same kind, without coming one jot nearer to the end of the process.

14. Those who want to prove that their idea of infinite is positive seem to do it through a ridiculous argument: the idea of an end is negative, so the idea of infinity—the negation of an end—is positive! Someone who sees that where bodies are concerned an end is just the extremity or surface of the body will not readily grant that the end is a bare negative, any more than will someone who sees that the end of his pen is black or white! Where duration is concerned, an end isn’t •the bare negation of existence but rather •the last moment of it. Also, the people I am arguing against here can’t deny that the beginning is the first instant of being, and isn’t conceived by anyone to be a bare negation; so by their own argument they should admit that the idea of an eternal past, or of a duration without a beginning, is a negative one.

[In section 15 Locke develops these views further. He agrees that when we think of (say) the infinity of space our thought does include a positive element, namely the vague thought of a really enormously large stretch of space; but he distinguishes that from a genuine thought about infinity. His crucial triple-point in this section is the following.] 1 The

64

Essay II John Locke xvii: Infinity

idea of so much is positive and clear. 2 The idea of greater is also clear, but it is only a comparative idea. 3 The idea of so much greater that it cannot be comprehended is a plain negative, not a positive. [A little later:] What lies beyond our positive idea towards infinity lies in obscurity, and has the indeterminate confusion of

a negative idea in which I know that I can’t include all that I want to, because that is too large for a finite and narrow ·mental· capacity ·such as mine·;

and that—where the greatest part of what I want to include is left out, and merely given the vague label ‘still greater’—must be very far from a positive complete idea....

[In section 16 Locke challenges those who think they have a positive idea of eternity. If there is or could be an eternally existing thing, he demands, has it lasted longer today than it had yesterday? The answer Yes strikes him as absurd because it involves different eternities, with different lengths. But the only way to support the answer No is to equate eternal duration with a kind of eternal present, to which the idea of succession, of longer and shorter durations, doesn’t apply. He aligns himself with those who find this unintelligible.]

[Section 17 repeats section 14’s point that there is nothing negative about the concept of a beginning.]

18. We can no more have a positive idea of the largest space than we can of the smallest space. The latter seems the easier of the two, and more within our intellectual reach, but really all we can manage is a comparative idea of smallness—the idea of a smallness that will always be less than any of which we have a positive idea. All our •positive ideas of any quantity, whether big or small, have bounds; though there are no bounds to the •comparative idea through which we can always add to the big or take from the small. [Locke has mostly been using ‘positive’ as the opposite of ‘negative’; but here and in some other places he uses it as the opposite of ‘relational’ or ‘comparative’.] But the part (big or small) that isn’t covered by our positive idea lies in obscurity; and we have no idea of it except the idea of the power of endlessly enlarging one and diminishing the other. The acutest thought of a mathematician can no more isolate ·the idea of· an indivisible ultimate particle of matter than a chemist wielding a pestle and mortar can ·physically· isolate such a particle. And a philosopher by the quickest flight of mind can no more reach ·a thought of· infinite space, containing it within a positive idea, than a surveyor can mark it out with his chain measure. When you think of a cube with a one-inch side, you have a clear and positive idea of it in your mind, and so can form one of ½, ¼, and so on, until you have the idea something very small. But it still isn’t the idea of that incomprehensible smallness that division can produce. What remains of smallness [Locke’s phrase] is as far from your thoughts as it was when you first began; so you never come to have a clear and positive idea of that smallness that is implied by infinite divisibility.

[Section 19 repeats the main point in a mildly joking

20. I have encountered people who agree that they cannot have a positive idea of •infinite space, but are sure they have one of •eternity. Here is my explanation for their mistaken view that the two should be treated differently. By about causes and effects, they are led to think that we must admit some eternal being, and so to consider the real of that being as matched by their idea of eternity; but on the other hand they have no argument driving them to admit the existence of some infinite body, which indeed they find absurd; and so they rush into •concluding that they can have no idea of infinite space because they can have no idea of infinite

65

Essay II John Locke xvii: Infinity

matter. [The argument about causes and effects and an eternal being is approvingly presented in IV.x.2–3.] This •inference is a poor affair, because the existence of matter isn’t necessary to the existence of space any more than the existence of motion or of the sun is necessary to duration, although duration is commonly measured by motion of the sun. A man can have the idea of ten thousand miles square without any body as big as that, as well as the idea of ten thousand years without any body as old as that.... Why should we think our idea of infinite space requires the real existence of matter to support it, when we find that we have as clear an idea of an •infinite duration to come as we have of •infinite duration past? [In the remainder of this section Locke expands these points somewhat, concluding thus:] If a man had a positive idea of infinity, whether of duration or of space, he could add two infinites together, making one infinite infinitely bigger than another—an absurdity too gross to be worth arguing against.

21. If after all this you still think you do have clear positive comprehensive ideas of infinity, enjoy your privilege! Some of us who don’t would like to hear from you about it. Until now I have been apt to think that the great and inextricable difficulties that perpetually arise in all discussions about infinity, whether of space, duration, or divisibility, have been sure signs of a defect in our ideas of infinity—namely the disproportion between •infinity itself and •how much our narrow minds can take in. Men talk and dispute about infinite space or duration, as if they had complete and positive ideas of them;....but the incomprehensible nature of the thing they are talking or thinking about leads them into perplexities and contradictions; and their minds are swamped by an object too large and mighty to be surveyed and managed by them.

22. If I have lingered rather long on duration, space, and number, and on what arises from thinking about them, namely infinity, it may be no more than the topic requires, for there are few simple ideas whose modes give more exercise to the thoughts of men than those do. I don’t claim to have treated them in their full extent; all I need is to show how the mind receives those ideas, such as they are, from •sensation and •reflection, and how even our idea of infinity—remote as it seems to be from any •object of sense or •operation of our mind—originates in sensation and reflection as do all our other ideas. Perhaps some very advanced mathematicians have other ways to introduce ideas of infinity into their minds; but this doesn’t alter the fact that even they, like all other men, first acquired their ideas of infinity from sensation and reflection in the manner I have described.

66

Essay II John Locke xviii: Other simple modes

Chapter xviii: Other simple modes

1. Perhaps I have given enough examples of simple modes of the simple ideas of sensation, going so far as to show how from simple ideas taken in by sensation the mind comes to extend itself even to infinity.... Still, for method’s sake I shall briefly describe a few more ·simple modes· before moving on to ideas that are more complex. ·Remember that in my classificatory system simple modes are complex ideas, though they are less complex than complex modes are·

2. To ‘slide’, ‘roll’, ‘tumble’, ‘walk’, ‘creep’, ‘run’, ‘dance’, ‘leap’, ‘skip’, and many others that might be named, are words for which every English-speaker has in his mind distinct ideas, which are all modifications of motion. Modes of motion correspond to those of extension: swift and slow are two different ideas of motion, measured by distances of time and space put together; so they are complex ideas comprehending time and space with motion.

3. We have a similar variety with sounds. Every articulate word is a different modification of sound; and from hearing such modifications the mind can be provided with almost infinitely many distinct ideas. [Locke also mentions the sounds of birds and beasts, and the auditory ideas that a composer may have in his mind when silently composing a tune.]

4. Ideas of colours are also very various. We pick out some of them as the different degrees or ‘shades’ (as they are called) of the same colour. But since we very seldom put different colours together for use or for pleasure without also giving a role to shape—as in painting, weaving, needle-work, etc.—the colours that we pick out for attention usually belong to mixed modes, as being made up of ideas of two kinds, shape and colour, as for example beauty, rainbow, etc.

5. All compounded tastes and smells are also modes made up of the simple ideas of those senses. But because we seldom have names for them, we take less notice of them, and they can’t be explained in writing. you’ll have to think up your own examples from your own experience.

6. Here is a point about simple modes that are considered to be merely different degrees of the same simple idea, ·e.g. slightly different shades of green·. Though many of them are in themselves entirely distinct ideas, when the difference between them is very small they ordinarily don’t have separate names, and the differences are not much taken notice of. I leave it to you to think about whether this is •because men haven’t had ways of precisely distinguishing amongst them, or rather •because distinguishing them wouldn’t yield knowledge that would be of general or necessary use.... Once the mind has acquired some simple ideas, it can variously repeat and compound them, and so make new complex ideas. ·This actually happens with some of our simple ideas and not with others·. Though white, red, sweet, etc. haven’t been modified or made into complex ideas by various combinations so as to be named and thereby sorted into kinds, some other simple ideas, namely those of unity, duration, motion, etc. (already discussed) and also power and thinking (·to be discussed in xxi and xix respectively·), have been modified into a great variety of complex ideas with names belonging to them.

[In section 7 Locke offers to explain this. The primary concerns of people have been with one another; they have mainly needed efficient ways of thinking and talking about

67

Essay II John Locke xix: Modes of thinking

their own behaviour—including the actions performed in specialized trades, for which technical terms are coined that the rest of the populace wouldn’t understand. Ideas such as those of tastes and smells haven’t had a great role in this kind of thought and speech, which is why we have few names for them. Locke undertakes to return to this in III.]

Chapter xix: The modes of thinking

1. When the mind looks in on itself and attends to its own actions, thinking is the first action it encounters. The mind observes a great variety of kinds of thinking, receiving different ideas from each. For example, the perception that accompanies and is attached to any impression made on the body by an external object gives the mind a distinct idea that we call sensation, which is, as it were, the actual entrance of any idea into the understanding by way of the senses. The same idea, when it occurs without the operation of any such object on the organs of sense, is remembrance; if it is sought by the mind and eventually, with considerable effort and difficulty, brought back into view, it is recollection. [The section continues with some others: contemplation, ‘that which the French call rêverie’, attention, ‘intention, or study’, dreaming, ecstasy. Here and in section 4 Locke uses ‘intention’ in its old sense of ‘intentness’ or ‘strenuous mental focus’.]

2. These are a few examples of the various modes of thinking that the mind can observe in itself, and so have distinct ideas of. I don’t claim to enumerate them all, or to give an extensive treatment of this set of ideas that are acquired from reflection, for that would fill a book. However, I shall later treat at some length reasoning, judging, volition, and knowledge, which are some of the most considerable operations of the mind and ways of thinking.

[Section 3 adds some detail about differences amongst attention, rêverie, and dreaming. It ends with this:] Sometimes the mind fixes itself so earnestly on thinking about some objects....that it shuts out all other thoughts, and takes no notice of the ordinary impressions that are then being made on the senses.... At other times it hardly notices the sequence of ideas that succeed in the understanding, and doesn’t pursue any of them. And at other times it lets them pass almost entirely unregarded, as faint shadows that make no impression.

4. I think everyone must have experienced within himself this difference in degree of •intention (and of its opposite, •remission) on a scale running from •earnest study at one end to •very nearly minding nothing at all at the other. Go down the scale a little further still and you find the mind in sleep—withdrawn from the senses, and out of the reach of motions made on the sense-organs that at other times produce very vivid and perceptible ideas.... In this state of withdrawal from the senses, the mind often retains a looser and less coherent manner of thinking that we call dreaming. Finally, sound sleep lowers the curtain in front

68

Essay II John Locke xx: Pleasure and pain

of the stage, putting an end to all appearances.... A side remark, ·returning briefly to the main topic of i.10–22·: We all have experience of our minds’ thinking with various degrees of intensity; even a waking man may have thoughts that are so dim and obscure as to be close to having none at all; so isn’t it probable that thinking is something the soul does but is not its essence? A thing’s •operations can easily be performed more or less intensely, but we don’t think of the •essences of things as capable of any such variation.

Chapter xx: Modes of pleasure and pain

1. Among the simple ideas that we receive from both sensation and reflection, pain and pleasure are two very considerable ones. •Bodily sensations may occur alone or accompanied by pain or pleasure; and •the thoughts or perceptions of the mind may also occur solo or else accompanied by pleasure or pain, delight or trouble, call it what you will. Like other simple ideas, these two can’t be described, nor can their names be defined; the only way to know them is by experience. A ‘definition’ of them in terms of the presence of good or evil makes them known to us only by making us reflect on what we feel in ourselves when we think about or undergo various operations of good and evil.

2. Things, then, are good or bad only in reference to pleasure or pain. [Locke wrote ‘good or evil’, but in his usage ‘evil’ means merely ‘bad’, without the extra force the word has today. When used as a noun, as in ‘presence of evil’, it is left unchanged because ‘bad’ doesn’t work well as a noun.] ·So that the attempt to define ‘pleasure’ and ‘pain’ in terms of good and evil puts things back to front·. We call something ‘good’ if it is apt to cause or increase pleasure or diminish pain in us, or else to enable us to get or retain some other good. On the other side, we call something ‘bad’ if it is apt to produce or increase pain or diminish pleasure in us or....[etc.] I am speaking of pleasure and pain of body or of mind, as they are commonly distinguished, though really they are all states of the mind—sometimes caused by disorder in the body and sometimes by thoughts of the mind.

3. Pleasure and pain and that which causes them, good and evil, are the hinges on which our passions turn. If we reflect on ourselves, and observe how these operate in us in various contexts, what states of mind and internal sensations (if I may so call them) they produce in us, this may lead us to form the ideas of our passions.

4. Anyone reflecting on the thought he has of the delight that any present or absent thing is apt to produce in him has the idea we call love. [Locke gives the example of someone who—in season and out—loves grapes.]

5. On the other side, the thought of the pain that anything present or absent is apt to produce in us is what we call hatred. If my theme were not confined to the bare ideas of our passions in their dependence on different kinds of pleasure and pain, I would remark that our love and hatred of •inanimate or unfeeling things is commonly founded on the

69

Essay II John Locke xx: Pleasure and pain

pleasure and pain we get from using them and encountering them through our senses, even if such use destroys them. But hatred or love towards •beings who are capable of happiness or misery is often the uneasiness or delight that we get just from the thought that they exist, or from the thought of their being happy.... But it suffices to note that our ideas of love and hatred are merely ·ideas of· the dispositions of the mind to experience pleasure or pain, however caused in us.

6. A man’s uneasiness over the absence of something whose present enjoyment carries the idea of delight with it is what we call desire; which is greater or less according to whether the uneasiness is more or less intense. [Locke adds some remarks about uneasiness as ‘the chief if not only spur to human industry and action’. He admits that this is off his intended path; he’ll deal with it at length in xxi.29–40.]

7. Joy is a delight of the mind from the thought of a good that one now possesses or will certainly possess in the future. We are possessed of a good when we have it in our power so that we can use it when we please. Thus a nearly starving man has joy at the arrival of food, even before he has the pleasure of eating it....

8. Sorrow is uneasiness in the mind upon the thought of a lost good that might have been enjoyed longer; or the sense of a present evil.

9. Hope is that pleasure in the mind that everyone finds in himself when he thinks about a probable future enjoyment of something that is apt to delight him.

10. Fear is an uneasiness of the mind from the thought of future evil that is likely to come to us.

11. Despair is the thought that some good is unattainable. This works variously in men’s minds, sometimes producing uneasiness or pain, sometimes slack passivity.

12. Anger is uneasiness or discomposure of the mind when one is harmed and intends to get revenge for this.

13. Envy is an uneasiness of the mind caused by the thought of a good that we desire that has been obtained by someone we think should not have had it before us.

14. These two last, envy and anger, are not caused simply by pain and pleasure, but have other ingredients in them—thoughts regarding oneself or others—which is why they aren’t to be found in all men, because some men don’t have those thoughts of their own merits (envy) or of intending revenge (anger). All the rest, which come down to purely pain and pleasure, are I think to be found in all men. For basically we •love, desire, rejoice, and hope only in respect of pleasure, and •hate, fear, and grieve only in respect of pain. In short, all these passions are moved by things only when they appear to be causes of pleasure and pain, or to be in some way associated with pleasure or pain. Thus we extend our hatred usually to the subject (at least if it is an agent that has perceptions and purposes) which has given us pain, because the fear it leaves with us is a constant pain. But we don’t so constantly love what has done us good, because pleasure doesn’t operate on us as strongly as pain does, and because we aren’t as apt to •hope that a good-doer will bring pleasure again as we are to •fear that a bad-doer will bring pain again. But this is by the way.

[In section 15 Locke repeats that he means ‘pleasure’ and ‘pain’, ‘delight’ and ‘uneasiness’, to cover mental as well as bodily ups and downs.]

16. It should further be noted that so far as the passions are concerned, the removal or lessening of a pain is considered as a pleasure and operates as such; and the loss or diminishing of a pleasure, as a pain.

70

Essay II John Locke xx: Pleasure and pain

17. Most of the passions in most persons operate on the body, causing various changes in it; but as these aren’t always perceptible, ·and indeed in some cases don’t occur at all·, they don’t make a necessary part of the idea of each passion. For example, shame, which is an uneasiness of the mind on the thought of having done something that is indecent or will lessen others’ valued esteem for us, isn’t always accompanied by blushing.

18. Don’t take me to be offering a treatise on the passions. There are many more of them than I have named; and each of those I have attended to merits a much fuller and more detailed treatment. I have mentioned these only as so many instances of modes of pleasure and pain resulting in our minds from various considerations of good and evil. I might perhaps have given instances that are simpler than these ·and don’t count as passions·, such as the pains of hunger and thirst and the pleasure of eating and drinking to remove them; the pain of sore eyes, and the pleasure of music; the pain of quarrelsome uninstructive argument, and the pleasure of reasonable conversation with a friend. But the passions are more important to us ·than the simpler pleasures and pains·, which is why I chose to focus on them and to show how our ideas of them come from sensation or reflection.

71

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

Chapter xxi: Power

1. The mind being every day informed by the senses of the alteration of the simple ideas [here = ‘qualities’] that it observes in things outside it, and

•noticing how one comes to an end and another begins to exist,

•reflecting also on what passes within itself, and observing a constant change of its ideas, sometimes by the impression of outer objects on the senses and sometimes by its own choice; and

•concluding from what it has so constantly observed to have happened that similar changes will in the future be made in the same things by similar agents and in similar ways,

•considers in one thing the possibility of having any of its simple ideas changed, and in another the possibility of making that change, and •so comes by that idea that we call power. Thus we say that fire has a power to melt gold, and gold has a power to be melted....; that the sun has a power to blanch wax, and wax a power to be blanched by the sun.... In all such cases the power we think of is in reference to the change of perceivable ideas, for we can’t observe or conceive any alteration to be made in a thing except by observing or conceiving a change of some of its ideas.

2. Power is twofold—the ability to make a change, and the ability to be changed; one may be called active, the other passive power. [In Locke’s usage, ‘power’ doesn’t mean ‘strength’; our nearest word to it is ‘ability’ or ‘capability’; sugar’s (passive) power to be dissolved in hot water is simply its being able to be thus dissolved.] God is entirely above passive power; and perhaps matter lacks all active power, so that only created minds have powers of both sorts; but I shan’t go into that question. My present business isn’t to enquire into what things have power, but rather to explore how we come by the idea of it. Still, I thought it worthwhile to make the foregoing remarks, directing our minds to the thought of God and minds for the clearest idea of active powers ·because otherwise that might have been lost sight of in what follows·. We shall see that active powers loom large in our complex ideas of natural substances, and I shall speak of such substances as having active powers, following common assumptions about them, even though they may not be such genuinely active powers as our casual thoughts are apt to represent them. That is why I have thought it worthwhile to direct our mind to God and spirits for the clearest idea of active power.

3. ·In xii.3 I announced that the three great categories of complex ideas are those of •modes, •substances, and •relations. We are still not finished with •modes. And yet·: I admit that power includes in it some kind of •relation—to action or to change—but then all our ideas turn out on close inspection to involve a relational element. ideas of extension, duration, and number all contain a secret relation of the parts. Shape and motion have something relative in them, much more obviously. As for sensible qualities such as colours and smells etc.—what are they but the powers of different bodies in relation to our perception? As for their basis in the things themselves, they depend on the volume, shape, texture, and motion of the parts, all of which include some kind of relation in them. So our idea of power, I think, ·being no more relational than any of the others·, is entitled to a place among the simple ideas, and be considered as one of them, being one of the ideas that make a principal

72

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

ingredient in our complex idea of substances, as we shall see later. [Locke should have said ‘a place among the simple modes’, which he has classified as complex ideas—see xii.5.]

4. We are abundantly provided with the idea of passive power by almost all sorts of perceptible things. In most of them we can’t help noticing that there are continual changes in their sensible qualities, and indeed a continual turn-over in the stuff they are made of; and from this we reasonably infer that they go on being liable to similar changes ·which is to attribute to them a •passive power to be thus changed·. We are at least as richly provided with examples of •active power (which is the more proper meaning of the word ‘power’), because whatever change we observe, the mind must infer ·an active· power somewhere to make that change, as well as ·a passive power·, a possibility in the thing to undergo the change. But if we think about it hard we’ll see that bodies don’t give us through our senses as clear and distinct an idea of active power as we get from reflecting on the operations of our minds. All power relates to action, and there are just two sorts of action of which we have any idea, namely •thinking and •motion. So let us consider from where we get our clearest ideas of the powers that produce these actions. 1 Body gives us no idea of thinking; it is only from reflection that we have that. 2 Neither does body give us any idea of the beginning of motion. A motionless body doesn’t give us any idea of any active power to move; and when a body is put in motion, that motion is a •passion in it rather than an •action [= ‘something with respect to which it is •passive rather than •active’]. For when the ball obeys the motion of a billiard cue, that isn’t any action on its part but mere passion; and when it hits another ball and sets it in motion, it only communicates the motion it had received from something else and loses in itself so much as the second ball received. This gives us only a very obscure idea of an active power of moving in body, because all we see the body do is to transfer motion, not to produce it. For it is a very obscure idea of power that doesn’t stretch as far as •the production of an action, and merely takes in •the continuation of a passion. That’s all that is involved in the movement of a body that is put into motion: its continuing to move after it has been set in motion is no more an action on its part than is its continuing to be flat after something has flattened it. The idea of the beginning of motion is one that we get only from reflection on what happens in ourselves, where we find by experience that merely by willing something—merely by a thought of the mind—we can move parts of our bodies that have been at rest. So it seems to me that our sensory perception of the operations of bodies gives us only a very imperfect and obscure idea of active power, since it provides no idea of the power to begin any action, whether physical or mental. If you think you have a clear idea of power from your observations of colliding bodies, I shan’t quarrel with you, because sensation is one of the ways by which the mind gets its ideas. But I thought it worthwhile to consider—just in passing—whether the mind doesn’t receive its idea of active power more clearly from reflection on its own operations than from any external sensation.

5. This at least seems to me evident:- We find in ourselves a power to begin or not begin, and to continue or end, various actions of our minds and motions of our bodies, by a mere thought or preference of the mind in which it commands (so to speak) that such and such an action be done or that it not be done. This power that the mind has to order that a given idea be thought about or that it not be thought about, or to prefer that a given part of the body move rather than stay still (or vice versa), is what we call the will. The actual exercise

73

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

of that power in a particular case is what we call volition or willing. If your doing x (or not doing y) results from such an order or command of the mind, your doing x (or not doing y) is called voluntary. And any action that is performed without such a thought of the mind is called involuntary. The power of perception is what we call the understanding. Perception, which is the act of the understanding, is of three sorts: 1 the perception of ideas in our minds; 2 the perception of the meanings of signs; 3 the perception of the connection or inconsistency, agreement or disagreement, that there is between any ·two· of our ideas. All these are attributed to the understanding, or perceptive power, though in ordinary parlance we are said to ‘understand’ only with the latter two, not with the mere perception of ideas in our minds.

6. These powers of the mind, namely of perceiving and of preferring, are usually called two faculties of the mind. The word ‘faculty’ is proper enough as long as it isn’t allowed to breed confusion in men’s thoughts by being taken to stand for some real beings—·some things·—in the soul that perform those actions of understanding and volition. For when we say

the will is the commanding and superior faculty of the soul,

the will is (or is not) free,

the will determines the inferior faculties,

the will follows the dictates of the understanding,

and so on, statements like these can carry a clear and distinct sense, for anyone who attends carefully to his own ideas, and whose thoughts follow the evidence of things rather than the sound of words. But I suspect that this talk about ‘faculties’ has misled many into a confused notion of active things in us,....and that this has led to wrangling, obscurity, and uncertainty in questions relating to them.

7. Everyone, I think, finds in himself a power to begin or not begin, continue or put an end to, various actions in himself. From thoughts of the extent of this power of the mind over the actions of the man the ideas of liberty and necessity arise. ·These two ideas have been at the heart of an enormous amount of philosophical wrangling, encouraged by much confusion. I shall try to sort all that out in the next twenty sections. In section 28 I shall turn to other topics, though freedom will return to the spotlight in sections 47–56·.

8. A man is free to the extent that he has the power to think or not, to move or not, according to the preference or direction of his own mind. (The only •actions of which we have any idea boil down to •thinking and •moving, which is why I mention only them.) Whenever it is not equally in a man’s power to do something x or not to do it—i.e. whenever doing it is not the case that

•if the preference of his mind directs him to do x, he will do x, and

•if the preference of his mind directs him not to do x, he won’t do x,

he isn’t free, isn’t at liberty, is under necessity. Thus, there can’t be liberty where there is no thought, no volition, no will; but there may be thought, will, volition, where there is no liberty. Some examples make this clear.

9. Nobody thinks that a tennis-ball, whether moving because it has been hit or lying still on the ground, is a free agent. Why? Because we don’t think of a tennis-ball as thinking or (therefore) as having any volition, any preference of motion to rest or vice versa. Lacking volition, the ball comes under our idea of necessary, and that is how we describe it. Another example: a man is crossing a bridge when it collapses, pitching him into the river below; he doesn’t have liberty in this, and isn’t a free agent. He does have volition, and prefers

74

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

his not falling to his falling, but not-falling isn’t within his power and so doesn’t follow from his volition; and therefore in this matter he isn’t free. A third example: a man strikes himself or a friend through a convulsive movement of his arm that it isn’t in his power—by volition or the direction of his mind—to stop or refrain from; and nobody thinks he has liberty in this; everyone sympathizes with him, as acting by necessity and constraint.

10. ·A fourth example·: a man is carried while fast asleep into a room where there is a person he has been longing to see and speak with; and he is there locked in securely; when he awakes he is glad to find himself in such desirable company, which he stays in willingly, preferring his staying to his going away. Nobody will doubt, I think, that his staying is voluntary; and yet it is clear that being locked in he isn’t at liberty not to stay. So liberty is not an idea belonging to •volition or preferring [Locke’s exact words], but to •the person’s having the power of doing or not doing something, according to what his mind chooses or directs. idea of liberty reaches as far as that power and no further. The moment that power is restrained, or some compulsion removes one’s ability to act or refrain from acting, liberty is extinguished.

11. We have examples of this—sometimes too many!—in our own bodies. A man’s heart beats, and the blood circulates, and it isn’t in his power by any thought or volition to stop either process; and therefore in respect to these motions he isn’t a free agent. Convulsive motions agitate his legs, so that although he wills it ever so much he can’t by any power of his mind stop their motion (as in that strange disease called St. Vitus’s dance) but he is perpetually dancing; he isn’t at liberty in this action—he has to move, just as does as a tennis-ball struck with a racket. On the other side, paralysis or the stocks prevent his legs from obeying the decision of his mind when it prefers that they take his body elsewhere. In all these there is a lack of freedom; though the sitting still even of a paralytic, while he prefers it to a removal, is truly voluntary. Voluntary then is not opposed to necessary, but to involuntary. For a man may prefer what he can do to what he can’t do; he may prefer the state he is in to its absence or change, even though necessity makes it unalterable.

12. As with the motions of the body, so with the thoughts of our minds: where any thought is such that we have power to take it up or set it aside according to the preference of the mind, there we are at liberty. A waking man being under the necessity of having some ideas constantly in his mind, is not at liberty to think or not think, any more than he is at liberty to touch other bodies or not—·given that he touches the ground he stands on·. But whether he turns his thoughts from one idea to another is often within his choice; and then he is as much at liberty in respect of his ideas as he is in respect of bodies he stands on; in each case he can move from one to another as he pleases. Still, just as some bodily movements are unavoidable, so some ideas are unavoidable by the mind, which can’t drive them away by the utmost effort it can use. A man on the rack isn’t at liberty to set aside the idea of pain and distract himself with other thoughts; and sometimes a boisterous passion hurries our thoughts along as a hurricane does our bodies, without leaving us free to think about other things that we would rather choose. But we consider the man as a free agent again as soon as •his mind regains the power to stop or continue, begin or not begin, any of these thoughts or bodily movements according as •it thinks fit to prefer either to the other.

13. Necessity occurs where thought is lacking, and where thought is present but doesn’t have the power to direct

75

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

the behaviour. If an agent ·has thought and· is capable of volition, but •starts or continues some action that is contrary to the preference of his mind, that is called compulsion; if he •stops or restricts an action when this is contrary to his volition, this is called restraint.

14. If I am right about all this, consider whether it might help to put an end to the question Is man’s will free or not? This has been long agitated, but I think it is unreasonable because unintelligible. It follows from what I have said that the question itself is as improper and meaningless as Is man’s sleep swift or not? and Is man’s virtue square or not? because liberty no more applies to the will than speed does to sleep or squareness to virtue. Liberty, which is a power, belongs only to agents, and cannot be an attribute of the will, which is only another power.

15. It is so difficult to convey in words clear notions of internal actions that I must warn you that my words ‘ordering’, ‘directing’, ‘choosing’, ‘preferring’, etc. will not distinctly enough tell you what volition is unless you reflect on what you yourself do when you will. For example, ‘preferring’, though it seems perhaps best to express the act of volition, doesn’t do it precisely. A man would prefer flying to walking, yet who can say he ever wills himself to fly? Clearly, volition is an act of the mind knowingly exerting that control it takes itself to have over any part of the man, ·so that we can’t will ourselves to fly because we know that we can’t do so·. [The rest of this section repeats material from preceding sections.]

16. Plainly the will is simply one power or ability, and freedom is another; so that to ask whether the will has freedom is to ask whether one power has another power, whether one ability has another ability—a question too obviously and grossly absurd to argue about or to need an answer. For anyone can see that powers belong only to •agents, and are attributes only of •substances, and not of powers themselves! So that the question ‘Is the will free?’ contains the question ‘Is the will a substance, an agent?’, since freedom can properly be attributed only to acting substances. If freedom can with any propriety of speech be applied to ·any· power, it is to the power a has man to affect movements of parts of his body by his choice or preference. But his having that power is what entitles him to be called ‘free’; indeed, that power is freedom. So now we have the question ‘Is freedom free?’, and if anyone asked that, we would conclude that he didn’t know what he was talking about. It would be like someone who, knowing that ‘rich’ was a word to express the possession of riches, asks ‘Are riches rich?’—making himself a candidate for Midas’s ears!

17. But the absurdity is somewhat disguised—its meaning somewhat hidden—when men speak of the will as a ‘faculty’ ·and slip into thinking of it as an active substance rather than as a power, which is what it really is·. As soon as it is made clear that the will is merely the power to do something, the absurdity of saying that it is or isn’t free plainly reveals itself. If it were reasonable to think and talk of faculties as distinct beings that can act (‘The will orders’, ‘The will is free’), it would also be all right to have a speaking faculty, a walking faculty, and a dancing faculty, and to think and talk of these as producing the relevant actions—‘The singing faculty sings’, ‘The dancing faculty dances’. And when we say such things as that •the will directs the understanding, or •the understanding obeys or disobeys the will, this is no more correct and intelligible than to say that the power of speaking directs the power of singing, or the power of singing obeys or disobeys the power of speaking.

[Section 18 continues that last point, criticising the state-

76

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

ment that ‘the understanding operates on the will, or the will on the understanding’, as though a power could operate on a power.]

19. I grant that this or that •thought may be the occasion of a •volition, that is, of a man’s exercising the power he has to choose; and that the •choice of the mind may cause the man’s •thinking about this or that thing. (Similarly, the singing of a tune may cause the dancing of a dance, or vice versa.) But in all these cases it isn’t one power that operates on another. Rather, the mind operates and exerts these powers; it is the man that does the action, it is the agent that has power or ability. For powers are relations, not agents; and the only thing that can be free or not free is •that which has or lacks the power to operate, not •the power itself....

[Section 20 continues with the theme of the misuse of the notion of a faculty. Of course the mind and the body have faculties, because that is to have powers; and they couldn’t operate if they had no power to operate. The trouble comes when faculties are treated as things, agents, rather than as powers; and Locke provides examples.]

21. To return now to the enquiry about liberty, I think the proper question is not Is the will free? but Is a man free? ·There are two ways of taking the former question; I shall deal with one in the remainder of this section, and the other in sections 22–4·. [Locke then repeats the position he has already laid out: that freedom consists in the ability to act in the manner one’s mind chooses. ‘How can we think anyone freer than to have the power to do what he will?’ He concludes:] So that in respect of actions within the reach of such a power in him, a man seems as free as it is possible for freedom to make him.

22. But the inquisitive mind of men who want to clear themselves of guilt as far as they can, even if that involves putting themselves into a worse state than that of total necessity, is not content with this notion of freedom. For their purposes freedom isn’t useful unless it goes further than this. And so we find people arguing that a man isn’t free at all unless he is as free to will as he is free to do what he wills. So a further question about liberty is raised, namely Is a man free to will? Arguments about whether the will is free are, I think, really about this. Here is my answer to it.

[In sections 23–4 Locke presents one basic point: If at some time you have in your mind the question of whether to start walking right now, and you do have the power to start walking and also the power not to do so, you cannot be free with respect to the relevant act of volition. Either you will start walking or you won’t; whichever it is will be an upshot of your choosing to walk or choosing not to; so you cannot get out of making an act of the will settling the matter; and so your act of the will is not free. In such a case, whatever you do will be ‘unavoidably voluntary’.]

25. Plainly, then, a man is hardly ever at liberty whether to will or not to will. But a new question arises: Is a man at liberty to will which of the two he pleases, motion or rest? This question is so obviously absurd that it might suffice to convince people that the question of freedom shouldn’t be asked about the will. To ask whether a man is at liberty to will either motion or rest, speaking or silence, whichever he pleases, is to ask, whether a man can will what he wills, or be pleased with what he is pleased with. This needs no answer, I think; and those who insist on asking it must suppose that one act of will arises from another, which arises from yet another, and so on ad infinitum.

26. The best way to avoid such absurdities is to establish in our minds definite ideas of the things we are talking about. If the ideas of liberty and volition were well fixed in our

77

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

understandings, and if we kept them in our minds through all the questions that are raised about liberty and volition, it would be easier (I think) to resolve most of the difficulties that perplex men’s thoughts and entangle their understandings; because it would be easier for us to see where the obscurity arose from •the nature of the thing under discussion and where it arose merely from •the confused meanings of some words.

27. First then, it should be borne in mind that freedom consists in the dependence on our volition ·or preference· of

an action’s being done or not done,

not in the dependence on our preference ·or volition· of

any action or its contrary.

A man standing on a cliff is at liberty to leap twenty yards downwards into the sea, not because he has a power to do the contrary action, which is •to leap twenty yards upwards (for he has no such power), but because he has a power to leap or •not to leap.... A prisoner in a room twenty feet square, when he is at the north side of the room, is at liberty to walk twenty feet southward because he can walk or •not walk it; but he isn’t at the same time at liberty to do the contrary, i.e. to •walk twenty feet northward. Freedom, then, consists in our being able to act or not to act according as we shall choose or will. ·With that I leave the topic of freedom until I re-engage with it in section 47·.

28. Secondly, we must remember that volition or willing is an act of the mind directing its thought to the performing of some action and thereby exerting its power to produce it. In the interests of brevity I ask permission to use the word ‘action’ to include also refraining from action. When walking or speaking are proposed to the mind, sitting still and staying silent are mere non-actions, but they need the determination of the will as much as walking and speaking do, and they are often as weighty in their consequences as the other two, the real actions. Those are reasons for counting such refrainings as actions too, but anyway I am doing so for brevity’s sake.

29. Thirdly, to the question What determines the will? the true answer is The mind. The will is the general power of directing action this way or that; it is a power that the agent has; and what determines its exercise in a given case is the agent, the mind, exercising its power in some particular way. If you aren’t satisfied with this answer, then you must be asking What determines the will? with the meaning What moves the mind, in every particular instance, to perform the particular act of volition that it does perform? ·This is an intelligible and respectable question, which doesn’t involve treating the will as an agent or anything like that·. To this question I answer:

The motive for •continuing in the same state or action is one’s present satisfaction in it; the motive to •change is always some uneasiness.

The only thing that ever leads us to will a change of state or the performing of a new action is some uneasiness ·with our present state or action·. This is the great motive that works on the mind, getting it to act. For brevity’s sake I shall call this determining the will. I shall explain it at more length.

30. First, though, I must say something about terminology. Volition is a very simple act, and if you want to understand what it is you will do better by •reflecting on your own mind and observing what it does when it wills than by •any variety of verbal explanations. Yet I have tried to put it into familiar words by using the terms ‘prefer’ and ‘choose’ and their like, and these ·are not really right because they· signify desire as well as volition.... I find the will often confounded with....desire, and one put for the other.... I think that this

78

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

has frequently led to obscurity and mistake in this matter, and should be avoided as much as possible. If you turn your thought inwards onto what goes on in your mind when you will, you’ll see that the will or power of volition has to do only with actions and non-actions that the mind takes to be in its power. So the will is quite different from desire, which may go directly against the will in a particular case. [Locke gives two examples, this being one: A man may be suffering pain, knowing that the only way for him to relieve it would give him other, worse, physical ailments. So he wants the pain to go away, but he doesn’t will any action that would make it go away.] This makes it evident that desiring and willing are two distinct acts of the mind, and thus that the will (the power of volition) is distinct from desire.

31. To return then to the question What determines the will in regard to our actions? I used to accept the widespread opinion—·to which I shall return in section 35·—that what determines the will is the greater good in view; but I now think that what does it is some uneasiness that the man is at present under. That is what determines the will from moment to moment, getting us to behave as we do. This uneasiness can be called desire, for that’s what it is: desire is an uneasiness of the mind for the lack of some absent good. All bodily pain of whatever kind, and all disquiet of the mind, is uneasiness; and it is always accompanied by—and indeed is hardly to be distinguished from—a desire that is equal to the pain or uneasiness that is being felt. For desire being an uneasiness in the lack of an absent good, in the case of pain the absent good is ease, freedom from the pain; and until ease is attained we can call the uneasiness ‘desire’, for nobody feels pain without wanting to be eased of it, with a desire equal ·in intensity· to that pain. Besides this desire for ease from pain—·which is essentially a desire for something negative·—there is also desire for absent positive good; and here also the desire and uneasiness are equal. The more strongly we desire any absent good the more intensely are we in pain from not having it. But the intensity of the pain doesn’t vary with •how great the good is or is thought to be—only with •the strength of the desire for it. Absent good can be contemplated without desire. But when there is desire there is an equally intense uneasiness.

32. Everyone who reflects on himself will quickly find that desire is a state of uneasiness. Everyone has felt in desire what the wise man says of hope (which isn’t much different from it) ‘that it being deferred makes the heart sick’ [Proverbs 13:12], and that the greatness of the desire sometimes raises the uneasiness to a level where it makes people cry out ‘Give me children, give me the thing desired, or I die’ [Genesis 30:1]. Life itself, with all its enjoyments, is a burden that cannot be borne under the lasting and unremoved pressure of such an uneasiness.

33. It is true that good and evil, present and absent, work on the mind; but what immediately determines the will to each voluntary action is the uneasiness of desire, fixed on some absent good—whether the good be negative (such as the absence of pain) or positive (such as pleasure). I shall now try to show, by argument and from experience, that it is indeed this uneasiness that determines the will to the series of voluntary actions of which the greatest part of our lives is made up.

34. When a man is perfectly content with the state he is in, and thus is without uneasiness, there is nothing to move him to stop being in that state. Observe yourself and you’ll see that this is right. And so we see that our All-wise Maker has put into us the uneasiness of hunger and thirst and other natural desires, which return at the proper time and

79

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

determine our wills for the preservation of ourselves and the continuation of our species. If the mere thought of those good ends had been sufficient to determine the will and set us to work, it is reasonable to think we would then have had none of these natural pains, and perhaps in this world little or no pain at all. ‘It is better to marry than to burn’, says St. Paul, [1 Corinthians 7:9] exhibiting what chiefly drives men into the enjoyments of the married state. There is more power in •the push of a little actual burning than •the pull of the prospect of greater pleasures.

35. It is so widely and confidently accepted that what determines the will is good, the greater good, that I am not surprised that I took this view for granted when I first published on this topic ·in the first edition of this Essay·. And I suspect that many readers will blame me not for that but rather for my present retraction. But when I looked harder into the matter, I was forced to conclude that even what a person knows to be the greater good doesn’t determine his will until his desire has been correspondingly raised and has made him uneasy in his lack of the good in question. [Locke gives the example of a poor man who agrees that affluence is better than poverty, but who isn’t uneasy over his poverty and therefore doesn’t bestir himself to get rich; and the example of a man who knows that virtue brings advantages, but who does nothing about it because he doesn’t ‘hunger and thirst after righteousness’. He writes colourfully of the alcoholic whose knowledge of what would be better for him leads him frequently to resolve to give up drinking, but doesn’t lead him actually to give it up because] the uneasiness to miss his accustomed delight returns, the acknowledged greater good loses its hold, and the present uneasiness determines his will to start drinking again. He may at the same time make secret promises to himself that he won’t drink any more—that this is the last time he’ll act against the attainment of those greater goods. And thus he is from time to time in the state of that unhappy complainer who said Though I see and approve the better, I follow the worse. We have constant experience of the truth of this for many people at many times; I know of no way except mine to make this fact intelligible.

36. Experience makes it evident that uneasiness alone operates on the will; but why is this so? ·In answering this, I shall assume that whenever volition occurs there is some uneasiness, the question being why it and not something else acts immediately on the will in every case·. The answer is that at any given time only one item can determine our will, and it naturally happens that uneasiness takes that role ·to the exclusion of anything else that might take it·. The reason for that is that while we are in a state of uneasiness we can’t sense ourselves as being happy or on the way to happiness, because everyone finds that pain and uneasiness are inconsistent with happiness, spoiling the savour even of the good things that we do have. So our will always, as a matter of course, chooses the removing of any pain ·or uneasiness· that we still have, as the first and necessary step towards happiness.

37. Here is another possible reason why the will is ·immediately· determined only by the will ·and not by the prospect of greater good. The greater good is only prospective, lying in a possible future; it isn’t present and actual. Uneasiness is the only relevant factor that is ·present; and it is against the nature of things that something absent should operate where it is not. ·So a merely future possible good cannot operate in the actual present.· You may object that absent good can, through thought, be brought home to the mind and made to be present. The idea of it may indeed be

80

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

in the mind and viewed as present there; but for •something that is in the mind in that way to counter-balance the removal of an uneasiness that we have, •it must raise our desire to a point where the uneasiness of that prevails over the other uneasiness in determining the will. Until that happens, the idea in the mind of some good is there only in the way other ideas are, as merely something to think about—not operating on the will and not setting us to work. (I shall give the reason for this shortly.)....

[In section 38 Locke writes at length about the fact of sinful conduct by people who really do believe that they are risking the loss of eternal joy in heaven. This would be inexplicable if mere unaided beliefs about the good could determine the will, because in that case those beliefs would surely always prevail. But their frequent failure to do so can be understood if one brings in Locke’s thesis that uneasiness is what determines the will. Near the end he writes:] Any intense pain of the body, the ungovernable passion of a man violently in love, or the impatient desire for revenge, keeps the will steady and focussed; and the will that is thus determined never lets the understanding set its object aside; all the thoughts of the mind and powers of the body are uninterruptedly employed in one direction by the determination of the will, which is influenced by that towering uneasiness as long as it lasts.... ·That completes my defence of my view that uneasiness is always what immediately determines the will. The notion of uneasiness will go on working for me, but won’t itself be the topic of further discussion·.

39. Up to here my examples of uneasiness have mainly concerned desire. That kind of uneasiness is the chief determinant of desire, and the one we are most conscious of; and it seldom happens that the will orders an action without some desire being involved. (I think that is why the will and desire are so often taken to be one and the same thing.) Still, some part in the story should be given to kinds of uneasiness that make up or at least accompany the other passions. Aversion, fear, anger, envy, shame, etc. each have their uneasiness too, which is how they influence the will. Each of those passions usually comes mixed with others,....and I think that desire is nearly always an element in the mix. I am sure that wherever there is uneasiness there is desire. Here is why: we constantly desire happiness; and to the extent that we feel uneasiness, to that extent we lack happiness ·and therefore desire to have it·.... Also, the present moment is not our eternity! However greatly we are enjoying the present, we look beyond it to the future, and desire goes with that foresight, and it carries the will with it. So that even in joy, what keeps up the action on which the enjoyment depends is the desire to continue it and the fear of losing it....

40. We are attacked by various uneasinesses, distracted by different desires, which raises the question: which of them takes precedence in determining the will to the next action? The answer is that ordinarily it the most pressing of them. (That is, the most pressing of the ones that the person thinks can be removed; for the will can never be moved towards something it then thinks is unattainable....) What ordinarily determines the will in that series of voluntary actions that makes up our lives is at each moment the most important and urgent uneasiness that we feel at that time. Don’t lose sight of the fact that the proper and only object of the will is some action of ours, and nothing else. The only outcome we can produce by willing is an action of our own, so that is as far as our will reaches.

41. If it is further asked What is it that moves desire?, I answer: Happiness, and that alone. ‘Happiness’ and ‘misery’

81

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

are the names of two extremes whose outer bounds we don’t know.... But we have very lively impressions of some degrees of each, made by various instances of delight and joy on the one side, and torment and sorrow on the other. For brevity’s sake I shall bring all these under the labels ‘pleasure’ and ‘pain’, because there is pleasure and pain of the mind as well as of the body.... Indeed, strictly speaking they are all of the mind, though some arise in the mind from thought, others in the body from certain modifications of motion.

42. Happiness then in its full extent is the utmost pleasure we are capable of, and misery the utmost pain.... Now because pleasure and pain are produced in us by the operation of certain objects on our minds or our bodies, and in different degrees, anything that is apt to produce pleasure in us we call ‘good’, and what is apt to produce pain we call ‘bad’, just because it is apt to produce in us the pleasure or pain that constitutes our happiness or misery. Further, even when what is apt to bring us some degree of pleasure is in itself good, and what is apt to produce some degree of pain is bad, we often don’t call it so because it is in competition with a •greater of its sort.... If we rightly estimate what we call ‘good’ and ‘bad’, we shall find it lies to a large extent in •comparison: the cause of every lesser degree of pain, as well as every greater degree of pleasure, has the nature of good, and vice versa.

43. Although good is the proper object of desire in general, sometimes a man’s desire remains unmoved by the prospect of good, because he doesn’t regard that good as a necessary part of his happiness. Everyone constantly pursues happiness, and desires whatever contributes to it; other acknowledged goods a person can look at without desire, pass by, and be content to go without. There is pleasure in knowledge, and many men are drawn to sensual pleasures. Now, let one man place his satisfaction in sensual pleasures, another in the delight of knowledge; each admits there is great pleasure in what the other pursues; yet neither makes the thing that delights the other a part of his happiness, and their desires are not moved that way. (As soon as the studious man’s hunger and thirst make him uneasy,....his desire is directed towards eating and drinking, though possibly not caring much what food he gets to eat. And on the other side, the epicure buckles down to study when shame, or the desire to look good to his mistress, makes him uneasy in his lack of some sort of knowledge.) Thus, however intent men are in their pursuit of happiness, a man may have a clear view of good—great and acknowledged good—without being concerned for it or moved by it, if he thinks he can be happy without it. But men are always concerned about pain, ·which is an intense uneasiness·. They can feel no uneasiness without being moved by it. And therefore whenever they are uneasy from their lack of some good that they think they need for their happiness, they start to desire it.

44. Something that each of us can observe in himself is this: although •the greater visible good doesn’t always raise a man’s desires in proportion to the greatness he acknowledges it to have, •every little trouble moves us and sets us to work to get rid of it. The nature of our happiness and misery makes it evident why this should be so. Any present pain, of whatever kind, makes a part of our present misery; but the absence of a good doesn’t necessarily do so. If it always did, we would be constantly and infinitely miserable, because there are infinite degrees of happiness that we don’t possess. So when we are free of all uneasiness, a moderate portion of good is enough to keep us content in the present; and a fairly

82

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

low level of pleasure in a series of ordinary enjoyments adds up to a happiness with which most of us can be satisfied. (If this were not so, there’d be no room for the obviously trivial actions that we so often exercise our wills on, voluntarily spending much of our lives on them—a pattern of conduct that couldn’t persist if our will or desire were constantly directed towards the greatest apparent good.) Few people need go far afield to be convinced that this is so. In this life, indeed, most people who are happy to the extent of having a constant series of moderate pleasures with no admixture of uneasiness would be content to continue in •this life for ever; even though they can’t deny that there may be a state of eternal durable joys in an •after-life, far surpassing all the good that is to be found in this one. In fact they can’t avoid realizing that such a wonderful after-life is more possible than is their getting and keeping the pittance of honour, riches, or pleasure that they are now pursuing to the neglect of that eternal state. And yet,

•with a clear view of this difference, •satisfied of the possibility of a perfect, secure, and lasting happiness in a future state, and •quite sure that it is not to be had in this life while they limit their happiness to some little enjoyment and exclude the joys of heaven from making a necessary part of it,

still their desires are not moved by this greater apparent good, nor are their wills determined to any action or effort towards its attainment.

[In section 45 Locke discusses at length the phenomenon of people not being moved to seek what they believe are very great long-term goods because their wills are activated by little present uneasinesses aimed at smaller goods that they think of as necessary for their happiness. These dominant uneasinesses may be for food, drink and so on, but there are also ‘fantastical’ uneasinesses directed at honour, power, riches, etc. ‘and a thousand other irregular desires that custom has made natural to us’. When we are in pain, misery, uneasiness, Locke says, the first thing we need, in order to become happy, is to get out of that state; and in that situation:] the absence of absent good does not contribute to our unhappiness, and so the thought of absent good—even if we have it, and admit that the item in question would be good—is pushed aside to make way for the removal of the uneasinesses that we feel. This situation will change only if appropriate and repeated contemplation of an absent good •brings it nearer to our mind, •gives us a taste of that good, and •raises in us some desire. That desire then starts to contribute to our present uneasiness, and competes with our other uneasinesses in the push to be satisfied; and if it exerts enough pressure it will in its turn come to determine the will.

46. By thoroughly examining any proposed good, we can raise our desires to a level that is proportional to how good it is, and then it may come to work on the will, and be pursued....wills are influenced only by the uneasinesses that are present to us; while we have any of those they are always soliciting, always ready at hand to give the will its next push. When any balancing goes on in the mind, ·it isn’t a balancing of prospective goods against one another; rather· it concerns only which desire will be the next to be satisfied, which uneasiness the next to be removed. So it comes about that as long as any uneasiness, any desire, remains in our mind, there is no room for good—considered just in itself as good—to come at the will or to have any influence on it....

47. Despite what I have said ·in section 40·, it doesn’t always happen that the greatest and most pressing uneasiness determines the will to the next action. As we find in

83

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

our own experience, the mind is usually able to suspend acting on some one of its desires, and so—taking them one at a time—to suspend acting on any of them. Having done this, the mind is at liberty to consider the objects of its desires—·the states of affairs that it wants to bring about·—to examine them on all sides and weigh them against others. In this lies man’s liberty; and all the mistakes, errors, and faults that we run into in living our lives and pursuing happiness arise from not availing ourselves of this liberty, and instead rushing into the determination of our wills, going into action before thinking enough about what we are aiming at. ability to suspend the pursuit of this or that desire seems to me to be the source of all freedom; it is what so-called ‘free will’ consists in. When we exercise it and then act, we have done our duty, all that we can or ought to do in pursuit of our happiness; and it isn’t a fault but a perfection of our nature to desire, will, and act according to the last result of a fair examination.

48. This is so far from confining or weakening our freedom, that it is the very essence of it; it doesn’t cut short our liberty, but brings it to its proper goal; and the further we are removed from such a determination—·that is, from being made to act by the judgments we have made and the uneasinesses that result from them·—the nearer we are to misery and slavery. If the mind were perfectly indifferent [= ‘in perfect balance’] about how to act, not fixed by its last judgment of the good or evil that is thought to attend its choice, that would be a great imperfection in it. A man is at liberty to lift his hand to his head, or let it rest in his lap; he is perfectly indifferent as between these, and it would be an imperfection in him if he lacked that power—·that is, if he were unable to lift his hand, or unable not to lift it, given that no desire of his selects one course of action rather than the other·. But it would be as great an imperfection if he had the same indifference as between lifting his hand and not lifting it in a situation where by raising it he would save himself from a blow that he sees coming. It is as much a perfection that desire (or the power of preferring) should be determined by good as that the power of acting should be determined by the will; and the more certain such determination is, the greater is the perfection. Indeed, if we were determined by anything but the last result of our judgments about the good or evil of an action, we would not be free....

49. If we think about those superior beings above us who enjoy perfect happiness—·that is, the angels in heaven·—we shall have reason to judge that they are more steadily determined in their choice of good than we are; and yet we have no reason to think they are less happy or less free. And if such poor finite creatures as us were entitled to say anything about what infinite wisdom and goodness could do, I think we might say that God himself cannot choose what is not good; his freedom does not prevent his being determined by what is best.

50. Would anyone choose to be an imbecile so as to be less determined by wise thoughts than a wise man? Is it worth the name of ‘freedom’ to be at liberty to play the fool, and draw shame and misery upon oneself? Breaking loose from the conduct of reason, and lacking that restraint of examination and judgment that keeps us from choosing or doing the worse—if that is liberty, true liberty, then madmen and fools are the only free men! Anyone who chose to be mad for the sake of such ‘liberty’ would have to be mad already. I don’t think that anybody thinks that our liberty is restricted in a way we might complain of by the fact that we are constrained to act so as to secure the happiness that we constantly desire. God Almighty himself is under

84

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

the necessity of being happy; and the more any thinking being is under that necessity, the nearer it comes to infinite perfection and happiness. To protect us—ignorant and short-sighted creatures that we are—from mistakes about true happiness, we have been given a power to suspend any particular desire and keep it from determining the will and engaging us in action. This is •standing still when we aren’t sure enough of which way to go. Examination ·of the possibilities· is •consulting a guide. The determination of the will after enquiry is •following the direction of that guide. And someone who has a power to act or not to act, according as such determination of the will directs, is free; such determination doesn’t limit the power in which liberty consists. Someone who has his chains knocked off and the prison doors opened for him is perfectly at liberty, because he can either go or stay, as he chooses, even if his preference is determined to stay because of the darkness of the night, the badness of the weather, or his lack of anywhere else to sleep. He doesn’t stop being free, although his desire for some convenience gives him a preference—all things considered—for staying in his prison.

[Section 51 continues with this theme.]

52. The liberty of thinking beings in their constant pursuit of true happiness turns on the hinge of their ability in particular cases to

suspend this pursuit until they have looked forward ·in time· and informed themselves about whether the particular thing they want and are considering pursuing really does lie on the way to their main end, really does make a part of the ·happiness· that is their greatest good.

By their nature they are drawn towards happiness, and that requires them to take care not to mistake or miss it; and so it demands that they be cautious, deliberate, and wary about how they act in pursuit of it. Whatever necessity requires us to pursue real happiness, the same necessity with the same force requires us to suspend action, to deliberate, and to look carefully at each successive desire with a view to discovering whether the satisfaction of it—·rather than promoting our happiness·—won’t interfere with our true happiness and lead us away from it. This, it seems to me, is the great privilege of finite thinking beings; and I ask you to think hard about whether the following isn’t true:

The course of men’s behaviour depends on what use they make of their ability to suspend their desires and stop them from determining their wills to any action until they have examined the good and evil of the contemplated action, fairly and with as much care as its importance merits. This ability is what brings freedom into the lives of men—all the freedom they have, all they can have, all that can be useful to them. This ·suspension of desire, followed by deliberation·, is something we can do, and when we have done it we have done our duty, all we can do, all we need to do.

Since the will needs knowledge to guide its choice, all we can do is to hold our wills undetermined until we have examined the good and evil of what we desire. What follows after that follows in a chain of consequences linked one to another, all depending on the last ruling of the judgment; and we have power over whether that ruling comes from a hasty and precipitate view or from a due and mature examination.

[In section 53 Locke writes about how greatly people vary in their tastes and in what they think would make them happy, and urges the importance of our exercising our freedom to suspend judgment and give ourselves time for further reflection and enquiry. In extreme cases one can’t do this,

85

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

for example a man under torture may be unable to refrain from telling his torturers right now what they want to know. And ‘love, anger, or any other violent passion’ may have the same effect. But we should work on freeing ourselves from being dominated in that manner. He continues:] In this we should •take trouble to bring it about that whether something is to our mind’s taste depends on the real intrinsic good or bad that is in it, and •not permit an admitted or supposed possible great good to slip out of our thoughts without leaving any taste of itself, any desire for it, until by adequate thought about its true worth we form an appetite in our mind that is suitable to it, and make ourselves uneasy in the lack of it or in the fear of losing it.... Let no-one say he can’t govern his passions, can’t prevent them from taking over and sweeping him into action; for what you can do before a prince or a great man you can do alone or in the presence of God, if you want to.

54. How does it come about that, although all men desire happiness, their wills carry them in such contrary directions and thus carry some of them to do bad things? What I have said makes it easy to answer this, which I do as follows. The various and contrary choices that men make show •not that they don’t all pursue good but •rather that different people find different things good—that we don’t all place our happiness in the same thing, or choose the same way to get it. If we were concerned only with how things go in this life, the explanation of why •one man devotes himself to study and knowledge and •another to hawking and hunting, why •one chooses luxury and debauchery and •another sobriety and riches, would not be because some of these didn’t aim at their own happiness but because different things make them happy. So the physician was right in what he said to his patient who had sore eyes: ‘If you get more pleasure from the taste of wine than from the use of your sight, wine is good for you; but if the pleasure of seeing is greater to you than that of drinking, wine is bad.’

55. The mind has its own taste for things, as well as the palate; and you’ll do no better trying to delight all men with riches or glory....than trying to satisfy all men’s hunger with cheese or lobsters.... As •pleasant tastes depend not on the things themselves but on how they suit this or that particular palate (and palates vary greatly), so also •the greatest happiness consists in having the things that produce the greatest pleasure and not having any that cause disturbance or pain. Now these, to different men, are very different things. So if men have nothing to hope for in an after-life, if this is the only life in which they can enjoy anything, it is neither strange nor unreasonable that they should seek their happiness by avoiding all the things that disease them here and pursuing all that delight them ·here·—and it’s not surprising that there should be much variety and difference among these. For if there is no prospect beyond the grave, the inference is certainly right: ‘let us eat and drink,’ let us enjoy what we delight in, ‘for tomorrow we shall die’ [Isaiah 22:13]. This, I think, may serve to show us why men pursue different ends even though the desires of all of them are bent on happiness. It can happen that men choose different things and they all choose rightly—if we suppose them ·to have no prospect of an after-life, which involves supposing them· to be merely like a crowd of poor insects—some of them bees delighting in flowers and their sweetness, others beetles enjoying other kinds of food—all of them able to enjoy themselves for a season, after which they go out of existence for ever.

56.....Liberty plainly consists in a power to do or not to do, as we choose. This much in undeniable; but it seems to

86

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

cover only the actions of a man resulting from his volition, so there remains the question Is he at liberty to will or not?’ ·In sections 23–4· I have answered that in most cases a man isn’t at liberty to refrain from the act of volition: he must exert an act of his will through which the proposed action is done or ·one through which it is· not done. Still, in one kind of case a man is at liberty in respect of willing, namely in choosing a remote good as an end to be pursued. Here a man can suspend choosing either for or against the thing proposed until he has examined whether it really is—or really will lead to—something that will make him happy. Once he has chosen it, thereby making it a part of his happiness, it raises desire, which gives him a corresponding uneasiness, which determines his will, which sets him to work in pursuit of his choice. This shows us how a man can deserve punishment, even though in all his particular actions he necessarily wills what he then judges to be good. His will is always determined by whatever is judged good by his understanding, but that doesn’t excuse him if by a too hasty choice of his own making he has adopted wrong measures of good and evil—judgments which, however false they are, have the same influence on all his future conduct as if they were true. He has spoiled his own palate, and must take responsibility for the sickness and death that follows from that.... What I have said may help to show us why men prefer different things and pursue happiness by contrary courses. But since men are always constant and in earnest about happiness and misery, the question still remains How do men come to prefer the worse to the better, and to choose what they admit has made them miserable?

[In section 57 Locke sketches an answer to his question. Some of the variation, and especially some of the conduct that isn’t conducive to the happiness of the agent, is due to 1 ‘causes not in our power’, such as extreme pain, overwhelming terror, and so on. The other source of counterproductive behaviour is 2 wrong judgment. Locke deals briefly with 1 in this section, and devotes sections 58–68 to 2.]

58. I shall first consider the wrong judgments men make of future good and evil, whereby their desires are misled. Nobody can be wrong about whether his present state, considered just in itself and apart from its consequences, is one of happiness or misery. Apparent and real good are in this case always the same; and so if every action of ours ended within itself and had no consequences, we would never err in our choice of good; we would always infallibly prefer the best....

59. But our voluntary actions don’t carry along •with them in their present performance all the happiness and misery that •depend on them. They are prior causes of good and evil that come to us after the actions themselves have passed and no longer exist. So our desires look beyond our present enjoyments, and carry the mind forward to any absent good that we think is needed to create or increase our happiness. The absent good gets its attraction from the belief that it is needed for happiness. Without that belief we are not moved by absent good. In this life we are accustomed to having a narrow range, in which we enjoy only one pleasure at a time; and when we have such a single pleasure and have no uneasiness, the pleasure is enough to make us think we are happy; and we aren’t affected by all remote good, even when we are aware of it. Because our present enjoyment and freedom from pain suffices to make us happy, we don’t want to risk making any change.... But as soon as any new uneasiness comes in, our happiness is disturbed and we are set to work again in the pursuit of happiness.

87

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

60. One common reason why men often are not raised to the desire for the greatest absent good is their tendency to think they can be happy without it. While they think that, the joys of a future state don’t move them; they have little concern or uneasiness; and the will, free from the determination of such desires ·for distant-future goods·, is left to pursue nearer satisfactions, removing those uneasinesses that it feels from its lack of them and its longing for them. [The remainder of this section develops this line of thought, applying it especially to those who ignore the prospects of the after-life in their pursuit of relatively trivial earthly pursuits. The section concludes:] For someone who—·unlike a bee or a beetle·—has a prospect of the different state that awaits all men after this life, a state of perfect happiness or of misery depending on their behaviour here, the measures of good and evil that govern his choice are utterly changed. For no pleasure or pain in this life can be remotely comparable to the endless happiness or intense misery of an immortal soul in the after-life, so his choices about how to act will depend not on the passing pleasure or pain that accompanies or follows them •here but on whether they serve to secure that perfect durable happiness •hereafter.

61. To understand in more detail the way men often bring misery on themselves, although they all earnestly pursue happiness, we must consider how things come to be misrepresented to our desires. That is done by the ·faculty of· judgment telling untruths about them. To see what causes wrong judgments, and what their scope is, we must note that things are judged good or bad in a double sense. In the strict and proper sense, only pleasure is good, only pain bad. But things that draw pleasure and pain after them are also considered as good and bad, because our desires—those of any creature with foresight—aim not only at present pleasure and pain but also at whatever is apt to cause pleasure or pain for us at a later time.

62. The wrong judgment that often misleads us and makes the will choose the worse option lies in misreporting the various comparisons of these ·consequences that I have just mentioned·. I am not talking about one person’s opinion about someone else’s choices, but of the choices a man makes that he himself eventually admits were wrong. Now, it is certain that every thinking being seeks happiness, which consists in the enjoyment of pleasure without much uneasiness mixed into it; and it is impossible that anyone should willingly slip something nasty into his own drink, or leave out anything in his power that would help to complete his happiness—impossible, that is, unless he has made a wrong judgment.... ·Such judgments are of two kinds: 1 about the relative goodness or badness of items considered just in themselves, and 2 about what the consequences will be of various items. I’ll discuss 1 in sections 63–5, and 2 in sections 66–7. Yet another kind of judgment will be discussed in section 68·.

63. When we compare present pleasure or pain with future (which is usually the case in most important questions about what to do), we often make wrong judgments about them, measuring them differently because of our different temporal distances from them. Nearby objects are apt to be thought to be bigger than ones that are actually bigger but are further away; and so it is with pleasures and pains, with which the present is apt to win the contest. Thus most men, like spendthrift heirs, are apt to judge a little in hand to be better than a great deal to come. But everyone must agree—whatever his values are—that this is a wrong judgment. That which is future will certainly come to be present, and then, having the same advantage of nearness, will show itself in

88

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

its full size, revealing the mistake of someone who judged it by unequal measures. [In the remainder of the section Locke develops this point at some length, with special reference to the drinker who knows he’ll have a hangover in the morning.]

64. It is because of the weak and narrow constitution of our minds that we judge wrongly when comparing present pleasure or pain with future. We can’t thoroughly enjoy two pleasures at once, much less enjoy a pleasure—with a few exceptions—while pain possesses us. A present pleasure, if it isn’t feeble to the point of hardly being a pleasure, fills our narrow souls, taking up the whole mind so as to leave hardly any room for thoughts of absent things. Even if among our pleasures there are some that aren’t strong enough to exclude thoughts about things in the future, we so intensely hate pain that a little of it extinguishes all our pleasures. So we come to desire to be rid of the present evil, whatever the cost; we are apt to think that nothing absent can equal it, because in our present pain we find ourselves incapable of any degree of happiness.... Nothing, we passionately think, can exceed—hardly anything can equal—the uneasiness that now sits so heavily on us. And not having a present pleasure that is available is a pain, often a very great one, with one’s desire being inflamed by a near and tempting object. So it is no wonder that that operates in the same way that pain does, lessens future goods in our thoughts, and so forces us blindfold (so to speak) into the embraces of the nearby pleasure.

[In section 65 Locke makes the point that in our judgments about possible future pleasure ‘of a sort we are unacquainted with’ we are apt, if that pleasure is in competition with something that is closer in time, to underestimate the former on the ground that if we actually had it we would find that it didn’t live up to its billing. He continues:] But this way of thinking is wrong when applied to the happiness of the after-life.... For that life is intended ·by God· to be a state of happiness, so it must certainly be agreeable to everyone’s wish and desire.... The manna in heaven will suit everyone’s palate....

66. When there is a question of some action’s being good or bad in its consequences, we have two ways of judging wrongly. 1 We may underestimate how bad a given bad consequence would be. 2 We may underestimate the probability that a given bad upshot will be a consequence of the proposed action—allowing ourselves to believe wrongly that the threatened consequence may somehow be avoided, e.g. by hard work, skill, nimbleness, change of character, repentance, etc. I could show, case by case, that these are wrong ways of judging; but I shall merely offer the following general point. It is very wrong and irrational to risk losing a greater good in order to get a lesser one on the basis of uncertain guesses and before the matter has been examined as thoroughly as its importance demands. Everyone must agree with this, I think, especially if he considers the usual causes of this wrong judgment, of which I now describe three.

67. One is ignorance. Someone who judges without informing himself as fully as he can is guilty of judging amiss. The second is carelessness, when a man overlooks things that he does know. This is a sort of self-induced temporary ignorance, which misleads our judgments as much as the other. Judging is like balancing an account to see whether there is profit or loss; so if either column is added up in a rush, resulting in the omission of some figures that ought to be included, this haste causes as wrong a judgment as if it were perfect ignorance. What usually causes it is the domination by some present pleasure or pain. understanding and

89

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

reason were given us so that we won’t rush in, but instead will search and see and then judge. Understanding without liberty would be useless, and liberty without understanding (if there could be such a thing) would signify nothing. If a man sees what would do him good or harm, make him happy or miserable, without being able to move one step towards or from it, what good is it to him that he sees it? And if someone is at liberty to ramble in perfect darkness, how is his liberty any better than if he were driven up and down as a bubble by the force of the wind? Being acted on by a blind impulse from •within oneself is no better than being acted on by one from •outside. So the first great use of liberty is to hinder blind headlong rushing; the principal exercise of freedom is to stand still, open the eyes, look around, and take a view of the consequences of what we are going to do—doing all this with as much thoroughness as the weight of the matter requires. I shan’t here explore this matter further.... I shall consider only one other kind of false judgment, which I think I ought to mention because it has great influence though it may usually be overlooked.

68. All men desire happiness, that’s past doubt; but when they are rid of pain they are apt to settle for any pleasure that is readily available or that they have grown to be fond of, and to be satisfied with that, and thus to be happy until some new desire disturbs that happiness and shows them that they are not happy. Some goods exclude others; we can’t have them all; so we don’t fix our desires on every apparent greater good unless we judge it to be necessary to our happiness; if we think we can be happy without it, it doesn’t move us. This brings up a third way in which men judge wrongly, namely by thinking something not to be necessary to their happiness when really it is so. This can mislead us •in our choice of goods to aim at and •in the means we adopt to achieve a good. We are encouraged to think that some good would not contribute to our happiness by the real or supposed unpleasantness of the actions needed to achieve it, for we tend to find it so absurd that we should make ourselves unhappy in order to achieve happiness that we don’t easily bring ourselves to it.

69. ·We now come to a fourth and final kind of error—not exactly an error of judgment—that men can make in their approach to issues concerning goods and happiness. Before presenting it, we need to grasp a background fact·. It is evident that in many cases a man has it in his power to change the pleasantness and unpleasantness that accompanies a given sort of action. It’s a mistake to think that men can’t come to take pleasure in something they used to dislike or regard with indifference. In some cases they can do it just by careful thinking; in most cases they can do it by practice, application, and habit. Bread or tobacco may be neglected even when they are shown to be useful to health, because of an indifference or dislike for them. But thought about the matter recommends that they be tried, and if they are tried the person finds that they are pleasant after all, or else through frequent use they become pleasant to him. This holds in the case of virtue also. Actions are pleasing or displeasing, either in themselves or considered as a means to a greater and more desirable end. [Locke the makes the point that •careful thought about the good to be attained may make one reconciled to the unpleasantness of the means to it, whereas •‘use and practice’ can lead one to enjoy those means, finding them pleasant after all.] Habits have powerful charms. They put so much easiness and pleasure into what we accustom ourselves to doing that we can’t give it up without uneasiness. Though this ·fact about human nature· is very visible, and everyone’s experience

90

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

displays it to him, it is much neglected as a help to men in their achievement of happiness. So neglected, indeed, that many people will think it paradoxical to say ·as I do· that men can make things or actions more or less pleasing to themselves, and in that way remedy something that is responsible for great deal of their wandering....

70. I shan’t go on about how men mislead themselves by wrong judgments and neglect of what is in their power. That would make a volume, and it isn’t my business. ·But there is one point about it that I shall present here because it is so important·. If someone is so unreasonable as to fail to think hard about infinite happiness and misery, he isn’t using his understanding as he should. The •rewards and punishments of the after-life that the Almighty has established as the enforcements of his law have enough weight to determine the choice, against •whatever pleasure or pain this life can show. For this to be so, the eternal state has only to be regarded as a bare possibility, and nobody could question that. Exquisite and endless happiness is a possible consequence of a good life here, and the contrary state the possible reward of a bad one; and someone who accepts this must admit that his judgment is wrong if he doesn’t conclude that a virtuous life (which may bring the certain expectation of everlasting bliss) is to be preferred to a vicious one (with the fear of that dreadful state of misery that may overtake the guilty, or at best the terrible uncertain hope of annihilation). This would obviously hold good even if the virtuous life here had nothing but pain, and the vicious one brought continual pleasure; which in fact is far from the case.... The •worst that comes to the pious man if he is wrong ·is that there is no after-life, which· is the •best that the wicked man can get if he is right. With ·possible· infinite happiness on the virtue side of the balance and ·possible· infinite misery on the vice side, it would be madness to choose the latter.... •If the good man is right, he will be eternally happy; if he is wrong, he won’t be miserable—he won’t feel anything. On the other side, •if the wicked man is right, he won’t be happy (·he won’t feel anything·); if he is wrong, he’ll be infinitely miserable.... I have said nothing about the certainty or probability of a future state, because I have wanted to show the wrong judgment that anyone must admit that he is making—on his own principles—if he prefers the short pleasures of a vicious life while he is certain that an after-life is at least possible.

71.....In correcting a slip that I had made in the first edition of this work, I was led to my present view about human liberty ·which I now repeat, before arguing against a rival view that I didn’t mention earlier·.

Liberty is a power to act or not act according as the mind directs. A power to direct the operative faculties to motion or rest in particular instances is the will. What determines the will to any change of operation is some present uneasiness, which is—or at least is always accompanied by—desire. Desire is always moved to avoid evil, because a total freedom from pain is always a necessary part of our happiness. But a ·prospective· greater good may fail to move desire, because it doesn’t make a necessary part of the person’s happiness or because he thinks it doesn’t. All that we ever desire is to be happy. But although this general desire of happiness operates constantly and invariably, the satisfaction of any particular desire can be suspended from determining the will until we have maturely examined whether the apparent good in question really does make a part of our real happiness. What we judge as a result of that examination is what ultimately determines us. A man couldn’t be free if

91

Essay II John Locke xxi: Power

•his will were determined by anything other than •his own desire, guided by •his own judgment.

I know that some people equate a man’s liberty with his being, before his will is determined, indifferent—·that is, able to go either way·. I wish those who lay so much stress on this supposed indifference had told us plainly whether it comes •before the thought and judgment of the understanding as well as •before the decree of the will. ·It may seem that they have to say that it does·. For it is pretty hard to place the indifference between them, that is, immediately after the judgment of the understanding and before the determination of the will; because the determination of the will immediately follows the judgment of the understanding. On the other hand, to equate liberty with an indifference that precedes the thought and judgment of the understanding places it in such darkness that we can neither see nor say anything of it. At any rate, it gives ‘liberty’ to something that isn’t capable of having it, because we all agree that no agent is capable of liberty except as a consequence of thought and judgment. If liberty is to consist in indifference, then, it must be an indifference that remains after the judgment of the understanding and indeed after the determination of the will ·because, as we have seen, it cannot occur before both, and cannot come between them either·. That, however, isn’t •an indifference of the man. He has judged whether it is best to act or not to act ·and has decided or chosen accordingly·, so he isn’t now indifferent. Rather, it is •an indifference of his operative powers: they are equally able to operate and to refrain from operating now, after the will’s decree, just as they were before it; if you want to call this ‘indifference’, do so! This indifference gives a man a kind of freedom: for example, I have the ability to move my hand or to let it rest; that operative power is ‘indifferent’ as between moving and not moving; I am then in that respect perfectly free. My will determines that operative power to keep my hand still; but I am free, because my operative power remains indifferent as between moving and not moving; my will has ordered the keeping-still of my hand, but the power to move it hasn’t been lost or even lessened; that power’s indifference as between moving and not moving is just as it was before the will commanded, as can be seen if the will puts it to the trial by ordering that my hand move. It would be otherwise if my hand were suddenly paralysed, or (on the other side) if it were set moving by a convulsion; in those cases, the indifference of the operative faculty is lost. That is the only sort of indifference that has anything to do with liberty.

[Section 72 opens with Locke saying that he has spent so long on liberty because of the topic’s importance. He also reports that the view about liberty that he presented in the first edition came to seem to him wrong, and expresses some pride in his willingness to admit to his errors and to correct them. In the remainder of the section he returns to something he said in section 4, namely that when bodies move their movement is given to them by other bodies, so that this is passive rather than active power. He now remarks that many mental events exhibit passive rather than active power, for example when the mind acquires an idea ‘from the operation of an external substance’. He concludes:] This reflection may be of some use to preserve us from mistakes about powers and actions that we can be led into by grammar and the common structure of languages—the point being that grammatically ‘active’ verbs don’t always signify action. When for example I see the moon or feel the heat of the sun, the verbs are active but what they report is no action by me but only the passive reception of ideas from external bodies. On the other hand, when I turn my eyes another way, or move my body out of the sunbeams, I

92

Essay II John Locke xxii: Mixed modes

am genuinely active, because I put myself into that motion of my own choice, by a power within myself. Such an action is the product of active power.

73. So now I have presented in compact form [chapters ii-xxi] a view of our original [here = ‘basic’] ideas, out of which all the rest are made up. I believe that hard philosophical work would show that all our ideas come down to these very few primary and original ones:

extension

solidity

mobility, or the power of being moved.

We get these ideas from bodies, through our senses. Also (coining two new words, which I think will be useful):

perceptivity, or the power of perception or thinking

motivity, or the power of moving.

We get these from our own minds, through reflection. When we add

existence

duration

number

which come to us through sensation and reflection, we may have completed the list of original ideas on which the rest depend. For I think that these would suffice to explain the nature of colours, sounds, tastes, smells, and all our other ideas, if only we had faculties acute enough to perceive the textures and movements of the minute bodies that produce in us those sensations ·of colour, taste, and so on·. But it is no part of my purpose in this book to investigate scientifically the textures and structures of bodies through which they have the power to produce in us the ideas of their sensible qualities. For my purposes it is enough to note that gold or saffron has a power to produce in us the idea of yellow, and snow or milk the idea of white, which we can only have by our sight; I needn’t explore the physics of what gives them those powers. Though ·I’ll say just this about the causes of those powers·: when we go beyond the bare ideas in our minds and start to think about their causes, we can’t conceive anything in a sensible object through which it could produce different ideas in us except the sizes, shapes, numbers, textures, and motions of its imperceptible parts.

Chapter xxii: Mixed modes

1. In the foregoing chapters ·xiii–xxi· I have discussed simple modes, showing through examples of some of the most important of them what they are and how we come by them. Now I am ready to consider the ideas that we call mixed modes. Examples are the complex ideas of obligation, drunkenness, a lie, etc., which I call mixed modes because they consist of combinations of simple ideas of different kinds, unlike the more simple modes, which consist of simple ideas all of the same kind. These mixed modes are distinguished from the complex ideas of substances by the fact that they are not looked upon to be typical marks of any real beings that have a steady existence, and are only

93

Essay II John Locke xxii: Mixed modes

scattered and independent ideas put together by the mind.

2. Experience shows us that the mind gets its simple ideas in a wholly passive manner, receiving them all from the existence and operations of things presented to us by sensation and reflection; we can’t make such an idea for ourselves. But mixed modes—our present topic—are quite different in their origin. The mind often exercises an active power in making these several combinations: once it has some simple ideas, it can assemble them into various complexes, thus making a variety of complex ideas, without examining whether they exist together in that way in nature. I think that is why these ideas are called notions, implying that they have their origin and their constant existence more in the thoughts of men than in the reality of things. To form such ideas it sufficed that the mind puts the parts of them together, and that they were consistent in the understanding, without considering whether they had any real being; though I don’t deny that some of them might be taken from observation. The man who first formed the idea of hypocrisy might either have •taken it at first from observing someone who made a show of good qualities that he didn’t really have, or else have •formed that idea in his mind without having any such pattern to fashion it by. ·There must be cases of the latter sort·. For it is evident that in the beginning of languages and societies of men, some of their complex ideas....must have been in men’s minds before they existed anywhere else; and that many names standing for such complex ideas were in use before the combinations they stood for ever existed.

3. Now that we have languages that abound with words standing for such combinations, one common way of acquiring these complex ideas is through explanations of ·the meanings of· the terms that stand for them. Because such an idea consists of a number of simple ideas combined, the words standing for those simple ideas can be used to explain what the complex one is. This procedure requires only that the pupil understand those names for simple ideas; he needn’t ever have encountered this particular combination of them in the real world. In this way a man can come to have the idea of sacrilege or murder without ever seeing either of them committed.

4. What gives a mixed mode its unity? How do precisely these simple ideas come to make a single complex idea? In some cases the combination doesn’t exist in nature, so that can’t be the source of the idea’s unity. I answer that the idea gets its unity from the mind’s act of combining those simple ideas and considering them as one complex idea of which those are the parts; and the giving of a name to the complex idea is generally viewed as the final stage in the process of combination. For men seldom think of any collection of simple ideas as making one complex one unless they have a name for it. Thus, though the killing of an old man is as fit in nature to be united into one complex idea as the killing of one’s father, because the former has no name (comparable with ‘parricide’ for the latter) it isn’t taken for a particular complex idea....

5. Of all the combinations of simple ideas that are, in the nature of things, fit to be brought together into complex ideas, men select some for that treatment and neglect others. Why? The answer lies in the purposes for which men have language. The purpose of language is for men to show their thoughts, or to communicate them to one another, as quickly as possible; so men usually make and name the complex modes for which they have frequent use in everyday life and conversation; and ones that they seldom have occasion to mention they leave loose, without names to tie them together. When they do need to speak of one of these combinations,

94

Essay II John Locke xxii: Mixed modes

they can do so through the names of their constituent simple ideas. The alternative is to trouble their memories with the burden of too many complex ideas that they seldom or never have any occasion to make use of.

[In sections 6–7 Locke gets two explanations out of his view that complex-idea words are coined when needed. It explains, he says in section 6, why every culture has words that aren’t strictly translatable into the language of others; and (in section 7) why within a single language the meanings of words constantly change. He then returns to his main theme:] If you want to see how many different ideas are in this way wrapped up in one short sound, and how much of our time and breath is thereby saved, try to list all the ·simple· ideas that are involved in the meaning of ‘reprieve’ or ‘appeal’!

8. Mixed modes are fleeting and transient combinations of simple ideas; they have a short existence everywhere except in the minds of men, and even there they exist only while they are thought of; their greatest permanency is in their names, which are therefore apt to be taken for the ideas themselves. If we ask where the idea of a triumph....exists, it is evident this collection of ideas could not exist all together anywhere in the thing itself, for a triumph is an action that stretches through time, so that its constituents could never all exist together. [Locke is using ‘triumph’ in its sense of ‘victory parade’.] This will be dealt with more extensively when I come to treat of words and their use ·in Book III·, but I couldn’t avoid saying this much at the present stage.

9. So there are three ways in which one can acquire a complex idea of a mixed mode. •By experience and observation of things themselves: by seeing men wrestle, we get the idea of wrestling. •By invention, putting together several simple ideas in our own minds: he that first invented printing had an idea of it in his mind before it ever existed. The most usual way, •by explaining the names of actions we never saw or notions we can’t see, enumerating all the ideas that are their constituent parts.... All our complex ideas are ultimately resolvable into simple ideas out of which they are built up, though their immediate ingredients (so to speak) may also be complex ideas. The mixed mode that the word ‘lie’ stands for is made of these simple ideas:

•Articulate sounds.

•Certain ideas in the mind of the speaker.

•Those words the signs of those ideas.

•Those signs put together by affirmation or negation, otherwise than the ideas they stand for are ·related· in the mind of the speaker.

I don’t think I need to go any further in the analysis of that complex idea we call a lie. What I have said is enough to show that it is made up of simple ideas, and it would be tedious to enumerate every particular simple idea that goes into this complex one.... All our complex ideas....can ultimately be resolved ·or analysed· into simple ideas, which are the only materials of knowledge or thought that we have or can have. There is no reason to fear that this restricts the mind to too scanty a supply of ideas: think what an inexhaustible stock of •simple modes we get from number and shape alone! So we can easily imagine how far from scanty our supply of •mixed modes is, since they are made from the various combinations of different simple ideas and of their infinite modes....

10. The simple ideas that have been most modified, and had most mixed ideas (with corresponding names) made out of them are these three: thinking and motion (which cover all action) and power (from which these actions are thought to flow). Action is the great business of mankind, and the

95

Essay II John Locke xxii: Mixed modes

whole subject-matter of all laws; so it is no wonder that all sorts of modes of thinking and motion should be attended to, their ideas observed and laid up in the memory, and names assigned to them. Without all this, laws could not be well made, or vice and disorders repressed. Nor could men communicate well with one another if they didn’t have such complex ideas with names attached to them. So men have equipped themselves with settled names, and supposedly settled ideas in their minds, of kinds of •actions distinguished by their causes, means, objects, ends, instruments, time, place, and other circumstances, and also of their •powers to perform those actions. For example, boldness is the •power to speak or do what we want, publicly, without fear or disorder.... When a man has acquired a power or ability to do something through doing it frequently, we call that a ‘habit’; when he has a power that he is ready to exercise at the drop of a hat, we call it a ‘disposition’. Thus ·for example· testiness is a disposition or aptness to be angry. Summing up: Let us examine any modes of action, for example

•consideration and assent, which are actions of the mind,

•running and speaking, which are actions of the body,

•revenge and murder, which are actions of both together;

and we shall find them to be merely collections of simple ideas that together make up the complex ideas signified by those names.

11. Power is the source of all action; and the substances that have the powers, when they exert a power to produce an act, are called causes; and what comes about by the exerting of that power—a substance that is produced, or simple ideas [here = ‘qualities’] that are introduced into any subject—are called effects. The efficacy through which the new substance or idea is produced is called action in the subject that exerts the power, and passion in the subject in which any simple idea is changed or produced. Although this efficacy takes many forms, I think that in thinking beings it is conceivable only as modes of •thinking and •willing, and in bodies only as modifications of •motion. If there is any kind of action other than these, I have no notion or idea of it; and so it is far from my thoughts, apprehensions, and knowledge, and I am as much in the dark about it as I am about five extra senses or as a blind man is about colours. Many words that seem to express some action, really signify nothing of the action—nothing of the how of it—but merely the effect together with some facts about •the thing that causes or •the thing upon which the cause operates. Thus, for example, creation and annihilation contain in them no idea of the action or how it is produced, but merely of the cause and the thing done. Similarly, when a peasant says ‘Cold freezes water’, although the word ‘freeze’ seems to import some ·specific kind of· action, all it really means ·in the mouth of the peasant· is that water that was fluid has become hard, implying no idea of the action through which this is done.

[In section 12 Locke remarks that his purpose has been to show how words with complex meanings can be defined, not actually to define them all.]

96

Essay II John Locke xxiii: Ideas of substances

Chapter xxiii: Complex ideas of substances

1. The mind is supplied with many simple ideas, which come to it through the senses from outer things or through reflection on its own activities. Sometimes it notices that a certain number of these simple ideas go constantly together, and it presumes them to belong to one thing; and—because words are suited to ordinary ways of thinking and are used for speed and convenience—those ideas when united in one subject are called by one name. Then we carelessly talk as though we had here one simple idea, though really it is a complication of many ideas together. What has happened in such a case is that, because we can’t imagine how these simple ideas could exist by themselves, we have acquired the habit of assuming that they exist in (and result from) some substratum, which we call substance. [‘Substratum’ = ‘what underlies’ = something that serves as the basis or foundation of something else.]

2. So that if you examine your notion of pure substance in general, you’ll find that your only idea of it is a supposition of an unknown support of qualities that are able to cause simple ideas in us—qualities that are commonly called ‘accidents’. If anyone were asked •‘What is the subject in which colour or weight inheres?’, he would have to reply ‘In the solid extended parts’; and if he were asked •‘What does that solidity and extension inhere in?’, he wouldn’t be in a much better position than the Indian philosopher who said that the world was supported by a great elephant, and when asked what the elephant rested on answered ‘A great tortoise’. Being further pressed to know what supported the broad-backed tortoise, he replied that it was something he knew not what. So too here, as in all cases where we use words without having clear and distinct ideas, we talk like children who, being asked ‘What’s this?’ about something they don’t recognize, cheerfully answer ‘It’s a thing’. Really all this means, when said by either children or adults, is that they don’t know what it is, and that ‘the thing’ they purport to know and talk about isn’t something of which they have any distinct idea at all—they are indeed perfectly in the dark about it. So the idea of ours to which we give the general name ‘substance’, being nothing but the supposed but unknown support of those qualities we find existing and which we imagine can’t exist ‘sine re substante’—that is, without some thing to support them—we call that support substantia; which, according to the true meaning of the word, is in plain English standing under or upholding. [‘Sub’ is Latin for ‘under’, and ‘stans’ is Latin for ‘standing’; so ‘substans’ (English ‘substance’) literally means something that stands under something.]

3. In this way we form an obscure and relative idea of substance in general. ·It is relative because it isn’t an idea of what substance is like in itself, but only an idea of how it •relates to something else, namely the qualities that it •upholds or stands under·. From this we move on to having ideas of various sorts of substances, which we form by collecting combinations of simple ideas that we find in our experience tend to go together and which we therefore suppose to flow from the particular internal constitution or unknown essence of a substance. Thus we come to have the ideas of a man, horse, gold, water, etc. If you look into yourself, you’ll find that your only clear idea of these sorts of substances is the idea of certain simple ideas existing together. It is the combination of ordinary qualities observable in iron, or a diamond, that makes the true complex idea of those kinds of substances—kinds that a smith or a jeweller commonly

97

Essay II John Locke xxiii: Ideas of substances

knows better than a philosopher does. Whatever technical use he may make of the term ‘substance’, the philosopher or scientist has no idea of iron or diamond except what is provided by a collection of the simple ideas that are to be found in them—with •one further ingredient. complex ideas of substances are made up of those simple ideas plus •the confused idea of some thing to which they belong and in which they exist. So when we speak of any sort of substance, we say it is a thing having such or such qualities: body is a thing that is extended, shaped, and capable of motion; •spirit, a thing that can think; and we say that hardness and power to attract iron are qualities to be found in a loadstone, ·conceived of as a thing containing these qualities·. [Loadstone is a kind of rock that is naturally magnetic.] These and similar ways of speaking show that the substance is always thought of as some thing in addition to the extension, shape, solidity, motion, thinking, or other observable ideas, though we don’t know what it is. [Locke uses •‘spirit’, as he does ‘soul’, to mean merely ‘thing that thinks’ or ‘thing that has mental properties’. It doesn’t mean something spiritual in any current sense of the term.]

4. So when we talk or think of any particular sort of corporeal substances—e.g. horse, stone, etc.—although our idea of it is nothing but the collection of simple ideas of qualities that we usually find united in the thing called ‘horse’ or ‘stone’, still we think of these qualities as existing in and supported by some common subject; and we give this support the name ‘substance’, though we have no clear or distinct idea of what it is. We are led to think in this way because we can’t conceive how qualities could exist unsupported or with only one another for support.

5. The same thing happens concerning the operations of the mind—thinking, reasoning, fearing, etc. These can’t exist by themselves, we think, nor can we see how they could belong to body or be produced by it; so we are apt to think that they are the actions of some other substance, which we call ‘spirit’. We have as clear a notion of the substance of •spirit as we have of •body. The latter is supposed (without knowing what it is) to be •the substratum of those simple ideas that come to us from the outside, and the former is supposed (still not knowing what it is) to be •the substratum of the mental operations we experience within ourselves. Clearly, then, we have as poor a grasp of the idea of bodily substance as we have of spiritual substance or spirit. So we shouldn’t infer that there is no such thing as spirit because we have no notion of the substance of spirit, any more than we should conclude that there is no such thing as body because we have no clear and distinct idea of the substance of matter.

6. Whatever the secret, abstract nature of substance in general may be, therefore, all our ideas of particular sorts of substances are nothing but combinations of simple ideas co-existing in some unknown cause of their union. We represent particular sorts of substances to ourselves through such combinations of simple ideas, and in no other way. They are the only ideas we have of the various sorts of things—the sorts that we signify to other people by means of such names as ‘man’, ‘horse’, ‘sun’, ‘water’, ‘iron’. Anyone who hears such a word, and understands the language, forms in his mind a combination of those simple ideas that he has found—or thinks he has found—to exist together under that name; all of which he supposes to rest in and be fixed to that unknown common subject that doesn’t inhere in anything else in its turn. Consider for instance the idea of the sun: it is merely a collection of the simple ideas, bright, hot, roundish, having a constant regular motion, at a certain distance from us—and perhaps a few others, depending on how accurately the owner of the idea has observed the

98

Essay II John Locke xxiii: Ideas of substances

properties of the sun.

7. The most perfect idea of any particular sort of substance results from putting together most of the simple ideas that do exist in it—·i.e. in substances of that sort·—including its active powers and passive capacities. (These are not simple ideas, but for brevity’s sake let us here pretend that they are.) Thus the complex idea of the substance that we call a loadstone has as a part the power of attracting iron; and a power to be attracted by a loadstone is a part of the complex idea we call ‘iron’. These powers are counted as inherent qualities of the things that have them. Every substance is as likely, through the powers we observe in it, (a) to change the perceptible qualities of other subjects as (b) to produce in us those simple ideas that we receive immediately from it. When (b) happens with fire (say), our senses perceive in fire its heat and colour, which are really only the fire’s powers to produce those ideas in us. When (a) happens, we also learn about the fire because it acts on us mediately [= ‘through an intermediary’] by turning wood into charcoal and thereby altering how the wood affects our senses.... In what follows, I shall sometimes include these powers among the simple ideas that we gather together in our minds when we think of particular substances. Of course they aren’t really simple; but they are simpler than the complex ideas of kinds of substance, of which they are merely parts.

8. It isn’t surprising that powers loom large in our complex ideas of substances. We mostly distinguish substances one from another through their secondary qualities, which make a large part of our complex ideas of substances. (Our senses will not let us learn the sizes, textures, and shapes of the minute parts of bodies on which their real constitutions and differences depend; so we are thrown back on using their secondary qualities as bases for distinguishing them one from another.) And all the secondary qualities, as has been shown ·in viii·, are nothing but powers....

9. The ideas that make our complex ideas of bodily substances are of three sorts. First, the ideas of the primary qualities of things, including the size, shape, number, position, and motion of the parts of bodies. We discover these by our senses, but they are in the bodies even when we don’t perceive them. Secondly, the sensible [= ‘perceptible’] secondary qualities. They depend on the primary qualities, and are nothing but the powers that bodies have to produce certain ideas in us through our senses. These ideas are not in the things themselves except in the sense that a thing is ‘in’ its cause. Thirdly, when we think that one substance can cause an alteration in the primary qualities of another, so that the altered substance would produce in us different ideas from what it did before, we speak of the active powers of the first substance and the passive powers of the second. We know about the powers of things only through sensible simple ideas. For example, whatever alteration a loadstone has the power to make in the minute particles of iron, we wouldn’t suspect that it had any power to affect iron if that power weren’t revealed by how the loadstone makes the iron particles move. I have no doubt that bodies that we handle every day have powers to cause thousands of changes in one another—powers that we never suspect because they never appear in sensible effects.

10. So it is proper that powers should loom large in our complex ideas of substances. If you examine your complex idea of gold, you’ll find that several of the ideas that make it up are only ·ideas of· powers. For example, the power of being melted without being burned away, and the power of being dissolved in aqua regia [a mixture of nitric and hydrochloric acids]—these ideas are as essential to our complex idea of

99

Essay II John Locke xxiii: Ideas of substances

gold as are its colour and weight. Indeed, colour and weight when properly understood turn out also to be nothing but powers. For yellowness is not actually in gold, but is a power that gold has, when placed in proper light, to produce a certain idea in us through our eyes. Similarly, the heat that we can’t leave out of our idea of the sun is no more really in the sun than is the white colour it gives to wax. These are both equally powers in the sun, which operates on a man—through the motion and shape of its sensible parts—so as to make him have the idea of heat; just as it operates on wax so as to make it capable of producing in a man the idea of white.

11. If our senses were sharp enough to distinguish the minute particles of bodies and the real constitution on which their sensible qualities depend, I am sure they would produce in us ideas quite different from the ones they now produce; the yellow colour of gold, for example, would be replaced by an admirable texture of parts of a certain size and shape. Microscopes plainly tell us this; for what to our naked eyes produces a certain colour is revealed through a microscope to be quite different. Thus sand or ground glass, which is opaque and white to the naked eye, is transparent under a microscope; and a hair seen this way loses its former colour and is mostly transparent, with a mixture of bright sparkling colours like the ones refracted from a diamond. Blood to the naked eye appears all red; but when its lesser parts are brought into view by a good microscope, it turns out to be a clear liquid with a few red globules floating in it. We don’t know how these red globules would appear if glasses could be found that would magnify them a thousand or ten thousand times more.

12. God in his infinite wisdom has given us senses, faculties, and organs that are suitable for the conveniences of life and for the business we have to do here. senses enable us to know and distinguish things, and to examine them in enough detail to be able to make use of them and in various ways accommodate them to our daily needs. insight into their admirable structures and wonderful effects goes far enough for us to admire and praise the wisdom, power, and goodness of their author.... But it seems that God didn’t intend that we should have a perfect, clear, and adequate knowledge of things; and perhaps no finite being can have such knowledge. faculties, dull and weak as they are, suffice for us to discover enough in created things to lead us to •the knowledge of the creator, and •the knowledge of our duty; and we are also equipped with enough abilities to •provide for the conveniences of living. These are our business in this world. But if our senses were made much keener and more acute, the surface appearances of things would be quite different for us, and, I’m inclined to think that this would be inconsistent with our survival—or at least with our well-being—in this part of the universe that we inhabit. Think about how little we are fitted to survive being moved into air not much higher than the air we commonly breathe—that will give you reason to be satisfied that on this planet that has been assigned as our home God has suited our organs to the bodies that are to affect them, and vice versa. If our sense of hearing were merely one thousand times more acute than it is, how distracted we would be by perpetual noise! Even in the quietest retirement we would be less able to sleep or meditate than we are now in the middle of a sea-battle. If someone’s eyesight (the most instructive of our senses) were a thousand or a hundred thousand times more acute than it is now through the best microscope, he would be able to see with his naked eyes things several million times smaller than the smallest object he can see now; ·and this would have •a good result and •a bad one·. •It would bring

100

Essay II John Locke xxiii: Ideas of substances

him nearer to discovering the texture and motion of the minute parts of corporeal things, and he would probably get ideas of the internal structures of many of them. But then •he would be in a quite different world from other people: nothing would appear the same to him as to others; the visible ideas of everything would be different. So that I don’t think that he could converse with others concerning the objects of sight, or communicate in any way about colours, their appearances being so wholly different. [The section continues with further remarks about the disadvantages of having ‘such microscopical eyes (if I may so call them)’. It ends thus:] Someone who was sharp-sighted enough to see the arrangement of the minute particles of the spring of a clock, and observe the special structure and ways of moving on which its elastic motion depends, would no doubt discover something very admirable. But if his eyes were so formed that he couldn’t tell the time by his clock, because he couldn’t from a distance take in all at once the clock-hand and the numerals on the dial, he wouldn’t get much advantage from the acuteness of his sight: it would let him in on the structure and workings of the parts of the machine while also making it useless to him!

[In section 13—an admitted interruption of the main line of thought—Locke remarks that the structure of our sense organs is what sets limits to what we can perceive in the material world, and offers his ‘extravagant conjecture’ about ‘Spirits’, here meaning something like ‘angels’. Assuming that they ‘sometimes’ have bodies, angels may be able to alter their sense organs at will, thus being able to perceive many things that we can’t. Locke can’t hide his envy about this, though he says that ‘no doubt’ God has good reasons for giving us sense-organs that we cannot flex at will, like muscles.]

14. Each of our ideas of a specific kind of substances is nothing but a collection of simple ideas considered as united in one thing. These ideas of substances, though they strike us as simple and have simple words as names, are nevertheless really complex and compounded. Thus the idea that an Englishman signifies by the name ‘swan’, is white colour, long neck, red beak, black legs, and webbed feet, and all these of a certain size, with a power of swimming in the water, and making a certain kind of noise—and perhaps other properties as well, for someone who knows a lot about this kind of bird—all united in one common subject.

15. Besides the complex ideas we have of •material sensible substances, we can also form the complex idea of an •immaterial spirit. We get this through the simple ideas we have taken from operations of our own minds that we experience daily in ourselves, such as

thinking

understanding

willing

knowing, and

power of beginning motion, etc.

all co-existing in some substance. By putting these ideas together, we have as clear a perception and notion of immaterial substances as we have of material ones. For putting together the ideas of •thinking and •willing and •the power of starting or stopping bodily motion, joined to substance, of which we have no distinct idea, we have the idea of an •immaterial spirit; and by putting together the ideas of •solid parts that hold together, and •a power of being moved, joined with substance, of which likewise we have no positive idea, we have the idea of •matter. [Here ‘positive’ contrasts with ‘relative’. The idea of substance in general is relative because it is only the idea of whatever-it-is that relates to qualities by upholding and uniting them.]

101

Essay II John Locke xxiii: Ideas of substances

The one is as clear and distinct an idea as the other, the ideas of thinking and moving a body being as clear and distinct as the ideas of extension, solidity, and being moved. For our idea of substance is equally obscure, or none at all, in both: It is merely a supposed I know not what, to support qualities. Those who believe that our senses show us nothing but material things haven’t thought hard enough! When you think about it, you’ll realize that every act of sensation gives us an equal view of both parts of nature, the corporeal and the spiritual [= ‘the bodily and the mental’]. For while I know by seeing or hearing etc. that there is some bodily thing outside me that is the object of that sensation, I know with even more certainty that there is some spiritual being within me that sees and hears. This seeing and hearing can’t be done by mere senseless matter; it couldn’t occur except as the action of an immaterial thinking being.

16. All that we know of body is contained in our complex idea of it as extended, shaped, coloured, and having other sensible qualities; and all this is as far from the idea of the substance of body as we would be if we knew nothing at all. And although we think we are very familiar with matter, and know a great deal about many of its qualities, it may turn out that our basic ideas of •body are no more numerous, and no clearer, than our basic ideas of •immaterial spirit.

17. The basic ideas that we have that apply to body and not to spirit are •the holding together of parts that are solid and therefore separable, and •a power of causing things to move by colliding with them. Bodies also have shapes, but shape is merely a consequence of finite extension.

18. The ideas we have belonging exclusively to spirit are •thinking and •will (which is the power of putting body into motion by thought) and •liberty. Whereas a body can’t help setting in motion a motionless body with which it collides, the mind is at liberty to put bodies into motion or refrain from doing so, as it pleases. The ideas of •existence, •duration, and •mobility are common to both body and spirit.

19. It shouldn’t be thought strange that I attribute mobility to spirit. Spirits, like bodies can only operate where they are; we find that a single spirit operates at different times in different places; so I have to attribute change of place to all finite spirits (I’m not speaking of ·God·, the infinite spirit, here). For my soul [= ‘spirit’ = ‘mind’] is a real thing just as much as my body is, and is equally capable of changing its distance from any other ·spatially located· being; and so it is capable of motion....

20. Everyone finds in himself that his soul •can think, will, and operate on his body in the place where that body is, but •cannot operate on a body or in a place a hundred miles away. You can’t imagine that your soul could think or move a body in Oxford while you are in London, and you have to realize that your soul, being united to your body, continually changes its location during the whole journey between Oxford and London, just as does the coach or horse that you ride on—so I think it can be said to be truly in motion throughout that journey. If that isn’t conceded as giving a clear idea enough of the soul’s motion, you will get one from ·the thought of· its being separated from the body in death; for it seems to impossible that you should think of it as •leaving the body while having no idea of •its motion.

[In section 21 Locke discusses a scholastic reason for denying that souls or spirits can move, and derisively challenges its supporters ‘to put it into intelligible English’. He concludes:] Indeed motion cannot be attributed to God—not because he is an immaterial spirit but because he is an infinite one.

102

Essay II John Locke xxiii: Ideas of substances

22. Let us compare our complex idea of immaterial spirit with our complex idea of body, and see whether one is more obscure than the other—and if so, which. idea of body, I think, is ·that of·

an extended solid substance, capable of transferring motion by impact;

and our idea of soul or immaterial spirit is ·the idea· of

a substance that thinks, and has a power of making a body move, by willing or thought.

Which of these is more obscure and harder to grasp? I know that people whose thoughts are immersed in matter, and have so subjected their minds to their senses that they seldom reflect on anything that their senses can’t reach, are apt to say that they can’t comprehend a thinking thing. Perhaps they can’t, but then if they think hard about it they’ll realize that they can’t comprehend an extended thing either.

23. If anyone says ‘I don’t know what it is that thinks in me’, he means that he doesn’t know what the substance is of that thinking thing. I respond that he has no better grasp of what the substance is of that solid thing. If he also says ‘I don’t know how I think’, I respond that he also doesn’t know how he is extended—that is, how the solid parts of body cohere together to make extension. ·I shall discuss the cohesion problem—the problem of explaining how portions of matter hang together to compose planets or pebbles or grains of sand—from here through to the end of section 27·. The pressure of the particles of air may account for the cohesion of some parts of matter that are bigger than the particles of air and have pores that are smaller than those particles; but that can’t explain the coherence of the particles of air themselves. Whatever holds them together, it isn’t the pressure of the air! And if the pressure of any matter that is finer than the air—such as the ether—can unite and hold together the parts of a particle of air (as well as of other bodies), it still can’t make bonds for itself and hold together the parts that make up every least particle of that materia subtilis [= ‘extra-fine matter’]. Thus, however ingeniously we develop our explanation of how the parts of perceptible bodies are held together by the pressure of other imperceptible bodies ·such as the particles of the ether·, that explanation doesn’t extend to the parts of the ether itself. The more success we have in showing that the parts of other bodies are held together by the external pressure of the ether, and can have no other conceivable cause of their cohesion and union, the more completely we are left in the dark about what holds together the parts of each particle of the ether itself. We •can’t conceive of those particles as not having parts, because they are bodies, and thus divisible; but we also •can’t conceive of how their parts cohere, because the explanation of how everything else coheres cannot be applied to them.

24. ·The foregoing argument shows that even if pressure from the ether •could explain the cohesion of most bodies, it leaves unexplained the cohesion of the particles of the ether itself·. But in fact pressure, however great, from a surrounding fluid ·such as the ether· •cannot be what causes the cohesion of the solid parts of matter. Such a pressure might prevent two things with polished surfaces from moving apart in a line •perpendicular to those surfaces,....but it can’t even slightly hinder their pulling apart in a line •parallel to those surfaces—·I shall call this a ‘lateral motion’·. The surrounding fluid is free to occupy each part of space that is deserted through such a lateral motion; so it doesn’t resist such a motion of bodies joined in that way, any more than it would resist the motion of a body that was surrounded on all sides by that fluid and didn’t touch any other body.

103

Essay II John Locke xxiii: Ideas of substances

And therefore, if there were no other cause of cohesion ·than this surrounding-fluid one·, all parts of ·all· bodies would be easily separable by such a lateral sliding motion. So it is no harder for us to have a clear idea of how the soul thinks than to have one of how body is extended. For the •extendedness of body consists in nothing but the •union and cohesion of its solid parts, so we shall have a poor grasp of the extension of body when we don’t understand the union and cohesion of its parts; and we don’t understand that, any more than we understand what thinking is and how it is performed.

25. Most people would wonder how anyone should see a difficulty in what they think they observe every day. ‘Don’t we see the parts of bodies stick firmly together? Is there anything more common? And what doubt can there be made of it?’ And similarly with regard to thinking and voluntary motion: ‘Don’t we experience it every moment in ourselves? So can it be doubted?’ The matter of fact is clear, I agree, but when we want to look more closely and think about how it is done, we are at a loss both about extension and about thought....

26. The little bodies that compose the fluid we call ‘water’ are so extremely small that I have never heard of anyone claiming to see their distinct size, shape, or motion through a microscope (and I’ve heard of microscopes that have magnified up to a hundred thousand times, and more). And the particles of water are also so perfectly loose one from another that the least force perceptibly separates them. Indeed, if we think about their perpetual motion we must accept that they don’t cohere with another; and when a sharp cold comes they unite, they consolidate, these little atoms cohere, and they can’t be separated without great force. Something we don’t yet know—and it would be a great discovery—is what the bonds are that tie these heaps of loose little bodies together so firmly, what the cement is that sticks them so tightly together ·in ice·. But someone who made that discovery would still be long way from ·solving the general problem·, making intelligible the extension of body (which is the cohesion of its solid parts). For that he would need to show how the parts of those bonds—or of that cement, or of the least particle of matter that exists—hold together. It seems, then, that this primary and supposedly obvious quality of body, ·extension·, turns out when examined to be as incomprehensible as anything belonging to our minds, and that it is as hard to conceive a solid extended substance as it is to conceive a thinking immaterial one....

27. Here is a further difficulty about solving the cohesion problem through an appeal to surrounding pressures. Let us suppose that matter is finite (as no doubt it is). Now think about the outermost bounds of the universe, and ask yourself:

What conceivable hoops, what bond, can hold this unified mass of matter together with a pressure from which steel must get its strength and diamonds their hardness and indissolubility?

If matter is finite, it must have boundaries, and there must be something that stops it from scattering in all directions. If you try to avoid this ·latest· difficulty by supposing that the material world is infinite in extent, ask yourself what light you are throwing on the cohesion of body—whether you are making it more intelligible by relying on the most absurd and incomprehensible of all suppositions. So far is our ·idea of· the extension of body (which is nothing but the cohesion of solid parts) from being clearer or more distinct when we enquire into the nature, cause, or manner of it, than is the idea of thinking!

104

Essay II John Locke xxiii: Ideas of substances

28. Another idea that we have of body is ·the idea of· the power of transferring motion by impact: and of our souls ·the idea of· the power of exciting motion by thought. Everyday experience clearly provides us with these two ideas, but here again if we enquire how each power is exercised, we are equally in the dark. In the most usual case of motion’s being communicated from one body to another through impact, the former body loses as much motion as the other acquires; and the only conception we have of what is going on here is that motion passes out of one body into the other. That seems to me to be as obscure and inconceivable as how our minds move or stop our bodies by thought, which we every moment find they do. Daily experience provides us with clear evidence of motion produced by impact, and of motion produced by thought; but as for how this is done, we are equally at a loss with both. So that when we think about •the communication of motion, whether by body or by spirit, •the idea of it that is involved in spirit-as-mover is at least as clear as •the one involved in body-as-mover. And if we consider the active power of moving (called ‘motivity’ ·in xxi.73·), it is much clearer in spirit than body. Place two bodies at rest side by side; they give us no idea of a power in the one to move the other, except through a borrowed motion. The mind, on the other hand, every day gives us ideas of an active power of moving bodies. This gives us reason to think that active power may be the proper [here = ‘exclusive’] attribute of spirits, and passive power the proper attribute of matter. If that is so, then created spirits are not totally other than matter, because as well as being active (as matter isn’t) they are also passive (as matter is). Pure spirit, namely God, is only active; pure matter is only passive; and beings ·like us· that are both active and passive may be judged to involve both....

29. In conclusion: Sensation convinces us that there are •solid extended substances, and reflection that there are •thinking ones. Experience assures us that •one has a power to move body by impact, •the other by thought. That much is sure, and we have clear ideas of it; but we can’t go any further. If we start asking about nature, causes, and manner ·of operation·, we see no more clearly into the nature of extension than we do into the nature of thinking. It is no harder to conceive how a substance that we don’t know should •by thought set body into motion, than how a substance that we don’t know should •by impact set body into motion....

[In sections 30–31 Locke sums up the results of the last few sections, re-emphasizing that the idea of a thinking substance is not less respectable than that of an extended substance. He concludes section 31 with a new difficulty about the latter:] Nothing in our notion of spirit is more perplexed, or nearer a contradiction, than something that the very notion of body includes in it, namely the infinite divisibility of any finite extended thing. Whether we accept this or reject it, we land ourselves in consequences that we can’t explain or make consistent within our thought—consequences that carry greater difficulty, and more apparent absurdity, than anything that follows from the notion of an immaterial knowing substance.

[In section 32 Locke starts by rehearsing the arguments he has given for the view that ‘we have as much reason to be satisfied with our notion of immaterial spirit as with our notion of body, and of the existence of the one as well as of the other’. He then launches, without announcing that he is doing so, into a new issue: is a human being an extended thing that thinks, or rather a pair of things of which one is extended and the other thinks?] It is no

105

Essay II John Locke xxiii: Ideas of substances

more a contradiction that •thinking should exist separate and independent from solidity than that •solidity should exist separate and independent from thinking. Thought and extension are simple ideas, independent one from another; and we are as entitled to allow •a thinking thing without solidity as we are •a solid thing without thinking. It may be hard to conceive how thinking could occur without matter, but it’s at least as hard to conceive how matter could think. Whenever we try to get beyond our simple ideas, to dive deeper into the nature of things, we immediately fall into darkness and obscurity, perplexity and difficulties. But whichever of these complex ideas is clearer, that of body or that of immaterial spirit, each is evidently composed of the simple ideas that we have received from sensation or reflection. So are all our other ideas of substances, even that of God himself.

[In section 33 Locke develops that last remark, contending that we can build up our idea of God as infinitely powerful, wise, etc. through a general procedure that he illustrates with an example in section 34.]

34. If I find that I know a few things, some or all of them imperfectly, I can form an idea of knowing twice as many; which I can double again, ·and so on indefinitely·, just as I can generate an endless series of numbers by repeated doubling. In that way I can enlarge my idea of knowledge by extending its coverage to all things existing or possible. And I can do the same with regard to knowing them more perfectly, thus forming the idea of infinite or boundless knowledge. The same may also be done for power....and also for the duration of existence.... We form the best idea of God that our minds are capable of, by •taking simple ideas from the operations of our own minds (through reflection) or from exterior things (through our senses) and •enlarging them to the vastness to which infinity can extend them.

35. It is infinity—joined to existence, power, knowledge, etc.—that makes our complex idea of God. Although in his own essence (which we don’t know, any more than we know the real essence of a pebble, or of a fly, or of ourselves) God may be simple and uncompounded, still our only idea of him is a complex one whose parts are the ideas of existence, knowledge, power, happiness, etc.—all this infinite and eternal....

36. Apart from infinity, there is no idea we attribute to God that isn’t also a part of our complex idea of other Spirits [here = something like ‘angels’]. We can attribute to Spirits only ideas that we get from reflection; and we can differentiate them ·from God on one side, and from us on the other· only through differences in the extent and degree of knowledge, power, duration, happiness, etc. that each has. Here is another bit of evidence that we are confined to the ideas that we receive from sensation and reflection: even if we think of ·unembodied· Spirits as ever so much, even infinitely, more advanced than bodies are, we still can’t have any idea of how they reveal their thoughts one to another. We have to use physical signs and particular sounds; they are the best and quickest we are capable of, which makes them the most useful we can find. Of course unembodied Spirits must have also a more perfect way of communicating their thoughts than we have; but of such immediate communication we have no experience in ourselves, and consequently no notion at all.

37. Now we have seen what kind of ideas we have of substances of all kinds, what they consist in, and how we came by them. All this, I think, makes three things very evident. 1 All our ideas of the various sorts of substances are nothing but collections of simple ideas, together with a supposition

106

Essay II John Locke xxiv: Collective ideas

of something to which they belong and in which they exist, though we have no clear distinct idea at all of this supposed something. 2 All the simple ideas which—when thus united in one common substratum—make up our complex ideas of various sorts of substances are received from sensation or reflection. Even •those extremely familiar ideas that apply to almost everything—·such as the ideas of time, motion, body, thought, feeling·—have such simple ideas of sensation and reflection as their only ingredients. So do •the ideas that seem furthest from having any connection with us, and that infinitely surpass anything we can perceive in ourselves by reflection or discover by sensation in other things. Even those ideas must be constructed out of the simple ideas that we originally received from sensation or reflection. This is clearly the case with respect to the complex ideas we have of angels, and especially our idea of God. 3 Most of the simple ideas that make up our complex ideas of substances are really only ·ideas of· powers, however apt we are to think of them as ·ideas of· positive qualities. [Here again ‘positive’ contrasts with ‘relative’.] For example, most of the ideas that make our complex idea of gold are yellowness, great weight, ductility, fusibility and solubility in aqua regia, etc. all united together in an unknown substratum; and these are all ideas of gold’s relations to other substances. ·To be heavy is to have a power to outweigh other things; to be yellow is to have a power to cause certain visual sensations in human observers·. [Ductility is the ability to be drawn out into a thin wire, and fusibility is the ability to melt when hot; neither of which is a relation to other substances. Perhaps Locke has a different thought at work here, not properly expressed: he may be contrasting ‘positive’ qualities not only with relative qualities but also with conditional ones. Attributing a power to something is asserting a conditional about it—If it is heated, it will melt. A positive quality such as squareness isn’t like that: the thing just is square, and ‘if’ doesn’t come into it.] These powers depend on the real and primary qualities of the gold’s internal constitution; they are what give it its power to operate on other substances and to be operated on by them; but the powers aren’t really in the gold considered purely in itself.

Chapter xxiv: Collective ideas of substances

1. Besides these complex ideas of various ·kinds of· single substances—man, horse, gold, violet, apple, etc. the mind also has complex collective ideas of substances. Such ideas are made up of many particular substances considered together as united into one idea, and which, so joined, are looked on as one. For example, the idea of a collection of men that make an army, though it consists of a great many distinct substances, is as much one idea as the idea of a man. Similarly with the great collective idea of all bodies whatsoever, signified by the name ‘world’....

[In section 2 Locke contends that power of the mind whereby it makes collective ideas out of complex ideas of individuals is the very one by which it makes the latter ideas out of simple ones. The crux is this:] It is no harder to conceive how an army of ten thousand men should make one idea

107

Essay II John Locke xxiv: Collective ideas

than to conceive how a man should make one idea. ·Each involves constructing a complex out of parts that are simple (or simpler)·.

3. Artifacts, or at least the ones that are made up of distinct substances—·e.g. carriages, houses, clocks·—fall under collective ideas of the kind I have been discussing. ·Not only do man-made things tend to fall under collective ideas, but conversely collective ideas are in a special way man-made·. All our collective ideas—such as those of army, constellation, universe—are merely artificial representations made by the mind. Such an idea gathers into a single view, under a single name, things that are very remote from and independent of one another, so as better to think and talk about them. As the meaning of the word ‘universe’ shows, no things are so remote or unalike that the mind can’t bring them under a single idea by this technique of composition.

108

Essay II John Locke xxv: Relation

Chapter xxv: Relation

1. Besides the ideas, simple and complex, that the mind has of things considered on their own, it gets other ideas from comparison between different things. [For Locke, a ‘comparison’ can be any kind of considering together of two things, not necessarily likening them to one another.] When the understanding thinks about a thing, it isn’t confined to that precise object: it can look beyond it, to see how it relates to some other thing. When the mind sets one thing alongside another (so to speak) and carries its view from one to the other, this is what we call relation and respect. A word is called relative if applying it to one thing signifies such a respect and leads the thought from the original subject to something else. The things that are thus brought together are said to be related. [Locke develops all this at some length, contrasting the non-relational thought that Caius is white with the relational thoughts that Caius is a husband and that Caius is whiter than freestone.]

[Section 2 points out that many relative terms come in pairs: ‘father’ and ‘son’, ‘bigger’ and ‘smaller’. Some relative terms could be paired in this way but happen not to be; Locke gives the example of ‘concubine’. He concludes:] All names that are more than empty sounds must signify some idea that either •is ·an idea of a quality· in the thing to which the name is applied, and then it is positive and is looked on as united to and existing in the thing in question, or •arises from the respect ·or relation· the mind finds the thing to bear to some other thing, and then it includes a relation.

[In section 3 Locke mentions terms that are tacitly relative though they are sometimes not seen to be so—for example ‘old’, ‘great’, ‘imperfect’, etc. Section 4 points out that two people might have very different ideas of man yet exactly the same idea of fatherhood—different relata, same relation. Section 5 points out that a relation ceases to hold if one of the related things ceases to exist. When his only child dies, Caius ceases to be a father though he hasn’t altered within himself. Also, a thing can be related to many other things, some of the relations being ‘contrary’ to others: Caius is older than Titus and younger than Sempronia.]

6. Anything that can exist, or be considered as one thing, is positive ·in contrast to being relative·; and so not only simple ideas and substances but also modes are positive beings. Their parts are very often relative one to another, but the whole considered together as one thing is a positive or absolute thing or idea: it produces in us the complex idea of one thing, and this idea is in our minds as one picture, under one name, even though it is an aggregate of different parts. The parts of ·the idea of· a triangle have relations to one another, yet the idea of the whole is a positive absolute idea; ·a thing’s triangularity doesn’t involve how it relates to anything else·. The same may be said of a family, a tune, etc. Any relation must be between two things considered as two things....

7. Concerning relation in general, there are four points to be made. First, any single •item can be related in an almost infinite number of ways to other things. The •item in question may be

a simple idea

a substance

a mode

a relation

109

Essay II John Locke xxvi: Cause and effect etc.

a name of a simple idea or substance or mode or relation.

·It is a remarkable fact that even •a relation or •a word can stand in relations to other things, but I shall not linger on that, and shall instead take the example of the many in which •a substance can stand to other things·. Thus, one single man may at once be involved in all these relations, and many more: father, brother, son, grandfather, grandson, father-in-law, son-in-law, husband, friend, enemy, subject, general, judge, patron, client, professor, European, Englishman, islander, servant, master, possessor, captain, superior, inferior, bigger, less, older, younger, contemporary, like, unlike, and so on almost to infinity, he being capable of as many relations as there can be ways of considering him together with something else....

8. Secondly, although relations aren’t contained in the real existence of things, but are something extraneous and added-on, the ideas that relative words stand for are often clearer and more distinct than of the substances to which they belong. The notion we have of a father is a great deal clearer and more distinct than our idea of man.... That is because I can often get the notion of a relation from my knowledge of one action or one simple idea, whereas to know any substantial being I need an accurate collection of many ideas.... Thus having the notion that one laid the egg out of which the other was hatched I have a clear idea of the relation of parent to chick between the two cassowaries in St. James’s Park, although I have only an obscure and imperfect idea of those birds themselves.

9. Thirdly, although ever so many relations hold between one thing and another, they are all made up of simple ideas of sensation or reflection—which I think are the whole materials of all our knowledge. To establish this I shall show it of •the most considerable relations that we have any notion of, and also of •some that seem to be the most remote from sense or reflection. The seemingly remote ones will be shown also to have their ideas from sense or reflection: the notions we have of those relations are merely certain simple ideas, and so originally derived from sense or reflection.

10. Fourthly, relation is thinking of one thing along with another, so that any word is relative if it necessarily leads the mind to any ideas ·of qualities· other than the ones that are supposed to exist in the thing to which the word is being applied. For example, ‘father’, ‘brother’, ‘king’, ‘husband’, ‘blacker’, ‘merrier’, etc. are relative, because each implies something else separate and exterior to the existence of the man to whom the word is applied. By way of contrast, such terms as ‘black’, ‘merry’, ‘thoughtful’, ‘thirsty’, ‘angry’, ‘extended’ are all absolute [= ‘positive’ = ‘not relative’], because they don’t signify anything beyond the man to whom they are applied.

11. Having laid down these ·four· premises concerning relation in general, I shall now proceed to show through examples how all our ideas of relation, however refined or remote from sense they seem to be, are made up of nothing but simple ideas. I shall begin with the most comprehensive relation, wherein all things that do or can exist are concerned, namely the relation of cause and effect. My next topic is the derivation of this from the two fountains of all our knowledge, sensation and reflection.

110

Essay II John Locke xxvi: Cause and effect etc.

Chapter xxvi: Cause and effect, and other relations

1. As we attend to the changes that things constantly undergo, we can’t help noticing that various qualities and substances begin to exist, and that they come into existence through the operations of other things. From this observation we get our ideas of cause and effect. We use the general name ‘cause’ for whatever produces any simple or complex idea, and ‘effect’ is our name for what is produced. When we find that applying a certain degree of heat to a piece of wax regularly turns it into a fluid, we call the simple idea of heat the cause of the fluidity, and call fluidity the effect of the heat.... Whatever we consider as conducing to, or operating to bring into existence, any particular simple idea or substance or mode that didn’t before exist, we take to be a cause and we label it accordingly.

2. So a cause is what makes some other thing—either simple idea, substance or mode—come into existence; and an effect is what is brought into existence by some other thing. We have no great difficulty in grouping the various origins of things into two sorts.

First, when a thing is made of which no part existed before—e.g. a new particle of matter comes into existence, having previously had no being. We call this creation.

Secondly, when a thing is made out of particles all of which already existed, although the whole thing of which they are made didn’t previously exist. Examples would be a man, an egg, a rose, etc. When this happens with a substance that is produced in the ordinary course of nature by an •internal force that works in •imperceptible ways, having been triggered by some external agent or cause, we call it generation. When the cause is •external to the thing that comes into existence, and the effect is produced by separating or joining parts in ways that •we can perceive, we call it making; all artificial things are in this category. When any simple idea [here = ‘quality’] is produced that wasn’t in that subject before, we call it alteration. Thus a man is generated, a picture made, and either of them ·may be· altered.... Things that are made to exist which weren’t there before are effects, and things that operated to ·produce· the existence are causes. In every case the notion of cause and effect arises out of ideas received through sensation or reflection; and the cause-effect relation, however widely applicable it may be, at last terminates in [= ‘comes down to’] simple ideas. For all you need to have the idea of cause and effect is to consider any simple idea or substance as beginning to exist through the operation of something else; you don’t have to know how it was done.

[In section 3 Locke remarks that many of our temporal descriptions are really relational, though they don’t appear to be so on the surface. For example, when we say ‘Queen Elizabeth reigned for forty-five years’, we are implicitly likening the length of her reign to the time taken by forty-five annual revolutions of the sun. Similarly with all other measures of time.]

[In section 4: not only measured time, but also some other temporal descriptions are covertly relational; for example ‘old’ means one thing applied to a dog and another applied to a human being, because calling a thing ‘old’ is comparing its duration with the usual duration of things of that kind. Where we know nothing of the latter, as with the sun, or a diamond, ‘young’ and ‘old’ have no application.]

[In section 5: spatial words such as ‘large’ and ‘small’ are

111

Essay II John Locke xxvii: Identity and diversity

also covertly relative, in the same way as ‘young’ and old’. A large apple is smaller than a small horse. Statements about where things are located are openly relational.]

6. So likewise ‘weak’ and ‘strong’ are relative, comparing the subject with some ideas we have at that time of ·something having· greater or less power. When we say ‘a weak man’ we mean one who has less strength than men usually have, or than men of his size usually have.... Similarly, when we say ‘Creatures are all weak things’ we use ‘weak’ as a relative term, signifying the disproportion in power between God and his creatures. An abundance of words in ordinary speech—perhaps the majority of them—stand only for relations, though at first sight they seem to have no such meaning. For example, in the statement ‘The ship has necessary stores’, ‘necessary’ and ‘stores’ are both relative words; one having a relation to accomplishing the intended voyage, and the other to future use....

Chapter xxvii: Identity and diversity

1. Another context in which the mind compares things [= ‘considers things together’] is their very being: when we consider something as existing at a given time and place and compare it with itself existing at another time, we are led to form the ideas of identity and diversity. [In this context ‘diversity’ means ‘non-identity’. To say that x is diverse from y is to say only that x is not y.] When we see a thing—any thing, of whatever sort—to be in a certain place at a certain time, we are sure that it is that very thing and not another thing existing at that time in some other place, however alike the two may be in all other respects. And in this consists identity, when the ideas to which it is attributed don’t vary from what they were at the moment of their former existence that we are comparing with the present. We never find—and can’t even conceive of—two things of the same kind existing in the same place at the same time, so we rightly conclude that whatever exists in a certain place at a certain time excludes all ·others· of the same kind, and is there itself alone. So when we ask whether a thing is ‘the same’ or not, we are always referring to something that existed at a given time in a given place, a thing that at that instant was certainly the same as itself and not the same as anything else. From this it follows that •one thing can’t have two beginnings of existence because it is impossible for one thing to be in different places ·at the same time·, and •two things can’t have one beginning, because it is impossible for two things of the same kind to exist in the same instant at the very same place. Thus, what had one beginning is the same thing; and what had a different beginning in time and place from that is not the same but diverse. The difficulties philosophers have had with this relation ·of identity· have arisen from their not attending carefully to the precise notions of the things to which it is attributed.

2. We have ideas of only three sorts of substances: God, finite intelligences, and bodies. 1 God is without beginning,

112

Essay II John Locke xxvii: Identity and diversity

eternal, unalterable, and everywhere; and so there can be no doubt concerning his identity. 2 Each finite spirit had its determinate time and place of beginning to exist, so its relation to that time and place will always determine its identity for as long as it exists. 3 The same holds for every particle of matter, which continues as the same as long as no matter is added to or removed from it.... These three sorts of ‘substances’ (as we call them) don’t exclude one another out of the same place, but we can’t conceive any of them allowing another of the same kind into its place. If that were to happen, the notions and names of identity and diversity would be useless, and there would be no way of distinguishing substances or anything else from one another. For example: if two bodies could be in the same place at the same time, then those two portions of matter would be one and the same, whatever their size. Indeed, all bodies would be one and the same, because allowing two bodies to be in one place ·at one time· allows for all bodies to do so. To suppose this ·to be possible· is to obliterate the distinction between identity and diversity, the difference between one and more....

·That all concerned the identity of substances·. There remain modes and relations, but because they ultimately depend on substances [Locke says they are ‘ultimately terminated in substances’], the identity and diversity of each particular one of them will be determined in the same way as the identity of particular substances.

Questions of identity and diversity don’t arise for things whose existence consists in a sequence ·of events·, such as the actions of finite beings, e.g. motion and thought. Because each of these ·events· perishes the moment it begins, they can’t exist at different times or in different places, as enduring things can; and therefore no motion or thought can be the same as any earlier motion or thought.

3. There has been much enquiry after the principle of individuation; but what I have said enables us easily to discover what that is: it is existence itself, which ties a being of a given sort to a particular time and place that can’t be shared by any other being of the same kind. This seems easier to conceive in simple substances or modes, but if we are careful we can just as easily apply it to compound ones. Consider an atom, i.e. a continued body under one unchanging surface, existing at a particular time and place: it is evident that at that instant it is the same as itself. For being at that instant what it is and nothing else, it is the same and so must continue as long as its existence is continued; for so long it will be the same and no other. [That sentence is Locke’s.] Similarly, if two or more atoms are joined together into a single mass, every one of those atoms will be the same by the foregoing rule. And while they exist united together, the mass whose parts they are must be the same mass, or the same body, however much the parts have been re-arranged. But if one atom is removed from the mass, or one new one added, it is no longer the same mass, or the same body. The identity of living creatures depends not on a mass of the same particles but on something else. For in them the variation of large amounts of matter doesn’t alter the identity. An oak growing from a sapling to a great tree, and then lopped, is still the same oak; and a colt grown up to be a horse, sometimes fat, sometimes lean, is the same horse throughout all this. In neither case is there the same mass of matter, though there truly is the same oak, or horse. That is because in these two cases, a mass of matter and a living body, identity isn’t applied to the same thing.

4. How, then, does an oak differ from a mass of matter? The answer seems to me to be this: the mass is merely the cohesion of particles of matter anyhow united, whereas the

113

Essay II John Locke xxvii: Identity and diversity

oak is such a disposition of particles as constitutes the parts of an oak, and an organization of those parts that enables the whole to receive and distribute nourishment so as to continue and form the wood, bark, and leaves, etc. of an oak, in which consists the vegetable life. Thus, something is one plant if it has an organization of parts in one cohering body partaking of one common life, and it continues to be the same plant as long as it partakes of the same life, even if that life is passed along to new particles of matter vitally united to the living plant, in a similar continued organization suitable for that sort of plants. This organization is at any one instant in some one collection of matter, which distinguishes it from all others at that instant; and what has the identity that makes the same plant is

that individual life, existing constantly from that moment forwards and backwards, in the same continuity of imperceptibly succeeding parts united to the living body of the plant.

It also makes all the parts of it be parts of the same plant, for as long as they exist united in that continued organization that is fit to convey that common life to all the parts so united.

5. The identity of lower animals is sufficiently like that for anyone to be able to see, from what I have said, what makes one animal and continues it the same. It can be illustrated by something similar, namely the identity of machines. What is a watch? Clearly it is nothing but a construction of parts organized to a certain end—an end that it can attain when sufficient force is applied to it. If we suppose this machine to be one continued body whose parts were repaired, added to, or subtracted from, by a constant addition or separation of imperceptible parts, with one common life, it would be very much like the body of an animal; with the difference that in an animal the fitness of the organization and the motion wherein life consists begin together, because the motion comes from within; but in a machine the force can be seen to come from outside, and is often lacking even when the machine is in order and well fitted to receive it—·for example, when a clock isn’t wound up·.

6. This also shows what the identity of the same man consists in, namely: a participation in the same continued life by constantly fleeting particles of matter that are successively vitally united to the same organized body. If you place the identity of man in anything but this, you’ll find it hard to make an embryo and an adult the same man, or a well man and a madman the same man. ·Your only chance of doing this is by tying ‘same man’ to ‘same soul’, but by that standard you will· make it possible for Seth, Ismael, Socrates, Pilate, St. Augustine, and Cesare Borgia to be the same man. If identity of soul alone makes the same man, and nothing in the nature of matter rules out an individual spirit’s being united to different bodies, it will be possible that those men with their different characters and living at widely different times, may have been the same man! That strange way of using the word ‘man’ is what one is led to by giving it a meaning from which body and shape are excluded....

7. So unity of substance does not constitute all sorts of identity. To conceive and judge correctly about identity, we must consider what idea the word it is applied to stands for: it is one thing to be the same substance, another the same man, and a third the same person, if ‘person’, ‘man’, and ‘substance’ are names for three different ideas; for such as is the idea belonging to that name, such must be the identity. If this had been more carefully attended to, it might have prevented a great deal of that confusion that often occurs regarding identity, and especially personal identity, to which

114

Essay II John Locke xxvii: Identity and diversity

I now turn ·after one more section on ‘same man’·.

8. An animal is a living organized body; and consequently the same animal, as I have said, is the same continued life communicated to different particles of matter, as they are successively united to that organized living body. And whatever other definitions are propounded, there should be no doubt that the word ‘man’ as we use it stands for the idea of an animal of a certain form. ·The time-hallowed definition of ‘man’ as ‘rational animal’ is wrong·. If we should see •a creature of our own shape and ·physical· constitution, though it had no more reason all its life than a cat or a parrot, we would still call him a man; and anyone who heard •a cat or a parrot talk, reason, and philosophize would still think it to be a cat or a parrot and would describe it as such. One of these two is •a dull, irrational man, the other •a very intelligent rational parrot. [Locke then quotes a tediously long traveller’s tale about encountering a rational parrot. His point is that someone who believes this account will go thinking of this rational animal as a parrot, not as a man.]

9. With ‘same man’ in hand, let us turn to ‘same person’. To find what personal identity consists in, we must consider what ‘person’ stands for. I think it is a thinking intelligent being, that has reason and reflection, and can consider itself as itself, the same thinking thing at different times and places. What enables it to think of itself is its consciousness, which is inseparable from thinking and (it seems to me) essential to it. It is impossible for anyone to perceive, without perceiving that he perceives. When we see, hear, smell, taste, feel, meditate, or will anything, we know that we do so. It is always like that with our present sensations and perceptions. And it is through this that everyone is to himself that which he calls ‘self’, not raising the question of whether the same self is continued in the same substance. Consciousness always accompanies thinking, and makes everyone to be what he calls ‘self’ and thereby distinguishes himself from all other thinking things; in this alone consists personal identity, i.e. the sameness of a rational being; and as far as this consciousness can be extended backwards to any past action or thought, so far reaches the identity of that person; it is the same self now that it was then; and this present self that now reflects on it is the one by which that action was performed.

10. Given that it is the same person, is it the same identical substance? Most people would think that it is the same substance if these perceptions with their consciousness always remained present in the mind, making the same thinking thing always consciously present and (most people would think) evidently the same to itself. What seems to make the difficulty—·that is, to make it at least questionable whether the same person must be the same substance·—is the following fact. •Consciousness is often interrupted by forgetfulness, and at no moment of our lives do we have the whole sequence of all our past actions before our eyes in one view; even the best memories lose the sight of one part while they are viewing another. Furthermore, •for the greatest part of our lives we don’t reflect on our past selves at all, because we are intent on our present thoughts or (in sound sleep) have no thoughts at all, or at least none with the consciousness that characterizes our waking thoughts. In all these cases our consciousness is interrupted, and we lose the sight of our past selves, and so doubts are raised as to whether or not we are the same thinking thing, i.e. the same substance.

That may be a reasonable question, but it has nothing to do with personal identity. For the latter, the question is about what makes the same person, and not whether the

115

Essay II John Locke xxvii: Identity and diversity

same identical substance always thinks in the same person. Different substances might all partake in a single consciousness and thereby be united into one person, just as different bodies can enter into the same life and thereby be united into one animal, whose identity is preserved throughout that change of substances by the unity of the single continued life. What makes a man be himself to himself is sameness of consciousness, so personal identity depends entirely on that—whether the consciousness is tied to one substance throughout or rather is continued in a series of different substances. For as far as any thinking being can repeat the idea of any past action with the same consciousness that he had of it at first, and with the same consciousness he has of his present actions, so far is he the same personal self. For it is by the consciousness he has of his present thoughts and actions that he is self to himself now, and so will be the same self as far as the same consciousness can extend to actions past or to come. Distance of time doesn’t make him two or more persons, and nor does change of substance; any more than a man is made to be two men by having a long or short sleep or by changing his clothes.

11. Our own bodies give us some kind of evidence for this. All the particles of your body, while they are vitally united to a single thinking conscious self—so that you feel when they are touched, and are affected by and conscious of good or harm that happens to them—are a part of yourself, i.e. of your thinking conscious self. Thus the limbs of his body are to everyone a part of himself; he feels for them and is concerned for them. Cut off a hand and thereby separate it from that consciousness the person had of its heat, cold, and other states, and it is then no longer a part of himself, any more than is the remotest material thing. Thus we see the substance of which the personal self consisted at one time may be varied at another without change of personal identity; for there is no doubt that it is the same person, even though one of its limbs has been cut off.

12. But it is asked: Can it be the same person if the substance changes? and Can it be different persons if the same substance does the thinking throughout?

·Before I address these questions in sections 13 and 14, there’s a preliminary point I want to make. It is that· neither question is alive for those who hold that thought is a property of a purely material animal constitution, with no immaterial substance being involved. Whether or not they are right about that, they obviously conceive personal identity as being preserved in something other than identity of substance; just as animal identity is preserved in identity of life, not of substance. ·This pair of questions does present a challenge to· •those who hold that only immaterial substances can think, ·and that sameness of person requires sameness of immaterial substance. Before •they can confront their materialist opponents, they· have to show why personal identity can’t be preserved through a change of immaterial substances, just as animal identity is preserved through a change of material substances. Unless they say that what makes the same life ·and thus the animal identity· in lower animals is one immaterial spirit, just as (according to them) one immaterial spirit makes the same person in men—and Cartesians at least won’t take that way out, for fear of making the lower animals thinking things too.

13. As to the first question, If the thinking substance is changed, can it be the same person?, I answer that this can be settled only by those who know •what kind of substances they are that think, and •whether the consciousness of past actions can be transferred from one such substance to another. Admittedly, if the same consciousness were •the same

116

Essay II John Locke xxvii: Identity and diversity

individual action, it couldn’t be transferred ·because in that case bringing a past headache (say) into one’s consciousness would be bringing back that very headache, and that is tied to the substance to which it occurred. But a present consciousness of a past event isn’t like that. Rather·, it is •a present representation of a past action, and we have still to be shown why something can’t be represented to the mind as having happened though really it did not. How far the consciousness of past actions is tied to one individual agent, so that another can’t possibly have it, will be hard for us to determine until we know

•what kind of action it is that can’t be done without a reflex act of perception accompanying it, and

•how such an action is done by thinking substances who can’t think without being conscious of it.

In our present state of knowledge it is hard to see how it can be impossible, in the nature of things, for an intellectual substance to have represented to it as done by itself something that it never did, and was perhaps done by some other agent.... Until we have a clearer view of the nature of thinking substances, we had better assume that such changes of substance within a single person never do in fact happen, basing this on the goodness of God. Having a concern for the happiness or misery of his creatures, he won’t transfer from one ·substance· to another the consciousness that draws reward or punishment with it....

14. The second question, Can it be different persons if the same substance does the thinking throughout?, seems to me to arise out of the question of whether the following is possible:

An immaterial being that has been conscious of the events in its past is wholly stripped of all that consciousness, losing it beyond the power of ever retrieving it again; so that now it (as it were) opens a new account, with a new starting date, having a consciousness that can’t reach ·back· beyond this new state.

·Really, the question is whether if this happened it could be the same person who had first one consciousness and then another, with no possibility of communication between them·. [Locke says that this must be regarded as possible by ‘those who hold pre-existence’, that is, who believe in reincarnation. He attacks them, thereby attacking the separation of ‘same person’ from ‘same consciousness’, and proposes a thoughtexperiment:] Reflect on yourself, and conclude that you have in yourself an immaterial spirit that is what thinks in you, keeps you the same throughout the constant change of your body, and is what you call ‘myself’. Now try to suppose also that it is the same soul that was in Nestor or Thersites at the siege of Troy. This isn’t obviously absurd; for souls, as far as we know anything of their nature, can go with any portion of matter as well as with any other; so the •soul ·or thinking substance· that is now yourself may once really have been the •soul of someone else, such as Thersites or Nestor. But you don’t now have any consciousness of any of the actions either of those two; so can you conceive yourself as being the same •person with either of them? Can their actions have anything to do with you? Can you attribute those actions to yourself, or think of them as yours more than the actions of any other men that ever existed? ·Of course you can’t·....

15. So we can easily conceive of being the same person at the resurrection, though in a body with partly different parts or structure from what one has now, as long as the same consciousness stays with the soul that inhabits the body. But the soul alone, in the change of bodies, would not be accounted enough to make the same man—except by

117

Essay II John Locke xxvii: Identity and diversity

someone who identifies the soul with the man. If the soul of a prince, carrying with it the consciousness of the prince’s past life, were to enter and inform the body of a cobbler who has been deserted by his own soul, everyone sees that he would be the same person as the prince, accountable only for the prince’s actions; but who would say it was the same man? The body contributes to making the man, and in this case I should think everyone would let the body settle the ‘same man’ question, not dissuaded from this by the soul, with all its princely thoughts. To everyone but himself he would be the same cobbler, the same man. I know that in common parlance ‘same person’ and ‘same man’ stand for the same thing; and of course everyone will always be free to speak as he pleases, giving words what meanings he thinks fit, and changing them as often as he likes. Still, when we want to explore what makes the same spirit, man, or person, we must fix the ideas of spirit, man, or person in our minds; and when we have become clear about what we mean by them, we shan’t find it hard to settle, for each of them, when it is ‘the same’ and when not.

16. But although the same •immaterial substance or soul does not by itself, in all circumstances, make the same man, it is clear that •consciousness unites actions—whether from long ago or from the immediately preceding moment—into the same person. Whatever has the consciousness of present and past actions is the same person to whom they both belong. If my present consciousness that I am now writing were also a consciousness that •I saw an overflowing of the Thames last winter and that •I saw Noah’s ark and the flood, I couldn’t doubt that I who write this now am the same self that saw the Thames overflowed last winter and viewed the flood at the general deluge—place that self in what substance you please. I could no more doubt this than I can doubt that I who write this am the same myself now while I write as I was yesterday, whether or not I consist of all the same substance, material or immaterial. For sameness of substance is irrelevant to sameness of self: I am as much involved in—and as justly accountable for—•an action that was done a thousand years ago and is appropriated to me now by this self-consciousness as I am for •what I did a moment ago.

17. Self is that conscious thinking thing that feels or is conscious of pleasure and pain and capable of happiness or misery, and so is concerned for itself as far as that consciousness extends. (This holds true whatever substance the thinking thing is made up of; it doesn’t matter whether it is spiritual or material, simple or compounded.) You must find that while your little finger is brought under your consciousness it is as much a part of yourself as is your head or your heart. If the finger were amputated and this consciousness went along with it, deserting the rest of the body, it is evident that the little finger would then be the person, the same person; and ·this· self would then would have nothing to do with the rest of the body. As with spatial separation so also with temporal: something with which the consciousness of this present thinking thing can join itself makes the same person, and is one self with it, as everyone who reflects will perceive.

18. Personal identity is the basis for all the right and justice of reward and punishment. What everyone is concerned for, for himself, is happiness and misery—with no concern for what becomes of any substance that isn’t connected with that consciousness. [Locke goes on to apply that to his ‘finger’ example, supposing that the finger takes the original consciousness with it, and that the rest of the body acquires a new consciousness.]

118

Essay II John Locke xxvii: Identity and diversity

19. This illustrates my thesis that personal identity consists not in the identity of substance but in the identity of consciousness. If Socrates and the present mayor of Queenborough agree in that, they are the same person; if Socrates awake doesn’t partake of the same consciousness as Socrates sleeping, they aren’t the same person. And to punish Socrates awake for something done by sleeping Socrates without Socrates awake ever being conscious of it would be as unjust as to punish someone for an action of his twin brother’s merely because their outsides were so alike that they couldn’t be distinguished.

20. It may be objected: ‘Suppose I wholly lose the memory of some parts of my life beyond any possibility of retrieving them, so that I shall never be conscious of them again; aren’t I still the same person who did those actions, had those thoughts that I once was conscious of, even though I have now forgotten them?’ To this I answer that we must be careful about what the word ‘I’ is applied to. This objector is thinking of sameness of the man, and calls it ‘I’ because he assumes that the same man is the same person. But ·the assumption isn’t necessarily correct·. If one man could have distinct disconnected consciousnesses at different times, that same man would certainly make different persons at different times. That this is what people in general think can be seen in the most solemn declaration of their opinions: human laws don’t punish the madman for the sane man’s actions, or the sane man for what the madman did, because they treat them as two persons. This is reflected in common speech when we say that someone is ‘not himself’ or is ‘beside himself’.Those phrases insinuate that the speaker thinks—or that those who coined the phrases thought—that the self was changed, the self-same person was no longer in that man.

21. ‘It is still hard to conceive that Socrates, the same individual man, might be two persons.’ To help us with this we must consider what is meant by ‘Socrates’, or ‘the same individual man’. ·There are three options·. The same man might be any of these:

1 the same individual, immaterial, thinking substance; in short, the numerically-same soul and nothing else,

2 the same animal, without any regard to an immaterial soul,

3 the same immaterial spirit united to the same animal.

Help yourself! On any of these accounts of ‘same man’, it is impossible for personal identity to consist in anything but consciousness, or reach any further than that does.

According to 1, a man born of different women, and in distant times, might still be the same man. Anyone who allows this must also allow that the same man could be two distinct persons....

According to 2 and 3, •Socrates in this life cannot be the same man as •anyone in the after-life. The only way to do this—·allowing for the possibility that •Socrates in Athens and •Socrates in Limbo are the same man·—is through an appeal to sameness of consciousness; and that amounts to equating human identity—·‘same man’·—with personal identity. But ·that equation is problematic, because· it makes it hard to see how the •infant Socrates can be the same man as •Socrates after the resurrection. There seems to be little agreement about what makes a man, and thus about what makes the same individual man; but whatever we think about that, if we are not to fall into great absurdities we must agree that sameness of person resides in consciousness.

22. You may want to object: ‘But isn’t a man drunk and sober the same person? Why else is he punished for what he does when drunk, even if he is never afterwards conscious of

119

Essay II John Locke xxvii: Identity and diversity

it? He is just as much a single person as a man who walks in his sleep and is answerable, while awake, for any harm he did in his sleep.’ ·Here is my reply to that·. Human laws punish both, with a justice suitable to the state of knowledge of those who administer the law: in these cases they can’t distinguish for sure what is real from what is counterfeit; and so they don’t allow the ignorance in drunkenness or sleep as a plea. Granted: punishment is tied to personhood, which is tied to consciousness, and the drunkard may not be conscious of what he did; but the courts justly punish him, because •his bad actions are proved against him, and •his lack of consciousness of them can’t be proved for him. It may be reasonable to think that on the great day when the secrets of all hearts are laid open, nobody will be held accountable for actions of which he knows nothing; everybody will receive his sentence with his conscience ·agreeing with God’s judgment by· accusing or excusing him.

23. Nothing but consciousness can unite remote existences into the same person. The identity of substance won’t do it. For whatever substance there is, and whatever it is like, without consciousness there is no person. A substance without consciousness can no more be a person that a carcass can. [In the remainder of this section, and in section 24, Locke discusses possible cases: two persons who take turns in animating one animal body (‘the night man and the day man’); and one person who alternately animates two different animal bodies. The central emphasis throughout is on the uselessness in these questions of the concept of the same immaterial substance.]

25. I agree ·that on the question of contingent fact· the more probable opinion is that this consciousness is tied to, and is a state of, a single immaterial substance. Please yourself about that. However, every thinking being that can experience happiness or misery must grant that

there is something, himself, that he is concerned for and wants to be happy; and that this self has existed continuously for a period of time and therefore may exist for months and years to come, with no set limit to its duration, and thus may be the same self carried by consciousness into the future.

It is through this consciousness that he finds himself to be the same self that acted thus and so some years ago and through which he is happy or miserable now. In all these thoughts we place sameness of self in sameness not of substance but of consciousness. Substances might come and go through the duration of such a consciousness; and for as long as a substance is in a vital union with the thing containing this consciousness it is a part of that same self. Thus, any part of my body, while vitally united to that which is conscious in me, is a part of myself (·for example my little finger, while it relates to me in such a way that if it is damaged I feel pain·); but when the vital union is broken, what was a part of myself a moment ago is now not so, any more than a part of another man’s self is a part of me. [The rest of the section illustrates and repeats this line of thought.]

26. ‘Person’, I take it, is the name for this self. Wherever you find what you call ‘myself’, anyone else may say there is ‘the same person’. ‘Person’ is a forensic term [= ‘a term designed for use in legal proceedings’], having to do with actions and their merit; and so it applies only to active thinking beings that are capable of a law, and of happiness and misery. It is only through consciousness that this personality [Locke’s word] extends itself beyond present existence to what is past, becoming concerned and accountable; the person owns and attributes past actions to itself for the same reason that

120

Essay II John Locke xxvii: Identity and diversity

it does the present. All this is founded in a concern for happiness, which unavoidably accompanies consciousness—something that is conscious of pleasure and pain desires that the self that is conscious should be happy. As for past actions that the self cannot through consciousness square with or join to the present self—it can no more be concerned with them than if they had never been done. To •receive pleasure or pain, i.e. reward or punishment, on account of any such action is all of a piece with •being born happy or miserable, without any ·merit or· demerit at all. Suppose a man were punished now for what he had done in another life of which he cannot have any consciousness, how does that ·so-called· punishment differ from simply being created miserable?....

27. In treating this subject I have considered as perhapspossible some states of affairs—·e.g. the one about the prince and the cobbler·—that will look strange to some readers, and perhaps are strange. But I think they are permissible, given our ignorance about the nature of the thinking thing in us which we look on as ourselves. If we knew with regard to this thinking thing

•what it is, or

•how it is tied to a certain system of fleeting animal spirits [see note in viii.12], or

•whether or not it can perform its operations of thinking and memory outside of a body organized as ours is, and

•whether God has decided that every such spirit ·or thinking thing· shall be united to only one such body, with its memory depending on the health of that body’s organs,

we might see the absurdity of some of the cases I considered. But as we are in the dark about these matters, we ordinarily think of the ·thinking thing or· soul of a man as an immaterial substance, owing nothing to matter and compatible with any kind of matter; and on that basis there cannot from the nature of things be any absurdity in supposing that the same soul might at different times be united to different bodies, making one man with each of them for as long as they were united....

28. To conclude: •any substance that begins to exist must during its existence necessarily be the same; •any complex of substances that begins to exist must during the existence of its component parts be the same; •any mode that begins to exist is throughout its existence the same.... It appears from this that the difficulty or obscurity that people have found in this matter has arisen from the poor use of words rather than from any obscurity in things themselves. For whatever makes the specific idea to which the name is applied, if we steadily keep to that idea it will be easy for us to distinguish same and different, with no doubts arising. ·I defend this in the next, final section·.

29. •Suppose we take a man to be a rational spirit, then it is easy to know what is the same man, namely the same spirit—whether or not it is embodied. •Suppose our idea of a man is a rational spirit vitally united to a body with a certain structure; then such a rational spirit will be the same man as long as it is united to such a body, though it needn’t be the same body throughout. •If anyone’s idea of a man is that of the vital union of parts in a certain shape [here = ‘structure’], as long as that vital union and shape remain in a compound body, remaining the same except for a turnover in its constituent particles, it will be the same man. For the complex idea we use when classifying a thing as being of a certain kind also determines what it is for a thing of that kind to continue in existence.

121

Essay II John Locke xxviii: Other relations

Chapter xxviii: Other relations

1. We can compare [= ‘relate’] or refer things one to another in respect of time, place, and causality, all of which I have discussed. We can also do so in countless other respects, of which I shall mention some. First, a simple idea [here = ‘quality’] that is capable of parts or degrees enables us to compare the things that have it to one another in respect of that simple idea—for example whiter, sweeter, equal·ly white·, more ·sweet·, etc. These relations depend on the equality and excess of the same simple idea in several subjects, and may be called proportional....

2. Secondly, we can also relate things, or think of one thing in a way that brings in the thought of another, in respect of the circumstances of their origin or beginning. Such relations can’t change through time, so they are as lasting as are the things related. Examples include father and son, brothers, first cousins, etc.—all the blood relationships, close and distant; and countrymen, i.e. those who were born in the same country, or region. I call these natural relations. We can see here how mankind have fitted their notions and words to daily needs and not to the truth and extent of things. For the relation of begetter to begotten is exactly the same in other species as in men; yet we don’t ordinarily say ‘This bull is the grandfather of that calf’ or ‘Those two pigeons are first cousins’. [Locke develops this point, remarking that some of our human-relational terms are needed in the law, and notes that cultures differ in this respect. He concludes:] This makes it easy to guess why in some countries they don’t even have a word meaning what ‘horse’ does for us, while in others, where they care more about the pedigrees of their horses than about their own, they have not only names for particular horses but also words for their various blood-relationships to one another.

3. Thirdly, sometimes things are brought together in a single thought on the basis of moral rights, powers, or obligations. Thus a general is one who has power to command an army; and an army under a general is a collection of armed men obliged to obey one man. A citizen is one who has a right to certain privileges in a given place. Such relations depend on men’s wills, or on agreement in society, so I call them ‘instituted’ or ‘voluntary’. Unlike the natural relations, most (if not all) of these are in some way alterable; two people related in such a way may cease to be so, while they both continue in existence. These relations, like all the others, involve relating two things to one another; but in many cases the relative nature of the term is overlooked because we have no standard relative name for one of the two subjects of the relation. For example, ‘patron’ and ‘client’ are easily recognized as relational ·because they come as a pair—if x is y’s patron then y is x’s client·—but ‘constable’ and ‘dictator’ are not, because there is no special name for those who are under the command of a dictator or of a constable....

4. Fourthly, another sort of relation has to do with whether or not men’s voluntary actions conform to some rule in terms of which they are judged. I think this may be called moral relation, because it concerns our moral·ly significant· actions. It deserves to be examined thoroughly, for there is no part of knowledge where we should be more careful to get fixed ideas and to do what we can to avoid obscurity and confusion. ·It will be my topic throughout the rest of this chapter·.

122

Essay II John Locke xxviii: Other relations

When human actions—with their various ends, objects, manners, and circumstances—are brought under distinct complex ideas, these are mixed modes, many of them with associated names. Taking gratitude to be a readiness to acknowledge and return kindness received, and polygamy to be the having of more than one wife at a time, when we form these notions in our minds we have there a couple of settled ideas of mixed modes. But our concern with our actions isn’t merely to know what complex ideas apply to them ·and thus how they should be classified·. We have another, greater, concern which is to know whether the actions thus classified are morally good or bad.

5. Good and evil, as I showed in xx.2 and xxi.42, are nothing but pleasure or pain, or what procures pleasure or pain for us. So moral good and evil is only the conformity or disagreement of our voluntary actions to some law, through which good or evil is drawn on us by the will and power of the law-maker. Such •good or evil, •pleasure or pain, that the law-maker decrees to follow from our observance or breach of the law is what we call •reward or punishment.

6. Of these moral rules or laws on the basis of which men generally judge the moral status of their actions, there seem to me to be three sorts, with three different enforcements, or rewards and punishments. ·Before listing them in section 7 and discussing them in 8–10, I defend my assumption that any kind of law does have a system of punishment and reward associated with it·. It would be utterly pointless for one thinking being to lay down a rule to govern the actions of another unless he had it in his power to reward compliance and punish deviation from his rule by some good or evil that isn’t the natural consequence of the action itself. A natural convenience or inconvenience would operate by itself, without help from a law. This ·association with reward and punishment· is, if I am not mistaken, the true nature of all law, properly so called.

7. The laws that men generally relate their actions to, in judging whether they are right or wrong, seem to me to be these three. 1. The divine law. 2. The civil law. 3. The law of opinion or reputation, if I may so call it. By their relation to the first of these, men judge whether their actions are sins or duties; by the second, whether criminal or innocent; and by the third, whether virtues or vices.

8. First, there is the divine law, by which I mean the law that God has set for the actions of men, whether announced to them by the light of nature or by the voice of revelation. Nobody is so cloddish as to deny that God has given men a rule by which to govern themselves. He has •a right to do it, because we are his creatures; he has •goodness and wisdom to direct our actions to what is best; and he has •power to enforce it by infinitely weighty rewards and punishments in the after-life. For nobody can take us out of his hands. This is the only true touchstone of moral rectitude; and it is by comparing their actions to this law that men judge the most considerable moral good or evil in their actions—that is, judge whether as duties or sins they are likely to procure them happiness or misery from the hands of God.

9. Secondly, there is the civil law, the rule set by a nation to ·govern· the actions of those who belong to it. Men relate their actions to this also, in judging whether or not they are criminal. Nobody ignores civil law, because the rewards and punishments that enforce it are ready at hand and are suitable to the power that makes this law, That is the force of the commonwealth, which is obliged to protect the lives, liberties, and possessions of those who live according to its law, and has the power to take away life, liberty, or goods from anyone who disobeys, that being the punishment of

123

Essay II John Locke xxviii: Other relations

offences against this law.

10. Thirdly, there is the law of opinion or reputation. ‘Virtue’ and ‘vice’ are names that are everywhere said and thought to apply to actions on the basis of their being inherently right or wrong; and as far as they really are applied in that way they to that extent coincide with the divine law above-mentioned. But whatever people say, we can see that the names ‘virtue’ and ‘vice’, in particular instances of their use throughout the various nations and societies in the world, are constantly attributed only to such actions as are in approved of or disapproved of in the country or society concerned. It isn’t surprising that men everywhere should call ‘virtuous’ the actions that they judge to be praiseworthy, and call ‘vicious’ the ones they regard as blameable; for otherwise they would condemn themselves by thinking something right without commending it, or wrong without blaming it. Thus what people say and think about virtue and vice is measured by the approval or dislike, praise or blame, which is silently agreed on in a society or tribe or club. When men unite into political societies they hand over to the public the decisions about how •their force is to be used, so that they can’t employ it against any fellow-citizens further than the law of the country directs; but they hang onto •the power of approving or disapproving of the actions of members of their society; and by this approval and dislike they establish amongst themselves what they call virtue and vice.

11. You will agree that this is the common measure of virtue and vice if you consider the fact that although what passes for vice in one country may be counted a virtue, or at least not a vice, in another; yet everywhere virtue and praise go together, as do vice and blame. Virtue is everywhere what is thought praiseworthy, and nothing but what is publicly esteemed is called virtue.... Differences in personal character, education, fashion, interests and so on can bring it about that what is thought praiseworthy in one place is censured in another; and so in different societies virtues and vices may sometimes have exchanged places; but in the main they have kept the same everywhere. ·What has kept standards of virtue and vice pretty much •the same as one another is what has kept them all pretty much •the same as the standards of right and wrong laid down by God. Here is why·. •Nothing can be more natural than to encourage with esteem and reputation what everyone finds to his advantage, and to blame and discountenance the contrary; and •nothing so directly and visibly advances the general good of mankind in this world as obedience to the laws that God has set for them, and nothing breeds such mischief and confusion as the neglect of those laws; and so •it is no wonder that esteem and discredit, virtue and vice, should to a large extent coincide with the unchangeable rule of right and wrong that the law of God has established. If people generally went wrong by placing their commendation or blame on the side that didn’t really deserve it, they would be renouncing all sense and reason, and also renouncing their own interests, to which they are in fact constantly true. Even men who behave badly bestow their approval in the right places; few of them are so depraved that they don’t condemn, at least in others, the faults they themselves are guilty of....

12. You might want to object:

When you say that the law by which men judge of virtue and vice is nothing but the consent of private men who haven’t enough authority to make a law, you are forgetting your own notion of a law, omitting something that ·according to you· is necessary and essential to a law, namely a power to enforce it.

124

Essay II John Locke xxviii: Other relations

I reply that if you imagine that commendation and disgrace don’t strongly motivate men to accommodate themselves to the opinions and rules of those with whom they have dealings, you can’t know much about the nature or history of mankind! Most people do govern themselves chiefly, if not solely, by this law of fashion; so they do what keeps them in reputation with their peers, having little regard for the laws of God or the law of the land. Some men—perhaps indeed most men—seldom reflect seriously on the penalties for breaking God’s laws; and amongst those that do, many go ahead and break the law anyway, entertaining thoughts of future reconciliation ·with God·, and making their peace ·with him· for such breaches. As for the punishments due from the laws of the commonwealth, men frequently comfort themselves with hopes of impunity. But no man who offends against the fashion and opinion of the society he belongs to and wants to be accepted by can escape the punishment of their censure and dislike. Not one man in ten thousand is stiff and thick-skinned enough to bear up under the constant dislike and condemnation of his own social circle. Someone who can content himself to live in constant disgrace and disrepute with his own particular society must have a strange and unusual constitution! Many men have sought solitude and been reconciled to it; but nobody who thinks at all—nobody with the least sense of a man about him—can live in society under the constant dislike and poor opinion of his associates. That is too heavy a burden for humans to bear....

[Section 13 briefly sums up the three laws.]

14. We test the goodness of an action by relating it to •a rule (like testing the quality of gold by rubbing it against a touchstone); the outcome of that test determines how we name the action, and that name is the sign of what value we attribute to it. Whether we take •the rule from the fashion of the country or from the will of a ·human or divine· law-maker, the mind can easily see how a given action relates to it, and so it has a notion of moral good/evil, which is an action’s conformity/nonconformity to that rule, and therefore is often called moral rectitude. This rule is merely a collection of several simple ideas, so that to judge whether an action conforms to it one has only to organize ·one’s thought of· it so as to see whether the simple ideas belonging to it correspond to the ones that the law requires. And so we see how moral notions are founded on, and come down to, the simple ideas we have received from sensation or reflection. For example, consider the complex idea we signify by the word ‘murder’: when we have dismantled it and examined all its parts we shall find them to be a collection of simple ideas derived from reflection or sensation. •From reflection: the ideas of willing, considering, intending in advance, malice; and also of life, perception, and self-motion. •From sensation: the collection of those simple sensible ideas that are ·of qualities· to be found in a man, and of an action through which a man no longer has perception or motion—·i.e. through which a man becomes dead·. All these simple ideas are brought together in ·the meaning of· the word ‘murder’. When I find that this collection of simple ideas agrees or disagrees with the esteem of the country I have grown up in, and is regarded by most men there as worthy praise or blame, I call the action •virtuous or vicious accordingly. If I have the will of a supreme invisible law-giver for my rule, then I call the action •good or bad, sin or duty, according to whether I think it has been commanded or forbidden by God. And if I compare the action to the civil law, the rule made by the legislative power of the country, I call it •lawful or unlawful, a crime or not a crime....

125

Essay II John Locke xxviii: Other relations

15. To conceive moral·ly significant· actions correctly, we must look at them in two different ways. 1 First, as they are in themselves, each made up of a certain collection of ·qualities represented by· simple ideas. Thus ‘drunkenness’ and ‘lying’ signify certain collections of simple ideas, which I call mixed modes; and understood in this way they are just as much positive absolute ideas ·with nothing relational, and so nothing moral, about them· as are ‘the drinking of a horse’ and ‘the speaking of a parrot’. 2 Secondly, our actions are considered as good, bad, or neither; and this is a relational way of looking at them, because what makes them regular or irregular, good or bad, is their conformity to or disagreement with some rule; and the comparison with a rule puts them into the category of relation. Thus duelling—·a positive, non-relational label·—is •a sin in relation to the law of God, •valour and virtue according to some laws of fashion, and •a capital crime according to the laws of some lands. In this case the action has one name (‘duelling’) taken just as a positive mode, and another name (‘sin’ etc.) as it stands in relation to the law; and the two names make it easy to grasp the difference between the non-relational and relational ways of looking at it; just as with substances we can have one name ‘man’) to signify the thing and another (‘father’) to signify the relation.

16. The positive idea of an action is often expressed in a word that also conveys the action’s moral relation, so that a single word expresses both the action itself and its moral rightness or wrongness. [Locke then warns against assuming that an action that falls under the non-moral part of such a word’s meaning must also fall under the moral part. He concludes with an example:] Taking a madman’s sword away from him without authority, though it is properly called ‘stealing’, understood as the ·non-relational· name of a mixed mode, is nevertheless not a sin or transgression in relation to the law of God.

[In section 17 Locke says that he thinks he has dealt with ‘some of the most considerable’ kinds of relation, and that there is no easy way to classify relations in general, because they are so numerous and various. He then announces a final trio of points.]

18. First, it is evident that all relations ultimately come down to the simple ideas we have acquired from sensation or reflection [Locke: ‘all relation terminates in and is ultimately founded on those simple ideas’]. So when we think or meaningfully say anything of a relational kind, all we have in our thoughts are some simple ideas, or collections of simple ideas, compared one with another. Nothing could be more obvious than this in the case of relations of the sort called ‘proportional’: when a man says ‘Honey is sweeter than wax’, it is plain that his thoughts terminate in the simple idea sweetness. This is equally true of all the rest ·of our relational thoughts·, though often the simple ideas are not taken notice of because the compounds containing them are so complex. When the word ‘father’ is used, its meaning involves •the particular species or collective idea signified by the word ‘man’, •the sensible simple ideas signified by the word ‘generation’, and •the effects of generation including all the simple ideas signified by the word ‘child’. [Locke gives a second example—a partial analysis of the meaning of ‘friend’, in which the fifth ingredient is] the idea of good, which signifies anything that may advance his happiness. This ·thought· terminates at last in particular simple ideas; the word ‘good’ in general can signify any one of these, but if it is entirely removed from all simple ideas it signifies nothing....

126

Essay II John Locke xxix: Clear/obscure, distinct/confused

19. Secondly, in relations we usually—if not always—have as clear a notion of the relation as we have of the things related.... If I know what it is for one man to be born of a woman, I know what it is for another man to be born of the same woman, and so have as clear a notion of brothers as of births. Perhaps clearer! For if I believed that his mother dug Titus out of the parsley-bed (as they used to tell children) and thereby became his mother, and that afterwards in the same way she dug Caius out of the parsley-bed, I would have as clear a notion of the relation of brothers between them as if I had all the skill of a midwife.... But though •the ideas of particular relations can be as clear and distinct in the minds of thoughtful people as those of mixed modes, and more determinate than those of substances, •words expressing relations are often as doubtful and uncertain in their meanings as names of substances or mixed modes, and much more than names of simple ideas. That is because a relational word is the mark of a comparison between two things—·an upshot of considering them together·—and this is something that occurs only in men’s thoughts; it is merely an idea in men’s minds; and it often happens that men apply a single relational word to different comparisons of things, according to their own imaginations, which don’t always correspond with those of others using the same word.

20. Thirdly, in moral relations (as I call them) I get a true relational thought by comparing the action with the rule, whether the rule itself is true or false. ·Similarly· if I measure a thing by a yardstick, I know whether the thing is longer or shorter than that supposed yard; but whether the yardstick I am using really is exactly a yard long is another question. Even if the rule I am invoking is wrong, and I am mistaken in relying on it, still I may perceive accurately that the action in question does, or that it doesn’t, conform to it.

Chapter xxix: Clear and obscure, distinct and confused ideas

1. I have shown the origin of our ideas, and surveyed their various sorts; and I have considered how the simple ones differ from the complex, and observed how the complex ones are divided into those of modes, substances, and relations. All this, I think, needs to be done by anyone who wants a thorough grasp of how the mind develops in its understanding and knowledge of things. You may think I have spent long enough examining ideas, but please let me say a little more about them. The first point is that some are clear and others obscure, some distinct and others confused.

2. The perception of the mind is most aptly explained by words relating to eyesight, so we shall best understand what ‘clear’ and ‘obscure’ mean as applied to ideas by reflecting on what they mean when applied to the objects of sight. Light is what reveals visible objects to us, so we describe as ‘obscure’ anything that isn’t placed in a good enough light to reveal in detail its shape and colours. Similarly, a simple idea is ‘clear’ when it is like an idea that one might receive in a well-ordered sensation or perception from an object of the kind that it comes from. While the memory retains

127

Essay II John Locke xxix: Clear/obscure, distinct/confused

them thus, and can produce them to the mind whenever it has occasion to consider them, they are clear ideas. In so far as they either lack some of the original exactness, or have lost any of their first freshness and are (so to speak) faded or tarnished by time, to that extent they are obscure. Complex ideas are clear when •their constituent simple ideas are clear and •the number and order of the simple ideas in the complex one is determinate and certain.

3. The causes of obscurity in simple ideas seem to be either •dull sense-organs, or •weak and fleeting impressions made by the objects, or else •a weakness in the memory which can’t retain them in the condition in which they were originally received. Think of the sense-organs or perceptual faculties in terms of sealing wax. •Frozen wax is too hard and won’t take an impression when the seal is pressed down on it in the usual way; •the wax that is all right won’t take an impression because the seal isn’t pressed down hard enough; and •very warm wax is too soft to retain the impression the seal gives it. In any of these cases the print left by the seal will be obscure. It is presumably clear enough how this applies to the obscurity of ideas.

4. A clear idea—·I repeat·—is one of which the mind has a perception that is as full and evident as it receives from an outward object operating properly on a healthy sense-organ. And a distinct idea is one in which the mind perceives a difference from all other ideas, and a confused idea is one that isn’t sufficiently distinguishable from another idea from which it ought to be different. ·This rather compressed and difficult account will become clearer in the course of the next two sections·.

5. It may be objected: ‘If the only way for an idea to be confused is for it to be inadequately distinguishable from another idea from which it should be different, it is hard to see how there can be any confused ideas. Whatever an idea is like, it can’t be different from what the mind perceives it to be; and that very perception sufficiently distinguishes it from all other ideas, for they can’t be other ideas—that is different ideas—without being perceived to be so. So no idea can be indistinguishable from another idea from which it ought to be different, unless you mean that it is different from itself; for from all other ideas it is obviously different.’

6. To remove this difficulty, and to help us to conceive correctly what the confusion is that ideas are sometimes accused of, we should note that things brought under different names are supposed to be different enough to be distinguished from one another, that so each sort can be marked off by its own special name and talked about, as need arises, separately from anything else. Quite obviously, most ·pairs of· different names are supposed to stand for ·pairs of· different things. Now, every idea that a man has is visibly what it is, and is distinct from all other ideas; so what makes it confused is its being such that it may as well be called by a name other than the one it is expressed by. Some things are supposed to fall under one of those names and others under the other; but in the sort of case just described—where someone has an idea that could go with either name—the difference has been lost.

7. The usual faults that lead to such confusion are, I think, of the following ·four· kinds. First, ·omission·. A complex idea (for they are the ones most liable to confusion) may be made up of too few simple ideas, containing only ideas ·all of· which are common to other things as well; in which case the idea leaves out the differences that entitle it to a different name. Thus someone who has an idea of merely a beast with spots has only a confused idea of a leopard, because it isn’t distinguished from that of a lynx and other sorts of spotted

128

Essay II John Locke xxix: Clear/obscure, distinct/confused

beasts.... You might want to consider how much the custom of defining words by general terms contributes to making the ideas we try to express by them confused and undetermined. This much is obvious: confused ideas bring uncertainty into the use of words, and take away the advantages of having distinct names.

8. Secondly, ·jumbling·. Another fault that makes our ideas confused occurs when, although the particulars that make up a ·complex· idea are numerous enough, they are so jumbled that it isn’t easy to see whether the idea belongs more properly to the name that is given it than to some other. The best way to understand this kind of confusion is to attend to a sort of pictures usually shown as surprising pieces of art, in which the colours, as they are laid by the pencil on the page itself, mark out very odd and unusual figures with no discernible order in their layout. This sketch, made up of parts in which no symmetry or order appears, is in itself no more a confused thing than the picture of a cloudy sky. The latter may have as little order of colours or shapes as the former, but nobody thinks it a confused picture. Then what makes it [i.e. the first picture] be thought of as confused, if not its lack of symmetry? (And that lack plainly doesn’t make it confused; for a picture that perfectly imitated this one ·would also lack symmetry etc., yet· wouldn’t be called confused.) I answer that the picture is thought to be confused when it is given a name that isn’t discernibly more appropriate to it than some other name. For example, when it is said to be the picture of a man (or of Caesar), then any reasonable person counts it as confused if it can’t be seen to fit ‘man’ (or ‘Caesar’) any more than it fits ‘baboon’ (or ‘Pompey’).... That is how it is with our ideas, which are as it were the pictures of things. No one of these mental sketches, however its parts are put together, can be called ‘confused’ until it is classified under some ordinary name that can’t be seen to fit it any more than does some other name whose meaning is agreed to be different.

9. Thirdly, ·wavering·. A third defect that frequently qualifies our ideas as ‘confused’ occurs when one of them is uncertain and undetermined. We sometimes see people who use the ordinary words of their language without waiting to learn their precise meaning, and change the idea they make this or that term stand for, almost as often as they use it. Someone who does this because he isn’t sure what to include in, and what to exclude from, his idea of church or idolatry every time he thinks of either, and doesn’t hold steady to any one precise combination of ideas that makes it up, is said to have a ‘confused idea’ of idolatry or of the church. The reason for saying this is the same as for speaking of ‘confusion’ where there is jumbling. It is because a changeable idea—if indeed we can call it one idea—can’t belong to one name rather than another; and so it loses the distinction that distinct names are designed for.

10. What I have said shows how much names—which are supposed to be steady signs of things, and through their differences to keep different things distinct ·in our minds·—are the occasion for labelling ideas as ‘distinct’ or ‘confused’, through the mind’s secretly and covertly relating its ideas to such names. This may be more fully understood in the light of my treatment of words in Book III. Without bringing in the relation of ideas to distinct names, as the signs of distinct things, it will be hard to say what a ‘confused idea’ is....

12. I think that this is the kind of confusion that is special to ideas, though even it involves a secret reference to names. Even if there is some other way for ideas to be confused, the one I have described is what mostly disorders men’s

129

Essay II John Locke xxix: Clear/obscure, distinct/confused

thoughts and discourses (for what men have in their minds whenever they converse with one another, and usually even when they are silently thinking, are ideas ranked under names).... The way to prevent this is to unite into one complex idea, as precisely as possible, all those ingredients that differentiate a given idea from others; and always to apply the same name to that complex. But this exactness is rather to be wished for than to be expected, because it is laborious and requires self-criticism, and it doesn’t serve any purpose except the discovery of naked truth—which isn’t everyone’s goal! And since the loose application of names to undetermined, variable, and almost no ideas, serves both to cover our own ignorance and to perplex and confound others—which counts as learning and superiority in knowledge!—it is no wonder that most men should engage in such faults themselves while complaining of it in others. But although I think that much of the confusion to be found in the notions of men could be avoided through care and ingenuity, I am far from concluding that it is all wilful. Some ideas are so rich and complex that (a) the memory doesn’t easily retain the very same precise combination of simple ideas under one name; (b) much less are we able constantly to guess what precise complex idea such a name stands for in another man’s use of it. From (a) follows confusion in a man’s own reasonings and opinions within himself; from (b) confusion in talking and arguing with others. I shall return to words, their defects and misuses, in Book III.

13. A complex idea is made up of a collection of different simple ones, so that it can be very clear and distinct in one part yet obscure and confused in another. When someone speaks of a chiliahedron, or a body with a thousand sides, the ideas of the shape may be confused though that of the number is distinct. He can talk about and do proofs concerning that part of his complex idea that depends on the number 1000, which may lead him to think that he has a distinct idea of a chiliahedron; yet he plainly doesn’t have a precise idea of its shape that would enable him to distinguish a chiliahedron by its shape from a figure that has only 999 sides. Unawareness of this problem causes no small error in men’s thoughts and confusion in their talk.

[Section 14 develops this point, contrasting two pairs of physical things: (a) a 1000-sided one and a 999-sided one, and (b) a cubic one and a five-sided one. We can distinguish the members of (a) through the different numbers (by counting the sides) but not by their different shapes, whereas we can distinguish the members of (b) in either way.]

15. We often use the word ‘eternity’, and think we have a positive comprehensive idea of it, which means that every part of that duration is clearly contained in our idea. Someone who thinks this may indeed have

a very clear idea of duration,

a clear idea of a very great length of duration, and

a clear idea of the comparison of the latter with a still greater duration.

But he can’t possibly include in his idea of any duration, however great, the whole extent of a duration in which he supposes no end; so the part of his idea that reaches beyond the bounds of that large duration he represents to his own thoughts—·that is, beyond the largest duration that he represents clearly·—is very obscure and undetermined. That is why, in disputes and reasonings concerning eternity or any other infinite, we are apt to blunder and to involve ourselves in obvious absurdities.

[In the long section 16 Locke discusses the attempts one might make to think clearly and positively about infinity. This discussion doesn’t add any doctrine to what has been

130

Essay II John Locke xxx: Real and fantastical ideas

said in xvii. All our attempts to think of infinite duration, or of infinitely extended or infinitely divisible space, he says, end up as attempts to think of infinite number. ‘When we talk about infinite divisibility of body, or about ·infinite· extension, our distinct and clear ideas are only of numbers; and after some progress of division the clear distinct ideas of extension are quite lost.’ As for the idea of infinite number, Locke dramatizes the inaccessibility (he thinks) of that by remarking that the attempt to reach it by successive additions of 400,000,000 is no better than trying to reach it by successive additions of 4.]

Chapter xxx: Real and fantastical ideas

1. There are other ways in which ideas can be thought of in relation to things from which they are taken, or things they are supposed to represent. These, I think, yield a trio of distinctions. Ideas may be

real or fantastical,

adequate or inadequate,

true or false.

·I shall treat the first pair in this chapter, the second in xxxi, and the third in xxxii·. By real ideas I mean ones that have a foundation in nature, and conform to the real being and existence of things, or to their archetypes [= ‘patterns or models from which they are copied’]. Fantastical or chimerical ideas are ones that have no foundation in nature, and don’t conform to that objective reality to which they are tacitly referred as to their archetypes. Let us apply this distinction to the sorts of ideas that I have distinguished.

2. First, our •simple ideas are all real, all agree to the reality of things. That isn’t to say that they are all images or representations of what exists, for I have shown that this isn’t so except with the primary qualities of bodies. But though whiteness and coldness are no more in snow than pain is, yet the ideas of whiteness and coldness, as well as of pain, are effects in us of powers in things outside us; they are real ideas in us, through which we distinguish the qualities that are really in things themselves. These various appearances were designed by God to be signs enabling us to know and distinguish things that we have to deal with; and our ideas can serve that purpose for us by being constant effects rather than exact resemblances of outer things. Their status as ‘real’ comes from how they dependably correspond with the constitutions of real beings; and it doesn’t matter whether they correspond as effects or as likenesses. So our simple ideas are all real and true, because they answer and agree to the powers of things that produce them in our minds; that being all it takes to make them real....

3. Though the mind is wholly passive in respect of its simple ideas, it isn’t so in respect of its complex ideas.They are combinations of simple ideas that have been assembled and united under one general name, and clearly the human mind has a certain freedom in forming them. How can

131

Essay II John Locke xxx: Real and fantastical ideas

it happen that one man’s idea of gold, or of justice, is different from another’s? It can only be because one •has included or omitted from his complex idea some simple idea that the other •has not. Well, then: which of these ·voluntarily constructed complex ideas· are real, and which merely imaginary combinations? What collections agree to the reality of things, and what not? ·My answer to that comes in two parts, one section each·.

4. Second: •mixed modes and relations have no reality except what they have in the minds of men, so all that is required for any such idea to be ‘real’ is that it be such that there could be something real to which it conformed. These ideas are themselves archetypes—·their own archetypes·—and so there can be no question of their differing from their archetypes ·and thus from themselves·! So the only way such an idea can chimerical is by its containing a jumble of inconsistent ideas.

Even when a complex idea isn’t inconsistent, it may be ‘fantastical’ in a certain sense because someone uses it as a meaning of a word that doesn’t ordinarily have that meaning—like using ‘justice’ to mean what is commonly meant by ‘liberality’. But this fantasticalness relates more to propriety of speech than reality of ideas. Consider these two ideas:

•being undisturbed in danger, calmly considering what it is best to do, and steadily doing it,

•being undisturbed in danger, without thinking or doing anything.

Each of these is a mixed mode, a complex idea of a state of being that could exist. The former of them fits the word ‘courage’ better than the other, which has no commonly accepted name in any known language; but there is nothing at all wrong with the latter considered just in itself.

5. Third: our •complex ideas of substances are all made in reference to things existing outside us, and are intended to represent substances as they really are. So such an idea is real only to the extent that it is a compound of simple ideas ·of qualities· that are really united in things without us. On the other side, those are fantastical that are made up of collections of simple ideas ·of qualities· that were never really united, never found together in any substance—such as

•a rational creature, consisting of a horse’s head, joined to a body of human shape, or

•a body that is yellow, malleable, fusible, and fixed [= ‘easily volatilized’], but lighter than common water, or

•a uniform, unstructured body that is capable of perception and voluntary motion.

Whether such substances can exist we don’t know; but we should count the ideas of them as merely imaginary because they don’t conform to any pattern existing that we know, and consist of collections of ideas ·of qualities· that no substance has ever shown us united together. But they are not as imaginary as the complex ideas that contain in them some inconsistency or contradiction among their parts.

132

Essay II John Locke xxxi: Adequate and inadequate ideas

Chapter xxxi: Adequate and inadequate ideas

1. Of our real ideas, some are adequate and some inadequate. I call ‘adequate’ the ones that •perfectly represent the archetypes that the mind supposes them to have been copied from, which it intends them to stand for, and to which it refers them. ‘Inadequate’ ideas are ones that •only partly or incompletely represent those archetypes to which they are referred. ·Let us now apply this distinction to each of our three big categories of ideas·.

2. First: all our •simple ideas are adequate. They are nothing but the effects of certain powers in things that are fit, and ordained by God, to produce such sensations in us; so they must correspond to and be adequate to those powers, and we are sure they agree with the reality of things. If sugar produce in us the ideas of whiteness and sweetness, we are sure there is a power in sugar to produce those ideas in our minds, or else they couldn’t have been produced by it. Thus, because each sensation corresponds to the power that operates on our senses, the idea so produced is a real idea, (and not a fiction of the mind, which has no power to produce any simple idea); and it cannot but be adequate since it ought only to correspond to that power. So all simple ideas are adequate.

It is true that we often talk inaccurately about the causes of these simple ideas of ours, using expressions that suggest that those ideas are real beings in the causally operative things. The fire’s power of producing in us the idea of pain we correctly report by saying that the fire •‘is painful to the touch’; but we handle differently its power to cause in us ideas of light and heat, saying that the fire itself •‘is bright’ and •‘is hot’, as though light and heat were not merely ideas in us but qualities in, or of, the fire. When I speak of things as having secondary qualities, please understand me as talking only about those powers. (I need to call them ‘qualities’ in order to fit in with common ways of talking, for otherwise I wouldn’t be well understood.) If there were no organs fit to receive the impressions fire makes on the sight and touch, or no mind joined to those organs to receive the ideas of light and heat through those impressions from the fire or sun, there would be no light or heat in the world (any more than there would be pain if there were no creature to feel it), even though Mount Aetna flamed higher than ever. In contrast, solidity, extension, shape, and motion and rest would still be really in the world if there were no sentient being to perceive them....

3. Second: our •complex ideas of modes, being voluntary collections of simple ideas that the mind puts together, without reference to any real archetypes or standing patterns existing anywhere, have to be adequate ideas. They aren’t intended to be copies of things really existing; we have them only as archetypes made by the mind to serve as standards for classifying and naming things; so they can’t lack anything. Each of them has the combination of ideas, and thus the perfection, that the mind intended it to have. Thus by having the idea of a figure with three sides meeting at three angles I have a complete idea that needs nothing more to make it perfect. That the mind is satisfied with the perfection of this one of its ideas is plain in that it has no thought of how there can be a more complete or perfect idea of triangle than that.

Contrast this with our ideas of substances: we want them to copy things as they really are, and to represent to us that constitution on which all the substances’ properties depend; and we see that our ideas don’t reach the intended level of

133

Essay II John Locke xxxi: Adequate and inadequate ideas

perfection. We find that they still lack something that we would like them to contain, and so they are all inadequate. But mixed modes and relations, being archetypes without patterns, and so having nothing to represent but themselves, must be adequate because everything is adequate to itself! Whoever first put together the idea of

danger perceived, absence of disorder from fear, calm consideration of what was justly to be done, and doing it without disturbance or being deterred by the danger of it

certainly had in his mind the complex idea made up of that combination; and as he intended it to be nothing but what is, and to contain only the simple ideas that it has, it couldn’t fail to be an adequate idea. And by laying this up in his memory with the name ‘courage’ attached to it, he gave himself a standard by which to measure and describe actions, according to whether they agreed with it. This idea thus made and laid up as a pattern must necessarily be adequate, as it is referred to nothing but itself, and takes it origin purely from the will of him who first made this combination.

[Section 4 makes the point that a second person may intend to use ‘courage’ with the same meaning—expressing the same idea—as the first, and yet get it wrong, associating the word with some other idea. In that case, his idea of courage is inadequate.]

[In 5 the point is developed further. Locke concludes:] In this way, but in no other, any idea of modes can be wrong, imperfect, or inadequate. And on this account our ideas of mixed modes are more liable to be faulty than any other kind; but this has to do with proper speaking rather than with true knowledge.

6. Third: I have shown above ·in xxiii· what ideas we have of •substances. Now, those ideas have in the mind a double reference: 1 Sometimes they are referred to a supposed real essence of each species of things. 2 Sometimes they are designed only to be pictures and representations in the mind of existing things, containing ·simple· ideas of the qualities we can discover in those things. In each of these respects, ideas of substances—these copies of those originals and archetypes—are imperfect and inadequate. ·I shall explain why for 1 in this section and the next, and for 2 in sections 8–10·.

Men usually make the names of substances stand for things considered as having certain real essences, which are what put them into this or that species. And because names stand for nothing but the ideas in men’s minds, men must constantly refer their ideas to such real essences as though they were what the idea was meant to represent. It is regarded as a commonplace, especially among those who have grown up with the scientific ideas taught in this part of the world, that each individual substance has a specific essence which makes it belong to a certain kind. Almost anyone who calls himself ‘a man’ takes himself to mean that he has the real essence of man. But if you ask what those real essences are, men obviously don’t know. It follows, then, that the ideas in their minds, purporting to represent unknown real essences, must be so far from being adequate that they can’t be supposed to be any representation of them at all. complex ideas of substances are certain collections of simple ideas ·of qualities· that have been observed or supposed constantly to exist together. But such a complex idea can’t be the real essence of any substance; for then the properties we discover in that body would depend on that complex idea, and be deducible from it, and their necessary connection with it be known; as all the properties of a triangle depend on and (as far as we can discover them) are deducible

134

Essay II John Locke xxxi: Adequate and inadequate ideas

from the complex idea of three lines enclosing a space. But our complex ideas of substances obviously don’t contain such ideas on which all the other discoverable qualities of the substance depend. The common idea men have of iron is a body of a certain colour, weight and hardness, and they also think of iron as malleable; but this property has no necessary connection with that complex idea; and there is no more reason to think that malleableness depends on that colour etc. than to think that colour etc. depends on malleableness. Yet it is very common for men to think that what puts things into different sorts is their different real essences, unknown as they are.

Consider the particular portion of matter that makes the ring I have on my finger: most men will unhesitatingly suppose it to have a real essence that makes it gold, and from which flow the qualities I find in it, namely its special colour, weight, hardness, fusibility, fixedness, and change of colour upon a slight touch of mercury, etc. When I enquire into and search for the essence from which all these properties ·supposedly· flow, it becomes obvious to me that I can’t discover it. The furthest I can go is to make this presumption: because the portion of matter is nothing but body, its real essence or internal constitution on which its other qualities depend must be the shapes, sizes, and connection of its solid parts. I have no distinct perception of any of this, so I can have no idea of that essence.

If anyone says that the real essence and internal constitution on which these properties depend isn’t the shape, size, and arrangement or connection of its solid parts, but something else called its particular form, this takes me still further away from having any idea of its real essence. ·Before ‘form’ came into the story, I did have something·. For I have an idea of shape, size, and situation of solid parts in general, though I have none of the particular shape, size, etc. that produce the qualities that I have mentioned—qualities that I find in the portion of matter circling my finger and not in the different portion of matter with which I trim my pen. But when I am told that something other than shape, size, etc. is its essence, something called ‘substantial form’, I confess to having no idea at all of this, but only of the sound of the word ‘form’, which is a good distance from an idea of a real essence or constitution!

I am equally ignorant of ·the details of· the real essence of this particular substance and of the real essences of all other natural kinds of substance. I think that others who examine their own knowledge will find themselves to be ignorant in the same way.

7. When men apply the word ‘gold’ to this particular portion of matter on my finger, don’t they usually mean the word to imply the matter’s belonging to a particular species of bodies by virtue of its having a real internal essence? Yes, they do. So for them the word ‘gold’ must be referred primarily to that essence, and so the idea that goes with it must also be referred to that essence and be intended to represent it. ·But an idea can’t represent something of which the idea’s owner knows nothing·. So those who use the word ‘gold’, not knowing the real essence of gold, have an idea of gold that is inadequate because it doesn’t contain that real essence that the mind intends it to. The same applies to all other natural kinds of substance.

8. Setting aside the useless supposition of unknown real essences, we can try to copy the substances that exist in the world by putting together the ideas of the sensible qualities that are found coexisting in them. This brings us much nearer to a likeness of them than is achieved by those who think in terms of real specific essences; but we still don’t arrive at perfectly adequate ideas of the substances in

135

Essay II John Locke xxxi: Adequate and inadequate ideas

question; our ideas don’t exactly and fully contain all the qualities that are to be found in their archetypes. That is because those qualities and powers of substances are so many and various that nobody’s complex idea contains them all. Men rarely put into their complex idea of any substance all the simple ideas ·of qualities that· they know to exist in that substance. Wanting to make the meanings of their words as clear and manageable as they can, they usually put into their specific ideas of the sorts of substance only a few of the simple ideas ·of qualities· that are to be found in them. But these have no special claim to be included while others are left out, so that clearly in both these ways—·that is, in the ideas of sensible qualities that they include, as well as in their secret reference to real essences·—our ideas of substances are deficient and inadequate. ·It isn’t merely that our ideas do omit many of the discoverable qualities of the substance; they must do so, for the following reason·. Except for shape and size in some cases, the simple ideas out of which we make our complex ideas of substances are all powers that are also relations to other substances. ·For example, a loadstone’s magnetic quality is its power to attract iron; a flower’s yellowness is its power to affect our eyesight in a certain way·. So we can never be sure that we know all the powers of a body until we have tried out how it can change or be changed by other substances when related to them in various ways. It is impossible to try all of that for any one body, much less for all bodies, so we can’t possibly bring any substance under an adequate idea made up of a collection of all its properties.

[In sections 9–10 Locke develops this line of thought, emphasizing how numerous the qualities of any kind of substance are, and how relatively accidental it is which subset of them get into the meaning of the common name for a kind of substance. He concludes section 10 with this remark about numerousness:] This won’t appear so much a paradox to anyone who thinks about that fairly simple figure the triangle—how much mathematicians have learned about it, and how far they still are from knowing all its properties.

11. So all our complex ideas of substances are imperfect and inadequate. The same would hold for mathematical figures if our complex ideas of them had to collect—·one by onew·—their properties in reference to other figures. ·In that case·, how uncertain and imperfect our idea of an ellipse would be, containing only a few of its properties! In fact, though, we have in our plain [Locke’s word] idea the whole essence of that figure, from which we discover its other properties and demonstratively see how they flow from it.

12. Thus the mind has three sorts of abstract ideas. First, simple ideas, which are copies, and are certainly adequate. That is because such an idea is intended to express nothing but the power in things to produce in the mind such a sensation ·or idea·, so that when that sensation is produced it must be the effect of that power....

13. Secondly, the complex ideas of substances are copies too, but not perfect ones, not adequate. This is very evident to the mind, which plainly perceives that whatever collection of simple ideas it makes of any real ·kind of· substance, it can’t be sure that it matches all ·the qualities· that are in that substance.... Furthermore, even if we had in our complex idea an exact collection of all the secondary qualities or powers of any substance, that wouldn’t give us an idea of the essence of that thing. The powers or qualities that are observable by us are not the real essence of that substance; they depend on it, and flow from it. Besides, a man has no idea of substance in general, nor knows what substance is in itself. ·See xxiii.1–2·.

136

Essay II John Locke xxxii: True and false ideas

14. Thirdly, complex ideas of modes and relations are originals, and archetypes; they aren’t copies, aren’t made after the pattern of any real existence that the mind intends them to fit and exactly to correspond to. Each of these collections of simple ideas that the mind itself puts together contains in it precisely all that the mind intends that it should.... The ideas of modes and relations, therefore, have to be adequate.

Chapter xxxii: True and false ideas

1. Though ‘true’ and ‘false’ are strictly applicable only to propositions, ideas are also often described as true or false. (What words are not used with great latitude, and with some deviation from their strict and proper meanings?) I think, though, that when ideas are termed ‘true’ or ‘false’ there is still some secret or tacit proposition on which that description is based. Look at particular occasions where ideas are called true or false, and you’ll find some kind of affirmation or negation at work. Ideas, being nothing but bare appearances or perceptions in our minds, can’t properly and simply in themselves be said to be true or false, any more than a single name can be said to be true or false.

2. Indeed both ideas and words may be called ‘true’ in a metaphysical sense of the word according to which anything that exists is ‘true’—that is, really is such as it is. Even when something is called ‘true’ in that sense, though, there is perhaps a secret reference to our ideas, looked on as the standards of that truth. That amounts to a mental proposition, though it is usually not taken notice of.

3. But our present topic is not that metaphysical sense of ‘true’, but rather the more ordinary meanings of ‘true’ and ‘false’. In the ordinary sense, then: the ideas in our minds are only so many perceptions or appearances there, so none of them are false. The idea of a centaur has no more falsehood in it when it appears in our minds than the name ‘centaur’ has falsehood in it when someone speaks or writes it. Truth or falsehood resides always in some affirmation or negation, mental or verbal; none of our ideas can be false until the mind passes some judgment on it, that is, affirms or denies something of it.

4. Whenever the mind refers one of its ideas to something extraneous to it, the idea becomes a candidate for being true or false, because in such a reference the mind tacitly assumes that the idea fits the external thing. According to whether that assumption is true or false, so can the idea itself be described. The most usual cases of this are the following ·three·.

5. First, when the mind assumes that one of its ideas matches the idea in other men’s minds called by the same common name; for example, when the mind intends or judges its ideas of justice, temperance, religion to be the same as what other men give those names to.

Secondly, when the mind supposes that one of it ideas fits some real existence. Thus the ideas of man and centaur,

137

Essay II John Locke xxxii: True and false ideas

supposed to be the ideas of real substances, are true and false respectively, one having a conformity to what has really existed, the other not.

Thirdly, when the mind refers an idea to the real constitution and essence of a thing on which all the thing’s properties depend. In this way most if not all our ideas of substances are false.

6. ....It is chiefly, if not only, concerning its abstract complex ideas that the mind makes such assumptions. Its natural tendency is towards knowledge; and it finds that if it dwelt only on particular things its progress would be very slow and its work endless; so it shortens its route to knowledge, and makes each perception [here = ‘idea’] more comprehensive, by binding things into bundles and grouping into sorts, so that what knowledge it gets of any of them it may confidently extend to all of that sort. This enables it to advance by longer strides towards knowledge, which is its great business....

7.....When the mind has acquired an idea that it thinks it may be useful in thought or in talk, the first thing it does is to abstract it, and then get •a name for it; and so tuck it away in its store-house, the memory, as containing the essence of a sort of things of which •that name is always to be the mark. When someone sees a new thing and asks ‘What is it?’, he is only asking what its •name is, as though the name carried with it the knowledge of the species, or of its essence....

8. •This abstract idea is something in the mind between •the thing that exists and •the name that is given to it. (·The •idea is what connects the •name with the •thing; for example, what makes ‘ring’ the right word for the thing around my finger is that 1 word ‘ring’ is associated with a certain abstract idea, and 2 that idea fits or conforms to the thing encircling my finger·.) So the rightness of our knowledge and the propriety and intelligibleness of our speaking both rely on our ideas. That is why men so freely suppose that the abstract ideas they have in their minds •agree to the outer things to which they are referred, and •are also the ones that commonly go with the names with which they associate them. Without this double conformity of their ideas, they would •think wrongly about things in themselves, and •talk unintelligibly about them to others. ·I shall discuss •talk in sections 9–12 and •thought in 13–18·.

9. First, when the truth of our ideas is judged by whether they match the ideas other men have and commonly signify by the same name, any of them can be false. But simple ideas are least liable to be mistaken in this way, because your senses and daily experience easily satisfy you regarding what the simple ideas are that various common words stand for. There aren’t many of them, and if you do suspect you are wrong about one of them you can easily correct that by going to the objects that involve them. So it seldom happens that anyone goes wrong in his names of simple ideas, applying the name ‘red’ to the idea green, for example, or the name ‘sweet’ to the idea bitter....

10. Complex ideas are much more liable to be false in this manner, and the complex ideas of mixed modes much more than those of substances. That is because substances (and especially ones that have common names in the language in question) have some conspicuous sensible qualities that ordinarily serve to distinguish one sort of substance from another; and this easily preserves careful users of the language from applying words to sorts of substances to which they don’t belong. But with mixed modes we are much more uncertain. It isn’t so easy to determine of various actions whether they are to be called ‘justice’ or ‘cruelty’, ‘generosity’

138

Essay II John Locke xxxii: True and false ideas

or ‘extravagance’. And so by the standard of match with the ideas that other men call by the same name, our idea may be false. The idea in our minds that we call ‘justice’ ought perhaps to have another name.

11. But whether or not our ideas of mixed modes are more liable than any other sort to be different from the idea that other men mark by the same names, it is certain at least that this sort of falsehood is much more commonly attributed to our ideas of mixed modes than to any other. When a man is thought to have a false idea of justice (or gratitude, or glory), it is simply because his idea doesn’t match the one that is the sign of justice (or gratitude, or glory) in the minds of other men.

12. Here is what I think is the reason for this. An abstract idea of a mixed mode is a precise collection of simple ideas that someone has chosen to put together; and so the essence of each sort is a human construct, which means that when we want to know whether a given item belongs to a given sort we have nowhere to look except to the relevant abstract idea. And if I want a standard by which to judge what I am saying or thinking about the given item, I can only appeal to the abstract ideas of the people who I think use the relevant name with its most proper meaning. That concludes my discussion of the truth and falsehood of our ideas in relation to their names.

13. Secondly—·picking up again from the end of section 8·—as to the truth and falsehood of our ideas in reference ·not to other people’s ideas, but· to the real existence of things: when that is the standard of their truth, the only ones that can be called ‘false’ are our complex ideas of substances.

14. Simple ideas are merely perceptions that God has fitted us to receive, and has enabled external objects to produce in us; and so their •truth consists purely in their being •appearances that are suitable to those powers God has placed in external objects.They are thus suitable, for if they were not, the objects wouldn’t produce them. So all such ideas are true. Nor do they fall under the charge of falsity if the mind judges (as in most men I believe it does) that these ideas are in the things themselves. God in his wisdom has set them as marks to help us to distinguish one thing from another, and it makes no difference to the nature of our simple idea ·or to its doing for us what God meant it to do· whether we think that the idea of blue is in the violet itself or in our mind only. [Locke goes on to expand this point a little, concluding thus:] The name ‘blue’ stands for that mark of distinction that is in a violet and that we can discern only through our eyes, whatever it ·ultimately· consists in, that being—perhaps fortunately—beyond our capacities to know in detail.

15. Simple ideas wouldn’t be convicted of falsity if through the different structure of our sense-organs it happened that one object produced in different men’s minds different ideas at the same time—for example, if the idea that a violet produced in one man’s mind by his eyes were what a marigold produced in another man’s, and vice versa. This could never be known, because one man’s mind couldn’t pass into another man’s body to perceive what appearances were produced by his organs; so neither the ideas nor the names would be at all confounded, and there would be no falsehood in either.... I am nevertheless inclined to think that the sensible ideas produced by any object in different men’s minds are usually pretty exactly alike. Many reasons could be offered for this opinion, but that is besides my present business, so I shan’t trouble you with them. Anyway, the contrary supposition, if it could be proved, would be

139

Essay II John Locke xxxii: True and false ideas

of little use either for the improvement of our knowledge or convenience of life; so we needn’t trouble ourselves to examine it.

[In sections 16–18 Locke repeats, with a little more detail, what he has said before. 16: simple ideas can’t be ‘false’ because of a wrong relation to external things. 17: Nor can complex ideas of modes be ‘false’ in that way, because they aren’t supposed to represent external things, though they can be ‘false’ in their relation to common language. 18: ideas of substances can be ‘false’ in relation to external things, either by including a secret reference to a real essence, or by aiming to include only ideas of perceptible properties of the substance-kind in question but getting the list of them wrong.]

19. Though in compliance with the ordinary way of speaking I have shown in what sense and for what reason an idea may be called ‘true’ or ‘false’, if we look more closely we find that in all those cases what is really true or false is some judgment that the mind makes or is supposed to make. Truth and falsehood always involve some affirmation or negation, explicit or tacit; they are to be found only where signs are joined or separated according to the agreement or disagreement of the things they stand for. The signs we chiefly use are either ideas and words, with which we make mental and verbal propositions respectively. Truth lies in so joining or separating these representatives, according to whether the things they stand for do in themselves agree or disagree; and falsehood in the contrary, as I’ll show more fully later on ·in IV.v·.

20. So any idea that we have in our minds, however it relates to external things or to ideas in the minds of other men, can’t properly be called false because of such a relation. Mistake and falsehood enter the picture in four ways.

21. First, there is falsehood when the mind has an idea that it mistakenly judges to be the same as what other men have in their minds and signify by the same name, i.e. to conform to the ordinary received meaning or definition of that word. This kind of error usually concerns mixed modes, though other ideas also are liable to it.

22. Secondly, falsehood occurs when the mind, having a complex idea made up of a collection of simple ones such as nature never puts together, judges it to fit a species of creatures really existing—for example, joining the weight of tin to the colour, fusibility and fixedness of gold.

23. Thirdly, there is falsehood when the mind makes a complex idea that unites some simple ideas ·of qualities· that do really exist together in some sort of thing, while omitting others that are inseparable from the first lot, and judges this to be a perfect complete idea of a sort of things which really it is not. For example, having joined the ideas of substance, yellow, malleable, most heavy, and fusible, the mind takes that to be the complete idea of gold, when really gold’s fixedness and solubility in aqua regia are as inseparable from those other ideas or qualities as they are from one another.

24. Fourthly, the mistake is even greater when I judge that this complex idea contains in it the real essence of some existing body, when really it contains only a few of the properties that flow from its real essence and constitution. [In the rest of this section Locke defends his saying ‘only a few’. He remarks yet again on how many properties of triangles flow from the seemingly simple real essence of triangle, and concludes:] I imagine it is the same with substances: their real essences are quite small, but the properties flowing from that internal constitution are endless.

140

Essay II John Locke xxxiii: Association of ideas

25. To conclude, a man has no notion of anything external to himself except through the idea he has of it in his mind; he is free to call the idea whatever he pleases, and to make an idea that neither fits the reality of things nor agrees to the idea commonly signified by other people’s words; but he can’t make a wrong or false idea of a thing that is known to him only through his idea of it. For example, when I form an idea of the legs, arms, and body of a man, and join to this a horse’s head and neck, I don’t make a false idea of anything, because it represents nothing external to me. But when I call it ·the idea of· a ‘man’ or a ‘Tatar’ and imagine it to represent some real being without me, or to be the same idea that others call by the same name, then I may err. That leads to the idea’s being called ‘false’, though really the falsehood lies not in the idea but in the tacit mental proposition attributing to it a fit and a resemblance that it doesn’t have....

[In section 26 Locke suggests that the true/false dichotomy, as applied to ideas on the basis of their fitting/not-fitting the ‘patterns to which they are referred’, might be better expressed in the language of ‘right’ and ‘wrong’. The point is purely verbal.]

Chapter xxxiii: The association of ideas

1. Almost anyone who observes the opinions, reasonings, and actions of other men will have noticed something that struck him as odd and that really is in itself wild. Everyone is quick-sighted enough to spot the least flaw of this kind in someone else and to condemn it as unreasonable—as long as the flaw is different from his own version of it. His own beliefs and conduct may show him to be guilty of something worse of the same general kind, but he doesn’t see it in himself and he’ll probably never be convinced that it is there.

2. This flaw doesn’t come wholly from self-love, though that often has a lot to do with it. Men of fair minds, not prone to extravagant self-flattery, are frequently guilty of it; and in many cases one hears the arguments of such a man with amazement, astonished at the obstinacy of a worthy man who doesn’t yield to the evidence of reason even when it is laid before him as clear as daylight.

3. This sort of unreasonableness is usually blamed on education and prejudice, and for the most part truly enough; but that doesn’t get to the bottom of the disease, or show distinctly enough what its ultimate source is or where it is located. Upbringing is often rightly assigned as the cause, and ‘prejudice’ is a good general name for the thing itself; but you need to dig deeper if you want to trace this sort of madness to the root from which it comes, explaining it in a way that will show how this flaw originates in sober and rational minds, and what it consists in.

4. You will pardon my calling it by so harsh a name as ‘madness’ when you reflect that opposition to reason deserves that name, and really is madness; and almost everyone has it severely enough to act or argue in some kinds of cases

141

Essay II John Locke xxxiii: Association of ideas

in ways which, if they spread throughout his life, would make him a candidate for a mad-house rather than for polite society. I don’t mean when he is overpowered by an unruly passion, but in the steady calm course of his life. In further defence of this harsh name, and the unpleasant accusation that it carries against most of mankind, I remark that when in xi.13 I enquired a little, in an aside, into the nature of madness, I found it to have very same cause as the flaw I am now speaking of. This struck me as right when I was thinking just about madness, without any thought of our present topic.

·One final point in defence of the label ‘madness’ is this·. If this flaw is a weakness to which all men are liable—a taint that so universally infects mankind—the greater should be our care to expose it under its right name, motivating people to give greater care to its prevention and cure.

5. Some of our ideas have a •natural correspondence and connection with one another, and it is reason’s business to trace these and to hold the ideas together in the union and correspondence that is based on their individual natures. There is also another connection of ideas, arising wholly from •chance or custom: ideas that have no kinship in themselves come to be so strongly linked in some men’s minds that it is very hard to separate them; as soon as one comes into the understanding its associate appears too, and if more than two are thus united the whole inseparable group show themselves together.

6. This strong tie between ideas that are not allied by nature is created by the mind either by choice or by chance, which is why there are different ties in men with different inclinations, education, interests, etc. Custom creates habits of •thinking in the understanding, as well as of •deciding in the will, and of •movement of the body. The habitual bodily movements ·at the most basic level· seem to be movements of the animal spirits: once these are started up, they continue in the ways they have been used to; and when these have been trodden for long enough they are worn into smooth paths, along which the motion becomes easy and seemingly natural. As far as we can understand thinking, ideas seem to be produced thus in our minds—·that is, produced through the movements of the animal spirits, so that the smoothing of paths (so to speak) explains intellectual as well as behavioural habits·. Even if ideas aren’t produced in that way, the notion of a worn path may nevertheless serve to explain their following one another in an habitual sequence once it has been begun, as well as it does to explain such motions of the body. A musician who is used to a particular tune will find that as soon at it begins in his head the ideas of its notes will follow on in due order in his understanding without any care or attention on his part, as regularly as his fingers move in the right order over the keys of the organ to play the tune he has begun, while his mind is on something else. This example suggests that the motion of the organist’s animal spirits really is the natural cause of his sequence of ideas of the notes, as well as of the regular dancing of his fingers; but I shan’t go into that. In any case, this comparison may help us a little to conceive of intellectual habits, and of the tying together of ideas.

7. That there are such associations of ideas made by custom in the minds of most men won’t, I think, be questioned by anyone who has attended thoroughly to himself or to others. Most of the sympathies and antipathies that can be seen in men might reasonably be assigned to this cause. The sympathies etc. work as strongly and produce effects in as regular a manner as if they were natural; and that leads people to think they are natural, though really they arose

142

Essay II John Locke xxxiii: Association of ideas

from an accidental connection of two ideas which—either because the first impression was so strong, or because the person subsequently allowed the two ideas to occur together in his mind—came to be so united that they always afterwards kept company together in that man’s mind, as if they were a single idea. I say ‘most of the antipathies’, not ‘all’, because some of them are truly natural, depend on our original constitution, and are born with us. But many others are counted natural which would, if they had been observed with enough care, have been known to arise from unheeded early impressions or from wanton fancies. An adult has a surfeit of honey, after which he reacts badly—with nausea etc.—to any mention or thought of honey. He knows when this weakness of his began, and what caused it. But if it had come from an over-dose of honey when he was a child, all the same effects would have followed but he wouldn’t have recognized its cause and would have regarded the antipathy as natural.

8. My present purposes in this book don’t require me to distinguish accurately between natural and acquired antipathies; but I have a different reason for mentioning that distinction. ·It is to issue a warning·: those who have children, or have charge of their upbringing, should think it worth their while to watch carefully to prevent the undue connection of ideas in the minds of young people. Early childhood is the time most susceptible to lasting impressions; and although discreet people attend to impressions that could harm the health of the body, and protect the young against them, those that could harm the mind, and have their effects in the understanding or the passions, have been much less heeded than they deserve. Indeed, those relating purely to the understanding have, I suspect, been wholly overlooked by nearly everyone.

[In sections 9–10 Locke develops this theme a little.]

11. A man is harmed by another, and thinks about •that man and •his action over and over; and by brooding over them strongly or frequently, he cements •those two ideas together so as to make them almost one. Whenever he thinks of the man, the pain and distress he suffered from him comes into his mind as well, so that he hardly distinguishes them, and has as much an aversion to the one as to the other. This is how hatreds often spring from slight and innocent occasions, and quarrels are propagated and continued in the world.

[Section 12 presents another example.]

13. When this combination ·of ideas· is settled, and for as long as it lasts, reason is powerless to help us and relieve us from the effects of it. ·For· once an idea is in our minds, it will operate according to its nature and circumstances ·and cannot be swerved or dislodged by reason·. This lets us see how the following can happen:

Someone has a recurring emotional pattern that his reason can’t overthrow, though it is unreasonable, and this person listens to his reason in other cases. This disorder is, however, cured by the passing of time.

The death of a child who was the daily delight of his mother’s eyes and the joy of her soul rips from her heart the whole comfort of her life and utterly torments her. To use the consolations of reason in this case is as useless as to preach ease to someone on the rack in the hope that rational discourses will allay the pain of his joints being torn apart. There is no way of reasoning the woman out of her tie between the thought of the child and the thought of her loss of pleasure, but the two thoughts may be separated by

143

Essay II John Locke xxxiii: Association of ideas

the passing of time, through which the tie is weakened by disuse. In some such people the union between these ideas is never dissolved, and they spend their lives in mourning, and carry an incurable sorrow to their graves.

[Sections 14–16 add anecdotes—some of them quite extraordinary—concerning associations of ideas.]

17. Intellectual habits and defects that come about in this way are just as frequent and as powerful ·as habits of behaviour and feeling·, though less notice is taken of them. Let the ideas of •being and of •matter be strongly joined either by education or by prolonged thought, and while they are tied together in a person’s mind, what thoughts and arguments will he put up concerning unembodied Spirits? ·Because in this person’s thought the idea of something real always brings with it the idea of something material, he will regard the notion of unembodied Spirit—something real and immaterial—as weird and almost contradictory·.

Let someone from early childhood associate the idea of •God with the idea of •shape, and what absurdities will he be liable to believe concerning the Deity?

Let the idea of •infallibility be inseparably joined in someone’s mind to ·the idea of· •some person, and the man whose mind has this association will swallow any absurdity that is affirmed by the supposedly infallible person—for example that a single body can be in two places at once.

18. Some such wrong and unnatural combinations of ideas will be found at the root of the irreconcilable opposition between different sects of philosophy and religion; for we can’t imagine that every follower of a sect deliberately sets himself to reject, knowingly, truth that is offered by plain reason. Self-interest is at work here, but even it can’t bring a whole society of men to such a universal perversity, with every single one of them maintaining something that he knows to be false. We must allow that at least some of them do what they all claim to do, namely to pursue truth sincerely; so there must be something that blinds the understandings of these sectarians, not letting them see the falsehood of what they embrace as real truth. What thus puts their reasons in chains and leads men blindfolded away from common sense turns out to be my present topic:

Some •ideas that are not naturally allied to one another, are—by upbringing, custom, and the constant din of the sect—so joined in the sectarians’ minds that •they always appear there together; and the sectarians can no more separate •them in their thoughts than if they were only a single idea—which is what they treat •them as being.

This gives sense to jargon, demonstration to absurdities, and consistency to nonsense! It is the foundation of the greatest errors in the world. I almost wrote ‘of all the errors in the world’; and if it isn’t quite as bad as that, it does produce the most dangerous errors because when it operates it hinders men from seeing and examining. [Locke adds some fine rhetorical flourishes.]

19. I have now given an account of the origin, sorts, and extent of our ideas, with several other points concerning these instruments or materials of our knowledge (may I call them that?). The project on which I embarked requires me now to go on immediately to show how the understanding uses ideas and what knowledge we have through them. In my first general view of the topic, I thought that this was all that would remain to be done at this point. But now that I have reached it, I find that ideas are so closely connected with words, and ·in particular· that abstract ideas are so regularly related to general words, that it is impossible to speak clearly and distinctly of our knowledge (which all consists in propositions) without considering first the nature, use, and meanings of language. That, therefore, is the business of the next Book.

144

An Essay Concerning Human Understanding

Book III: Words

John Locke

Copyright © 2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are reported on, between [brackets], in normal-sized type.
First launched: July 2004 Last amended: August 2007
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Chapter i: Words or language in general 145
Chapter ii: The signification of words 146
Chapter iii: General terms 148
Chapter iv: The names of simple ideas 155
Chapter v: The names of mixed modes and relations 158
Chapter vi: The names of substances 162
Chapter vii: Particles 175

Essay III John Locke

Chapter viii: Abstract and concrete terms 176
Chapter ix: The imperfection of words 177
Chapter x: The misuse of words 183
Chapter xi: The remedies of those imperfections and misuses 190

Essay III John Locke i: Words in general

Chapter i: Words or language in general

1. God, having designed man to be a sociable creature, not only made him with an inclination and a need to have fellowship with other men, but also equipped him with language, which was to be the great instrument and common tie of society. So nature shaped man’s organs so that he could make articulate sounds, which we call ‘words’. But this wasn’t enough to produce language, for parrots and some other birds can learn to make distinct enough articulate sounds, yet they are far from being capable of language.

2. Besides articulate sounds, therefore, man had also to be able to use these sounds as signs of internal conceptions, making them stand as marks of ideas in his own mind. This was so that he could make those ideas known to others, thus conveying thoughts from one mind to another.

3. But this still didn’t suffice to make words as useful as they ought to be. If every particular thing had to be given a separate name, there would be so many words that the language would be too complicated to use; so a fully satisfactory language needs sounds that, as well as being signs of ideas, can be used in such a way that one word covers a number of particular things. So language was improved in yet another way by coming to include general terms, so that one word can mark a multitude of particular things. Sounds could be used in this helpful manner only by signifying ideas of a special kind: names become general if they are made to stand for general ideas, and names remain particular if the ideas they signify are particular. [Locke regularly uses ‘name’ to cover not only proper names but also general words such as ‘woman’, ‘island’, ‘atom’ and so on.]

4. Besides these names standing for ideas, there are other words that men use to signify not any idea but rather the lack or absence of certain ideas or of all ideas whatsoever. Examples are nihil [= ‘nothing’] in Latin, and in English ‘ignorance’ and ‘barrenness’. These negative or privative words can’t be said properly to have no ideas associated with them, for then they would be perfectly meaningless sounds. Rather, they relate to positive ideas, and signify their absence.

[In section 5 Locke discusses the words referring to items far removed from anything of which we have sense-experience. The meanings of many such words, he says, are borrowed from ideas of sense-perception.] For example, ‘imagine’, ‘apprehend’, ‘comprehend’, ‘adhere’, ‘conceive‘, etc. are all words taken from the operations of perceptible things and applied to certain modes of thinking....

6. But to understand better the use and force of language as a means for instruction and knowledge, we should tackle two questions. 1 In the use of language, what are names immediately applied to? Also, given that all words (except proper names) are general, and so stand not for particular things but for sorts and kinds of things, 2 what are these sorts and kinds (or, if you prefer Latin, these species and genera)? what do they consist in? how do they come to be made? When we have explored these thoroughly, we’ll have a better chance of finding the right use of words, the natural advantages and defects of language, and the remedies that ought to be used to avoid obscurity or uncertainty in the signification of words. Without that, we can’t talk in a clear and orderly way about knowledge; and knowledge, which has to do with propositions (most of them universal ones), has a greater connection with words than perhaps is suspected. So these matters will be the topic of the following chapters.

145

Essay III John Locke ii: Signification of words

Chapter ii: The signification of words

1. A man may have a great variety of thoughts that could bring profit and delight to others as well as to himself; but they are all locked up inside him, invisible and hidden from others, and incapable of being brought out into the open. If society is to flourish, thoughts must be communicated; so people had to devise some external perceptible signs through which they could let one another know of those invisible ideas of which their thoughts are made up. For this purpose nothing was so suitable—because plentiful and quickly available—as those articulate sounds they found they could make so easily and in such variety. That is presumably how men came to use spoken words as the signs of their ideas. There is no natural connection between particular sounds and particular ideas (if there were, there would be only one human language); but people arbitrarily chose to use such and such a word as the mark of such and such an idea. So that is what words are used for, to be perceptible marks of ideas; and the ideas they stand for are their proper and immediate signification [= ‘meaning’]. [Locke uses ‘arbitrary’ in what was then its dominant sense, as meaning ‘dependent on human choice’, not implying that the choice was random or unreasonable or unmotivated. This will be important in v.3 and thereafter.]

2. Men use these marks either •to record their own thoughts as an aid to their memory or •to bring their ideas out into the open (so to speak) where others could see them. So words in their primary or immediate signification stand for nothing but the ideas in the mind of him that uses them, however imperfectly or carelessly those ideas are taken from the things they are supposed to represent. When one man speaks to another, it is so as to be understood; and the goal of his speech is for those sounds to mark his ideas and so make them known to the hearer. What words are the marks of, then, are the ideas of the speaker. And nobody can apply a word, as a mark, immediately to anything else. For that would involve making the word be a sign of his own conceptions, and yet apply it to another idea; which would be to make it a sign and yet not a sign of his ideas at the same time; which would in effect deprive it of all signification. ·In case it isn’t clear to you why I say ‘a sign of his own conceptions’, I shall explain: applying the word as a mark of a thing involves applying it intending it to stand for that thing, which means applying it with an accompanying thought about the word’s significance·.

·Here is a second argument for the same conclusion·. Words are voluntary signs, and can’t be voluntary signs imposed by someone on something that he doesn’t know, for that would be to make them signs of nothing, sounds without signification. For a man to make his words be the signs either of •qualities in things or of •conceptions in someone else’s mind, he must have in his own mind •ideas of those qualities or conceptions. Till he has some ideas of his own, he can’t suppose them to correspond with the conceptions of another man. And when a man represents to himself other men’s ideas by some of his own, he may agree to give them the same names that other men do; but it is still his own ideas ·that he immediately signifies·—ideas that he has, not ones that he lacks.

3. This is necessary if language is to succeed—so necessary that in this respect ignorant people and learned ones all use words in the same ways. Meaningful words, in each man’s mouth, stand for the ideas that he has and wants to express by them. A child who has seen some metal and heard it

146

Essay III John Locke ii: Signification of words

called ‘gold’, and has noticed nothing in it but its bright shining yellow colour, will apply the word ‘gold’ only to his own idea of that colour and to nothing else; and so he will call that same colour in a peacock’s tail ‘gold’. Someone who has also noticed that the stuff is heavy will use the sound ‘gold’ to stand for a complex idea of a shining, yellow, and very heavy substance. Another adds fusibility to the list; and then for him the word ‘gold’ signifies a body that is bright, yellow, fusible, and very heavy. Another adds malleability, and so on. Each uses the word ‘gold’ when he has occasion to express the idea that he has associated with it; but obviously each can apply it only to his own idea, and can’t make it stand as a sign of a complex idea that he doesn’t have.

4. But although words can properly and immediately signify nothing but ideas in the mind of the speaker, yet men in their thoughts give words a secret reference to two other things. First, they suppose their words to be marks also of ideas in the mind of the hearer. Without that they would talk in vain; if the sounds they applied to one idea were applied by the hearer to another, they couldn’t be understood, and would be speaking different languages. Men don’t often pause to consider whether their ideas are the same as those of the hearers. They are satisfied with using the word in what they think to be its ordinary meaning in that language; which involves supposing that the idea they make it a sign of is precisely the same as the one to which literate people in that country apply that name.

5. Secondly, because a man wants his hearers to think he is talking not merely about his own imagination but about things as they really are, he will often suppose his words to stand ·not just for his ideas but· also for the reality of things. This relates especially to substances and their names, as perhaps the former ‘secret reference’ does to simple ideas and modes ·and their names·; so I shall deal more fully with these two different ways of applying words when I come to discuss the names of mixed modes and especially of substances. Let me just say here that it is a perverting of the use of words, and brings unavoidable obscurity and confusion into their signification, whenever we make them stand for anything but ideas in our own minds.

6. Two further points about words are worth noting. First, because they immediately signify one’s own ideas,....the constant use of a word may create such a connection between that sound and the idea it signifies that hearing the word excites the idea almost as readily as if the relevant kind of object were presented to the senses. This is manifestly so in regard to all the obvious perceptible qualities, and in regard to in all substances that frequently come our way.

7. Secondly, through familiar use of words from our cradles we come to learn certain articulate sounds very perfectly, and have them readily on our tongues and always at hand in our memories, yet aren’t always careful about what exactly they mean; and so it comes about that men, even when they want to think hard and carefully, often direct their thoughts more to words than to things. Indeed it goes further. Many words are learned before the ideas for which they stand are known, and so it happens that some people—not only children, but adults—utter various words just as parrots do, because they have learned them and have been accustomed to those sounds. But so far as words are useful and significant, so far is there a constant connection between the sound and the idea, and a designation that the one stands for the other. ‘Words’ that are not thus connected with ideas are nothing but so much insignificant noise.

[In section 8 Locke emphasizes that each word has its meaning by a purely ‘arbitrary imposition’, and that ultimately it

147

Essay III John Locke iii: General terms

is for each individual to decide what idea he will associate with a given word. There are practical reasons for wanting one’s own word-idea pairings to be the same as those of most speakers and hearer’s in one’s own society; but that is a practical concern that leaves standing the fact of personal responsibility for the meanings of one’s speech.]

Chapter iii: General terms

1. Since all things that exist are particulars, it might be thought reasonable that words, which ought to conform to things, would stand for particular things. But the facts are quite different: most words in all languages are general terms. There are reasons for this; indeed it was inevitable—·for three reasons·.

2. First, it is impossible for every particular thing to have a name all of its own. Because the meaningful use of words depends on the mind’s connecting them with the ideas of which they are signs, the mind must contain those ideas, and it must have stored within itself all the information about which idea is signified by each word. But it is beyond our power to form and retain separate ideas of all the particular things we meet with: every bird and beast that men have seen, every tree and plant that has affected the senses, couldn’t find a place in the most capacious understanding. When a general knows by name every soldier in his army, this is thought to be a prodigious feat of memory; so it is easy to see why men have never tried to give a name to each sheep in their flock, or every crow that flies over their heads; much less to call every grass-blade or grain of sand that comes their way by its own proper name.

3. Secondly, even if this were possible, it would be useless, because it would get in the way of language’s main purpose. Nothing would be achieved by heaping up names of particular things: that wouldn’t help us to communicate our thoughts. The only reason to learn names and use them in talk with others is so as to be understood; and for that to happen the sound I make through my organs of speech must arouse in your mind the same idea that I had in mind when I spoke. This can’t be done through names that stand only for particular things of which I alone have the ideas in my mind. If you haven’t encountered those very same things, the words that I use to stand for them won’t be intelligible to you.

4. Thirdly, even if this were feasible (which I don’t think it is), a separate name for every particular thing wouldn’t be of much use for increasing our knowledge. Although knowledge is ultimately based on particular things, it broadens itself to take general views of things; and for this it needs to group them into sorts, under general names. These sorts, with the names belonging to them, are fairly limited in number; they don’t multiply beyond what the mind can contain or beyond what we have use for. That is why men have mostly relied on such general names, though they also give individual names

148

Essay III John Locke iii: General terms

to particular things when it is convenient to do this—for example, giving proper names to individual people whom they often have occasion to mention.

5. Not only persons but also countries, cities, rivers, mountains, and other geographical items are often given singular names, and always for the same reason. If we had reason to mention particular horses as often as we have particular men, no doubt we would use proper names for the former as we do for the latter.... That is how it is with jockeys, for whom horses have proper names to be known and picked out by, because they often have occasion to mention this or that particular horse when he is out of sight ·and therefore can’t be designated by pointing·.

6. Now we must consider how general words come to be made. For since all things that exist are only particulars, how do we come by general terms? Where do we find those ‘general natures’ they are supposed to stand for? Words become general by being made the signs of general ideas; and ideas become general by separating from them the circumstances of time and place and any other ideas that may tie them down to this or that particular existence. By means of such abstraction they are fitted to represent more than one individual. Every individual that conforms to that abstract idea is of that sort (as we call it).

7. To understand this more clearly, let us trace our notions and names from their beginning in infancy, and see how they develop from there. It’s perfectly obvious that the ideas of the persons that children encounter are, like the persons themselves, only particular. The ideas of the nurse and the mother are well formed in an infant’s mind. They represent only those individuals, and the only words that the infant has for the individuals are, in effect, proper names, like ‘Nurse’ and ‘Mamma’. As they get older and meet more people, infants notice that many other things in the world resemble—in shape and in other ways—their father and mother and other people they have been used to; and they form an idea that applies equally to all those many particular people, associating this idea with the name ‘man’. [Here, as nearly everywhere, Locke uses ‘man’ to mean ‘human’; it isn’t confined to the male sex.] That is how they come to have a general name and a general idea. In doing this, they don’t •make anything new, but only •leave out of the complex ideas they had of Nurse and Mamma, Peter and James, Mary and Jane, whatever is unique to each, and retain only what is common to them all.

8. In the same way that they come by the general name ‘man’ and the general idea of man, they easily advance to names and notions that are even more general. They notice that various things that differ from their idea of man, and so can’t be brought under the name ‘man’, nevertheless share certain qualities with man. By uniting just those qualities into one idea, leaving all other qualities out, they come to have another yet more general idea, which they associate with a new word that applies to more things than ‘man’ does. This new idea is made not by adding anything but only, as before, by leaving out the shape and some other properties signified by the name ‘man’, and retaining only a body, with life, sense, and spontaneous motion. Those are the properties signified by the name ‘animal’.

9. It is obvious that this is how men first came to form general ideas and to associate general names with them. To see that it is right, you have only to consider what goes on in your mind, or in the minds of others, when you or they think and gain knowledge. Someone who thinks that general natures or notions are anything but such abstract and partial ideas, drawn from more complex ideas and originally

149

Essay III John Locke iii: General terms

taken from particular existing things, will be at a loss to say what they are. Reflect on your own mind and then answer this: How does your idea of man differ from your idea of Peter and Paul (or your idea of horse differ from your idea of Bucephalus) except by leaving out whatever is unique to each individual and retaining only what is present in all the complex ideas of particular men (or particular horses)? Again, by starting with the complex ideas signified by the names ‘man’ and ‘horse’, omitting whatever features they don’t share and retaining only those that are common to both, we can form a complex idea to which we give the name ‘animal’. Leave sense and spontaneous motion out of the idea of animal, and what remains are the simpler ideas of body, life, and nourishment; they constitute a more general idea that we associate with the term ‘living’. In the same way the mind proceeds to ‘body’, ‘substance’, and at last to universal terms that stand for any of our ideas whatsoever—I mean terms such as ‘being’ and ‘thing’. To conclude, this whole mystery of genera and species, which they make such a fuss about in the schools and which are rightly disregarded everywhere else, is simply a matter of more or less comprehensive abstract ideas, with names tied to them. [A genus (plural: genera) is a large class; a species is a smaller one within it. Mankind may be seen as a species within the genus of animals. The ‘schools’ mentioned here are the universities of western Europe in the late Middle Ages. Thinkers who accepted the (mostly Aristotelian) doctrines in metaphysics, logic and theology that were taught there were known as ‘Schoolmen’ or ‘Scholastics’.] There are no exceptions to this: every more general term stands for such an idea, and the idea is merely a part of any of the ideas associated with less general terms contained under the more general one—·so that, for instance, the idea of ‘animal’ is a part of the ideas of ‘man’ and of ‘tiger’·.

10. This may show us why we sometimes define a word—that is, declare its meaning—in terms of the ‘genus’ or next general word that covers it. This saves the labour of listing all the simple ideas that the next general word or genus stands for; and it may sometimes spare us from the shame of not being able to do that! Although defining by genus and differentia is the shortest way, however, it may not be the best.... [The ‘differentia’ is what marks off the species within the genus. Taking adult human as a genus and woman as a species, the differentia is female.] It is certainly not the only way, so we aren’t absolutely required to follow it. To define a word is simply to make someone else understand through words what idea the defined word stands for; and the best way to do this is by straightforwardly enumerating the simple ideas that are combined in the meaning of the word being defined. If, instead, most of those simple ideas are conveyed by naming the genus under which the defined word falls, that isn’t done out of necessity, or even for greater clearness, but merely for the sake of speed and convenience. If someone wants to know what idea the word ‘man’ stands for, his needs will be as well met by being told that man is a solid extended substance, having life, sense, spontaneous motion, and a capacity for reasoning as by being told that man is a rational animal. The two definitions are really equivalent, by virtue of the meanings of ‘animal’, ‘living’ and ‘body’. This example illustrates what led people to the rule that a definition must consist of genus and differentia; and it also shows that the rule is not necessary and not even very useful.... I shall say more about definitions in the next chapter.

11. To return to general words, it is plain from what I have said that generality and universality are not properties of reality itself, but are something the understanding has

150

Essay III John Locke iii: General terms

invented for its own convenience, and they apply only to ·verbal and mental· signs—words and ideas. I repeat: •a word is general when it is used as a sign of a general idea, so that it applies to many particular things; and •an idea is general when it is taken to represent many particular things; but universality doesn’t belong to things themselves, which are all particular in their existence—even the words and ideas that have general meanings. ·For example, the word ‘chapter’ at the end of your copy of the last section is in itself a particular array of ink on a page; but its meaning isn’t particular but general, because it is applicable to any chapter·. So the only general items there are have been created by us, and they are ‘general’ only in the sense that we can use them to signify [= ‘mean’] or represent many particulars. Their meaning is nothing but a relation that is added to them by the human mind.

12. Let us now consider what kind of signification general words have. Obviously such a word doesn’t •signify just one particular thing—for then it wouldn’t be a general term but a proper name—but it is equally evident that it doesn’t •signify a plurality. ·For example, ‘man’ isn’t the name of some one man; but nor is it a name for some group of men or for the totality of all men·. If it did signify a plurality, ‘man’ would mean the same as ‘men’, and the distinction between singular and plural would disappear. What a general word •signifies is a sort of things; and it does this by standing for an abstract idea in the mind. When existing things are found to conform to that idea, they come to be classified under that name, or—to say the same thing in different words—they come to be of that sort. This makes it evident that the essences of the sorts of things (or species of things if you prefer Latin) are nothing but these abstract ideas. [The ‘essence’ of a sort is the set of features that are essential for a thing to be of that sort. To know what is needed for something to be of a the sort gold (Locke is saying), you start with the general word ‘gold’, are led from that to your abstract idea of gold, and the features represented in that abstract idea are the essence of gold.] What makes a thing belong to a ·sort or· species is its having the essence of that species; and what gives a thing a right to a species name is its conforming to the idea with which that name is associated. Thus, for something to •have the essence of a species is just for it to •conform to the idea associated with that species’ name; that is all there is to it. ·I shall now re-state all this in slightly different terms, illustrating it through the sort man, though of course it applies equally well to any other sort, and any other general term·. Each of the items in the following list is equivalent to the item that immediately follows it:

•having the essence of man

•being a man, or belonging to the species man

•having a right to the name ‘man’

•conforming to the abstract idea that the name ‘man’ stands for.

So the first item is equivalent to the last: the abstract idea for which the name stands, and the essence of the species, is one and the same. This makes it easy to see that the essences of the sorts of things, and consequently the sorting of things, is all done by the understanding that abstracts and makes those general ideas.

13. I haven’t forgotten—still less do I deny—that nature makes things in such a way that some of them are like others. This is perfectly obvious, especially in the case of animals and plants. Still, it is all right to say that the sorting of things under ·general· names is the work of the understanding. What it does is to attend to the similarities it finds amongst things, and on the basis of those it makes abstract general ideas (with names attached), which it uses

151

Essay III John Locke iii: General terms

as patterns. When a particular existing thing is found to agree with one of these patterns, it comes to be of that species, to have that name, or to be put into that class. For when we say ‘This is a man’, ‘That is a horse’, ‘This is justice’, ‘That is cruelty’, ‘This is a watch’, ‘That is a bottle’, all we do is to classify things under different specific names [= ‘names of species’] because they conform with the abstract ideas that we use those names to signify. And the •essences of the species that we have set out and marked by names are simply the •abstract ideas in the mind, which are (as it were) the bonds that tie particular things to the names under which they are classified. What connects a general name with a particular thing is the abstract idea that unites them: So that the essences of species, as picked out and labelled by us, can’t be anything but these abstract ideas that we have in our minds. If the supposed ‘real essences’ of things are different from our abstract ideas, they can’t be the essences of the species into which we group things. Nothing in the natures of things themselves dictates which groups of them constitute a single species, rather than two species or parts of a single species. What changes can you make in a horse or a piece of lead without making either of them belong to a different species? If you go by our abstract ideas, this is easy to answer; but if you try to go by supposed real essences, you will be at a loss—you’ll never be able to settle exactly when any thing ceases to belong to the species of horse or lead.

14. My claim that these essences or abstract ideas are the work of the understanding will come as no surprise to anyone who realizes that complex ideas are often different collections of simple ideas in the minds of different men—so that people will differ, for instance, in what they mean by saying that someone is ‘covetous’. Abstract ideas of substances seem to be dictated by the things themselves, yet even they are not settled and the same for everyone—even as regards our own species. It has sometimes been doubted whether a particular fetus born of a woman was human, with debates about whether it should be kept alive and baptized. This couldn’t happen if the abstract idea or essence to which the name ‘human’ belonged were of nature’s making, rather than being an uncertain collection of simple ideas that various people’s understandings have put together ·in different ways· and associated with a name. Really, then, every distinct abstract idea is a distinct essence, and the names that stand for such distinct ideas are the names of things that are different in their essences. Thus a circle is as essentially different from an oval as a sheep is from a goat; and rain is as essentially different from snow as water is from earth. In each case, the essence of one kind isn’t present in the other. So any two abstract ideas that differ from one another in any way at all, with two distinct names annexed to them, constitute two distinct sorts or species, which are as essentially different as any two of the most remote or opposite in the world.

15. Some people think that the essences of things are wholly unknown, and they have some reason for this. To understand it, we should consider the various meanings of the word ‘essence’. First, ‘essence’ may be taken for the very being of any thing—what makes it be what it is. Using the term in this way, a thing’s ‘essence’ is its internal constitution—the real but usually unknown inner nature on which its perceptible qualities depend. This is the proper original meaning of the word, as can be seen from its origin: the Latin essentia comes from the verb esse, which means ‘to be’. The word ‘essence’ is still used in this sense, when we speak of the essence of particular things without giving them any name. [The point of the last

152

Essay III John Locke iii: General terms

five words is this. If I use the phrase ‘the essence of this gold coin’, I could be referring to its essence-considered-as-a-gold-coin, which is dictated by the meaning of the phrase ‘gold coin’. But if I hold up a gold coin and use the phrase ‘the essence of this’, without giving it any name, I have to mean ‘essence’ in some way that doesn’t depend on the meaning of a word; so I mean the inner nature of this thing, call it what you will.] Secondly, academic wrangling about genus and species has had the effect of almost entirely suppressing that original meaning of ‘essence’. Instead of referring to the real constitutions of things, essences these days are usually thought of in a second way, in which they are connected with the artificial constitution of genus and species. ·Real constitutions are ones that are laid down in the things themselves; artificial ones are products of human artifice, that is, of human classificatory procedures·. When people talk in this way, they assume that each sort of things has a real constitution; and it is unquestionably true that any collection of simple ideas [here= ‘qualities’] that regularly go together must be based on some real constitution. But the fact remains that when things are classified into sorts or species, and named accordingly, what we go by are the abstract ideas with which we have associated those names. The essence of each genus or sort—·that is, what fixes the sort, what determines membership in it·—is just the abstract idea that the general name stands for. This, we shall find, is how ‘essence’ is mostly used. These two sorts of essences could reasonably be called the real and the nominal essence respectively [‘real’ comes from Latin res = ‘thing’; ‘nominal’ comes from Latin nomen = ‘name’].

16. Nominal essences are tied to names. Whether a given thing x is to be described by a given general name depends purely on whether x has the essence that makes it conform to the abstract idea that the name is associated with.

17. [Here and later Locke speaks of ‘monstrous’ births. A monster is an organism which is markedly and disturbingly different from what is normal for its species.] There are two opinions about the real essences of bodies. •Some people think there is a certain ·limited· number of real essences according to which all natural things are made. Each particular thing, they believe, exactly fits one of these essences, and thus belongs to one species. These folk use the word ‘essence’ without knowing what essences are. •Others have a more reasonable view: according to them, the essence of a natural thing is the real but unknown constitution of its imperceptible parts, from which flow the perceptible qualities on the basis of which we classify things into sorts under common names. The former of these opinions, which takes essences to be a certain number of forms or moulds into which all natural things are poured (so to speak) has created great confusion in the knowledge of natural things. In every animal species, births frequently occur, and human births sometimes produce imbeciles or other strange products ·which are not clearly human and not clearly non-human·; and all this poses problems for this hypothesis about real essences.... Even apart from those difficulties, the mere fact that these ·‘first-opinion’· real essences can’t be known means that they are useless to us in classifying things, although they are supposed to mark off the real boundaries of the species! In our thoughts about classification, then, we ought to set these supposed real essences aside—·and, for the same reason, set aside ‘second-opinion’ real essences as well·—and content ourselves with knowable essences of sorts or species. When we think the matter through, we shall see that these are, as I have said, nothing but the abstract complex ideas with which we have associated separate general names.

153

Essay III John Locke iii: General terms

18. Having distinguished essences into nominal and real, I point out that in the species of •simple ideas and •modes the two kinds of essence are always the same, while with •substances they are always quite different. Thus ·a mode such as· a figure including a space between three straight lines is the real as well as the nominal essence of a triangle; for it isn’t only •the abstract idea to which the general name is attached, but also •the very essentia or being of the thing itself, that foundation from which all its properties flow and to which they are all inseparably united. It isn’t like that with the portion of matter that makes the ring on my finger, which apparently has two different essences. All its perceptible properties of colour, weight, fusibility, fixedness, etc. flow from ·its real essence, that is· the real constitution of its imperceptible parts; we don’t know •this constitution, so we have no •particular idea of it and, therefore, no •name that is the sign of it. But its colour, weight, fusibility, fixedness, etc. are what make it gold, or give it a right to that name; so they are its nominal essence. ·What they constitute really is an ‘essence’, properly so-called·, since nothing can be called ‘gold’ unless its qualities fit that abstract complex idea to which the word ‘gold’ is attached. This distinction between two kinds of essence is especially relevant to substances; I’ll deal with it more fully when I come to the names of substances ·in vi·.

19. For more evidence that such abstract ideas with names attached to them really are essences, consider what we are told regarding essences, namely that they cannot be created or destroyed. This can’t be true of the real constitutions of things, which begin and perish with the things. All things that exist (except God) are liable to change, especially the things we have come across and have sorted into groups under separate names. What is •grass to-day will tomorrow be •the flesh of a sheep, and a few days after that become •part of a man. In all such changes, it is evident that the thing’s real essence—the constitution of it on which its properties depend—is destroyed, and perishes with the thing. On the other hand, essences considered as ideas established in the mind with names attached to them are supposed to remain steadily the same, whatever changes the particular substances undergo. Whatever becomes of Alexander and Bucephalus, the ideas to which ‘man’ and ‘horse’ are attached are supposed to remain the same; and so the essences of those species—·of man and of horse·—are preserved whole and undestroyed, whatever changes happen to any man or horse, or indeed to all men or horses. By this means the essence of a species remains safe and whole, even if there doesn’t exist a single individual of that kind. [Locke gives other examples: the idea of circle (supposing there were no exact circles), of unicorn, of mermaid. He concludes:] From what has been said it is evident that the doctrine of the of essences proves them to be only abstract ideas. Being founded on the relation established between those ideas and certain sounds as signs of them, the doctrine will always be true as long as the same name can have the same meaning.

20. Summing up, all the great business of genera and species, and their essences, amounts to nothing but this: when people make abstract ideas and settle them in their minds with names attached, they enable themselves to think and talk about things in bundles, as it were. This enables them to communicate and learn more quickly and easily; their knowledge would grow very slowly if their words and thoughts were confined to particulars.

154

Essay III John Locke iv: Names of simple ideas

Chapter iv: The names of simple ideas

1. Although all words immediately signify ideas in the mind of the speaker, and nothing else, closer scrutiny shows that each of the main categories of names—of simple ideas, of mixed modes (which I take to include relations), and of natural substances—has peculiarities of its own. ·I shall point out six of these. The first (section 2) is a feature shared by names of simple ideas and substances but not by mixed modes, the second (section 3) is a feature of the names of simple ideas and mixed modes but not of substances, the third (sections 4–14) and fourth (15) and fifth (16) are peculiarities of the names of simple ideas; the sixth (17) also differentiates names of simple ideas from those of substances and, even more strongly, from those of mixed modes·.

2. First, the names of •simple ideas and •substances, as well as the abstract ideas in the mind that they immediately signify, indicate also some real existence from which came the idea that was their original pattern. But the names of •mixed modes terminate in the idea in the mind and don’t lead thoughts any further. I shall enlarge on this in the next chapter.

3. Secondly, the names of •simple ideas and •modes signify always the real as well as nominal essence of their species ·because with each of these the nominal essence is the real essence·. But the names of •natural substances rarely if ever signify anything but the nominal essences of those species. I shall show this in vi.

4. Thirdly, the names of •simple ideas can’t be defined; the names of all •complex ideas can. ·So can the names of •substances, but I shall say nothing about them in the following ten sections·. So far as I know, nobody has explored the question of what words can and what can’t be defined. The lack of knowledge about this seems to me to contribute to great wrangling and obscurity in men’s discourses: some demand definitions of terms that can’t be defined, and others think they ought to be satisfied with equating a word with a more •general word and its •restriction (or in technical terms, a ‘definition through •genus and •difference’ [see note in iii.10]), even when the definition made according to that rule doesn’t help anyone to understand the meaning of the word better than he did before. I think, anyway, that it is relevant to my present purposes to show what words can and what cannot be defined, and what a good definition consists in. This may throw enough light onto the nature of these signs and ·of their relation to· our ideas to justify this more thorough enquiry.

5. I shan’t trouble myself here to prove that not all terms are definable, arguing from the infinite regress that we would obviously be led into if we tried to define all names: if the terms of each definition had to be defined by yet another, where would the process end? ·Rather than labouring that·, I shall argue from the nature of our ideas and the signification of our words, showing why some names can be defined and others cannot, and which are which. ·The argument from infinite regress doesn’t pick on any name as indefinable, still less show why it is so·.

6. I think it is agreed that to define a word is to show its meaning through several other words no one of which is synonymous with it. The meaning of a word is just the idea that the user makes it stand for; so he shows the meaning of a term—he defines it—when he uses other words to set

155

Essay III John Locke iv: Names of simple ideas

before the hearers the idea that the defined word stands for. This is all that definitions are good for, and all they are meant to do; so it is the only measure of what is or is not a good definition.

7. On that basis, I say that the names of simple ideas, and they alone, cannot be defined. Here is why. Defining is really nothing but showing the meaning of one word through several others no one of which signifies the same thing; ·so the terms of a definition must jointly signify the idea that the defined word signifies·; but the different terms of a definition, signifying different ideas, can’t jointly represent an idea that is simple and thus has no complexity at all. So definitions can’t be given for the names of simple ideas.

[In section 8 Locke jeers at Aristotelian philosophers (‘the schools’) for offering absurd definitions of some of these words, and for leaving many others ‘untouched’. Their fault, one gathers, was to leave the latter untouched without saying why they had to do so.]

9. The modern philosophers have tried to throw off the jargon of the schools and to speak intelligibly, but they haven’t had much more success in defining ·names of· simple ideas, whether by explaining their causes or in any other way. Consider the atomists, who define ‘motion’ as a passage from one place to another: what do they do except to put one synonymous word for another? For what is passage other than motion? Isn’t it at least as proper and significant to say ‘Passage is a motion from one place to another’ as to say ‘Motion is a passage, etc.’? Equating two words that have the same signification is translating, not defining. If one word is better understood than the other, the equation may help someone to learn what idea the unknown word stands for; but this is very far from a definition. If you call it a definition, you will have to say that every English word in the dictionary is the definition of the Latin word it corresponds to, so that ‘motion’ is a definition of motus....

[In section 10 Locke mocks a supposed Aristotelian definition of ‘light’. Its worthlessness can be seen, he says, from its obvious inability to enable a blind man understand ‘light’. (He remarks in passing that this type of argument can’t be used against definitions of ‘motion’, because the idea of motion can enter the mind through touch as well as sight, so that nobody is perceptually cut off from motion as the blind are from light.) He continues:] Those who tell us that light is a great number of little globules striking briskly on the bottom of the eye speak more intelligibly than the schools; but these words, however well understood, wouldn’t help a man who has no idea of light to get such an idea.... Even if this account of the thing is true, it gives only the idea of the cause of light, and that doesn’t give us the idea of light, any more than the idea of the shape and motion of a sharp piece of steel would give us the idea of the pain it can cause in us. The cause of a sensation and the sensation itself are two ideas, and are as different and distant one from another as two ideas can be. Therefore, if the globules that Descartes postulates were to strike ever so long on the retina of a blind man, that would never give him an idea of light, or anything like it, even though he perfectly understood what little globules are, and what it is for something to strike on another body. So the Cartesians do well to distinguish •light that causes that sensation in us from •the idea that the former produces in us. It is the latter that is light properly so-called.

11. Simple ideas, as I have shown, can be acquired only from the impressions that objects make on our minds through the appropriate sensory inlets. If one of them isn’t received in this way, all the words in the world won’t suffice to

156

Essay III John Locke iv: Names of simple ideas

explain or define its name by producing in us the idea it stands for. Words are just sounds, and the only simple ideas they can produce in us are the ideas of those very sounds—except when a simple idea is connected with a word through common usage in which that idea is the word’s meaning. If you doubt this, see whether you can by words give anyone who has never tasted pineapple an idea of the taste of that fruit. He may approach a grasp of it by being told of its resemblance to other tastes of which he already has the ideas in his memory, imprinted there by things he has taken into his mouth; but this isn’t giving him that idea by a definition, but merely raising up in him other simple ideas that will still be very different from the true taste of pineapple. [Locke continues with more along the same lines, applied to ‘light and colours’. The section concludes:] A studious blind man who had used explanations written in books or given to him by his friends in an attempt to understand the names of light and colours that he often encountered bragged one day that he now understood what ‘scarlet’ signified. It was, he said, like the sound of a trumpet! That’s the sort of ‘understanding’ of the name of a simple idea that can be expected from someone relying on verbal definitions or other explanations.

12. The case is quite otherwise with complex ideas. A complex idea consists of several simple ones, and words that stand for those constituent simple ideas can imprint the complex idea in the mind of someone who had never had it before, and so make him understand the name of that idea. When a single name applies to such a collection of ideas, a definition can occur, teaching the meaning of one word by several others, making us understand the names of things that never came within the reach of our senses. [Locke adds the proviso that the person who learns a meaning through a definition must understand all the words that are used in it; and decorates this point with an uninstructive joke about a blind man adjudicating between a statue and a picture.]

13. Someone who had never seen a rainbow but had seen all those colours separately could come to understand the word ‘rainbow’ perfectly through an enumeration of the shape, size, position and order of the colours. But even a perfect definition of that kind would never make a ·congenitally· blind man understand the word, because several of the simple ideas that make that complex one haven’t been given to him through sensation and experience and can’t be aroused in his mind by words.

[Section 14 summarizes the content of the preceding ten sections.]

15. Fourthly [following ‘Thirdly’ in section 4], although the names of •simple ideas don’t have the help of definitions to fix their meanings, they are generally less doubtful and uncertain than are the names of •mixed modes and •substances. Because the former stand for one simple perception each, people mostly agree—easily and perfectly—about their meanings, there being little room for mistake and wrangling. Someone who once grasps that ‘white’ is the name of the colour he has observed in snow or milk won’t be apt to misapply the word as long as he retains that idea; and if he entirely loses the idea, this will lead him not to mistake the meaning of the word but rather to see that he doesn’t understand it. There is no multiplicity of simple ideas to be put together, which is what brings doubt into the names of •mixed modes; nor is there a supposed but unknown real essence....which creates problems over the names of •substances. Rather, in the case of •simple ideas the whole signification of the name is known at once, and doesn’t consist of parts of which more or fewer may be put in by different people, making the

157

Essay III John Locke Chapter v: Names of mixed modes etc.

signification of the name obscure or uncertain. 16. Fifthly, simple ideas and their names have only a few ascents in the line of predication from the lowest species to the highest genus. [An example of a word with many ‘ascents’ might be ‘man’: from it we can ascend to ‘animal’, to ‘organism’, to ‘complex physical thing’, to ‘physical thing’.] This is because the lowest species is just one simple idea, so that nothing can be left out of it so as to get something more general ·in the way that something is left out of man to get the more general animal·. For example, there is nothing that can be left out of the ideas of white and of red to make them agree in one common appearance and so have one general name; as rationality being left out of the complex idea of man makes it fall under the more general idea and name of ‘animal’. When men want for brevity’s sake to bring white and red and several other such simple ideas under one general name, they do it with a word that denotes ·not something common to the natures of these different ideas, but· only the way they get into the mind. For when white, red, and yellow are brought together under the genus or name ‘colour’, all that this means is that such ideas are produced in the mind only by the sight and get in only through the eyes. And when men want to develop a still more general term, to cover colours and sounds and the like simple ideas, they do it with a word (·namely, ‘quality’·) that signifies all ideas that come into the mind by only one sense. And so the general term ‘quality’ in its common meaning applies to colours, sounds, tastes, smells, and tangible qualities, as distinct from extension, number, motion, pleasure, and pain, which make impressions on the mind, and introduce their ideas, by more senses than one.

17. Sixthly, the names of simple ideas, substances, and mixed modes differ also in the following way. Names of •mixed modes stand for ideas that are perfectly arbitrary; those of •substances are not perfectly arbitrary, but refer to a pattern, though they have some latitude ·in how the patterning is done·; and those of •simple ideas are perfectly taken from the existence of things, and are not arbitrary at all. In the following chapters we shall see what difference this makes in the significations of their names. The names of simple modes are pretty much like the names of simple ideas.

Chapter v: The names of mixed modes and relations

1. The names of mixed modes being general, they stand for sorts or species of things, each of which has its own special essence. The essences of these species are nothing but the abstract ideas in the mind, to which the name is attached. Up to here, the names and essences of mixed modes have nothing that they don’t share with all other ideas; but if we look more closely we’ll find that they have peculiarities of their own that may be worth studying.

2. The first peculiarity I shall note is that the abstract ideas (or, if you like, the essences) of the various species of mixed modes are made by the understanding. In this they are

158

Essay III John Locke Chapter v: Names of mixed modes etc.

unlike those of [= the ideas of?] simple ideas. The mind has no power to make any one of the latter, but only accepts what comes to it through the operations on it of the real existence of things.

3. In the next place, these essences of the species of •mixed modes are very arbitrarily made by the mind, without patterns or any reference to any real existence. [See note at end of iii.2.] In this they differ from those of •substances, which carry with them the supposition of some real thing from which they are taken and which they fit. In its complex ideas of mixed modes, the mind permits itself not to follow the existence of things exactly. It unites and retains certain collections, each as a specific complex idea, while other collections that are just as common in nature and just as plainly suggested by outward things are neglected and not given special names. When we examine a complex idea of a ·kind of· substance, we have recourse to the real existence of things—·that is, to the stuff itself·; but we don’t proceed like that with mixed modes, checking them against patterns containing such complexes in nature. If you want to know whether your idea of adultery or incest is right, will you check it out against existing things?.... No. All that is needed is for men to have put together such a collection into one complex idea; that is the archetype [= ‘thing that is copied’], whether or not any such action ·as incest or adultery· has ever actually been performed.

4. To understand this correctly, we must think about what the mind does in making such complex ideas. It •selects some of the ·simpler· ideas it already has, then •connects them so as to turn them into one idea, and finally •ties them together by a name. If we examine how the mind goes about these three activities, and what freedom of choice it we shall easily see how these essences of the species of mixed modes are the workmanship of the mind, and thus that the species themselves are of men’s making.

5. To become sure that these ideas of mixed modes are made by a voluntary collection of ideas put together in the mind, independently of any original patterns in nature, think about the fact that any such idea can be made, abstracted, and named—so that a species is constituted—before any individual of that species exists. Obviously the ideas of sacrilege and adultery could have been framed in the minds of men and have names given to them—thus constituting these species of mixed modes—before either of them was ever committed. They could have been talked and reasoned about, and truths discovered concerning them, just as well •back when they existed only in the understanding as •now when they are all too common in the real world. We cannot doubt that law-makers have often made laws about sorts of actions that were only the creatures of their own understandings, having no existence outside their own minds. And nobody can deny that resurrection was a species of mixed modes in the mind before it really existed.

[In section 6 Locke seeks to show ‘how arbitrarily these essences of mixed modes are made by the mind’ by looking at examples. It is we who choose to pick out killing one’s father and not killing a sheep, and so on. The section concludes:] I don’t say that these choices are made without reason (more about this later); but I do say that we have here are the free choice of the mind, pursuing its own ends; and that therefore these species of mixed modes are artifacts of the understanding. And it is utterly evident that when the mind forms these ideas it seldom looks for its patterns in nature, or checks the ideas it makes against the real existence of things. Rather, it puts together such ·collections of simple ideas· as may best serve its own purposes, without tying

159

Essay III John Locke Chapter v: Names of mixed modes etc.

itself to a precise imitation of anything that really exists.

7. But, although these complex ideas (or essences) of mixed modes depend on the mind and are made by it with great freedom, they are not made at random and jumbled together for no reason. They are always suited to the purpose for which abstract ideas are made. Their constituent ideas have no more union with one another than various others which the mind never combines into one complex idea, but they are always made for the convenience of communication, which is what language is mainly for. What language does is to enable the speaker to express general conceptions quickly and easily, through short sounds; and such a general conception not only covers a great many particulars but also involves a great variety of independent ideas collected into one complex one. In making species of mixed modes, therefore, men have attended only to such combinations as they have wanted to mention one to another. [The section continues with examples, and an explanation of why the ideas daughter and mother are both ingredients in the idea of a heinous kind of sexual intercourse (incest) though only mother is an ingredient in parricide, the idea of a heinous kind of killing.]

[Section 8 develops the point that a language may contain words that have no exact equivalent in another language, offering this as evidence for Locke’s thesis that the ideas and names of mixed modes are answerable only to human interests and needs. The section concludes:] We shall find this much more so with the names of more abstract and compounded ideas, such as most of those that make up moral discourses. If you look carefully into how those words compare with the ones they are ·customarily· translated into in other languages, you will find that very few of them exactly correspond across the whole extent of their meanings.

9. The reason why I emphasize this thesis so strongly is to prevent us from being mistaken about genera and species and their essences, as if they were things regularly and constantly made by nature and had a real existence in things—·that is, as though enquiring into the essence of the species sacrilege were like enquiring into the essence of the species iron·.... The suspect meaning of the word ‘species’ may make my statement ‘The species of mixed modes are made by the understanding’ grate in your ears; but you can’t deny that the mind makes those •abstract complex ideas to which specific names are given; and it is also true that the mind makes the •patterns for sorting and naming of things. Well, then, think about it: who makes the •boundaries of the sort or species? (For me ‘species’ and ‘sort’ are equivalent, one Latin and the other English.)

10. For further evidence of the close inter-relations amongst •a species, •an essence, and •its general name (at least with mixed modes), notice that it is the name that seems to preserve those essences and give them their lasting duration. The loose parts of those complex ideas aren’t held together by any particular foundation in nature; so they would lose their connection and scatter if something weren’t holding them together. The mind makes the collection, but the name is the knot (so to speak) that ties them together. [The remainder of this section elaborates this point, with an example, and aims a parting shot at ‘those who look on essences and species as real established things in nature’.]

11. So we find that when men speak of mixed modes, they seldom think of any species of them other than those that have been named. ·And we can see why this should be so·.... To what purpose should the memory burden itself with such complexes other than to make them general by abstraction? And why would it do that if not so as to

160

Essay III John Locke Chapter v: Names of mixed modes etc.

have general names for the convenience of discourse and communication? [The section goes on with examples of differences in the ‘collections’ made by people in different cultures.]

12. My account of the essences of the species of mixed modes is further confirmed by the fact that their names lead our thoughts to the mind and no further. When we speak of ‘justice’ or ‘gratitude’ we have no thought of any existing thing; our thoughts terminate in the abstract ideas of those virtues, and look no further. We do look further when we speak of a ‘horse’ or ‘iron’, whose specific ideas we think of not as merely •in the mind but as •in things that are the original patterns of those ideas. But with mixed modes—or at least the most important subset of them, namely the moral ones—we regard the original patterns as being •in the mind.... I think this is why these essences of the species of mixed modes are called ‘notions’, as pertaining in a special way to the understanding. [Here and in some other places, ‘moral’ means little more than ‘pertaining to human conduct’.]

13. From this we can also learn why the complex ideas of •mixed modes are commonly more compounded—·more complex·—than those •of natural substances. Ideas of mixed modes are made by the understanding for convenience in expressing through short sounds the ideas it wants to make known to others; and in thus pursuing its own purposes it exercises great freedom, often uniting into a single abstract idea things that don’t in their own nature go together, and so under one name bundle together a great variety of....ideas. Think about the word ‘procession’: what a great mixture of independent ideas of persons, clothes, candles, orders, motions, and sounds have been arbitrarily put together by the mind of man to be expressed by that one word! Whereas the complex ideas of sorts of substances are usually made up of only a few simple ideas; and when it comes to the species of animals, the whole nominal essence often consists of nothing but shape and voice.

14. Another thing we can see from what I’ve said is that the names of mixed modes always signify the real essences of their species. These abstract ideas are the workmanship of the mind, and aren’t referred to the real existence of things, so there is no supposition of anything’s being signified by that name beyond the complex idea the mind has formed. And all the properties of the species depend on and flow from that idea alone. Thus, in these ·species· the real and nominal essences are the same. We shall see later what bearing this has on secure knowledge of general truths.

15. This may also show us why the names of mixed modes are usually learned before the ideas they stand for are perfectly known. It is convenient if not outright necessary to know the names before one tries to form these complex ideas, because usually we don’t attend to the ones that don’t have names (and all of them—·it should be remembered·—are arbitrary mental constructs). The alternative is for a man to fill his head with a horde of abstract complex ideas ·of mixed modes· which others have no names for and thus he has no use for, except to set them aside and forget them again! I agree that in the beginning of languages it was necessary to have the idea before one gave it the name; and so it is still when someone makes a new complex idea, gives it a new name, and thereby makes a new word. But....in language as a going concern, isn’t it usual for children to learn the names of mixed modes before acquiring the ideas of them? Does one child in a thousand form the abstract ideas of glory and ambition before hearing their names? With •simple ideas and •substances it is otherwise. Those ideas have a real existence and union in nature, and in their case it’s a

161

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

matter of chance which comes first, the idea or the name.

16. What I have said here about mixed modes can be applied with very little difference to relations as well; and I needn’t go on about this, because everyone can see it for himself. One reason for cutting that short is that my treatment of words in this third Book may strike some as excessively long for such a slight topic. I agree that it could have been briefer; but I was willing to take my reader through an argument that appears to me new, and a little out of the way (it certainly hadn’t occurred to me when I began to write). My hope has been that if I explore it to the bottom, and turn it on every side, each reader may find in it something that fits with his own thoughts and leads him—however careless or disinclined he may be—to give some thought to a general blunder that has hardly been noticed before although it is of great consequence. When you think what a fuss is made about essences, and how greatly all sorts of knowledge, discourse, and conversation are bedevilled and disordered by the careless and confused use of words, you may think it worthwhile set all this out thoroughly. A reason why I think my views on this matter need to be inculcated (and this is an excuse for going on so long about them) is that the faults they expose don’t just hinder true knowledge—they are positively admired and thought of as being true knowledge! If only men would look beyond fashionable sounds, and observe what ideas are or are not conveyed by the words that they are so armed with at all points, and that they so confidently wield in battle, they would see what a vanishingly small pittance of reason and truth is mixed in with those puffed-up opinions they are swelled up with. I shall think I have done some service to truth, peace, and learning if I can, through an extended discussion of this subject, •make men reflect on their own use of language, and •give them reason to suspect that they may sometimes have very good and approved words in their mouths and writings with meanings that are uncertain, skimpy, or non-existent. ·They will acknowledge that· others are frequently guilty of this, so might not they be guilty too? If they see this, it will be reasonable for them to become wary about their own performances, and willing to submit themselves to examination by others. With this purpose in mind, therefore, I shall continue with the rest of what I have to say about this matter.

Chapter vi: The names of substances

1. The common names of substances, as well as other general terms, stand for sorts—which simply means that they are used as signs of complex ideas in which several particular substances do or might agree, by virtue of which they can be brought under one common conception and referred to by one name. I say ‘do or might agree’ for the following reason. There is only one sun in the world, but the idea of it is an abstract one, so that more substances could agree in it; sun is as much a sort as it would be if there were as many suns as there are stars. There are reasons for

162

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

thinking that indeed there are, and that each fixed star when seen from a suitable distance would fit the idea the name ‘sun’ stands for. That, incidentally, illustrates how much the sorts of things—or, if you like, the genera and species of things (for those Latin terms mean the same to me as the English word sort)—depend on what collections of ideas men have made, and not on the real nature of things; since what is a sun to one person may be a star to someone else.

2. The measure and boundary of each sort or species, by which it is constituted as that particular sort and distinguished from others, is what we call its essence. This is nothing but the abstract idea to which the name is attached; so that everything contained in the idea is essential to that sort. Although this is the only essence of natural substances that we know, and the only one by which we can distinguish them into sorts, I give it the special name ‘nominal essence’, to distinguish it from the •real constitution of substances. [See note at end of iii.15.] The latter is •the source of the nominal essence and of all the properties of that sort ·or species·; and so it can be called ‘the real essence’ of the sort. For example, the nominal essence of gold is the complex idea that the word ‘gold’ stands for—something like a body that is yellow, of a certain weight, malleable, fusible, and fixed. But the real essence is the constitution of the imperceptible parts of that body, on which those qualities and all the other properties of gold depend. Although both of these are called ‘essence’, you can see at a glance how different they are.

3. The complex idea to which I and others attach the name ‘man’, making that the nominal essence of the species man, is the idea of voluntary motion, with sense and reason, joined to a body of a certain shape. Nobody will say that this complex idea is the •real essence and source of all those operations that are to be found in any individual of that sort, ·that is, in any man·. The •foundation of all those qualities that are the ingredients of our complex idea of man is something quite different. Angels may, and God certainly does, have a full knowledge of the •constitution of man from which his faculties of moving, sensing, reasoning, and other powers flow; if we had it too, we would have a quite different idea of man’s essence from what is now contained in our definition of our species. In that case, our idea of any individual man would be very different from what it is now; just as that the idea of the famous clock at Strasbourg possessed by someone who knows all its springs and wheels and other contrivances differs from the idea of it possessed by a gazing peasant, who merely sees the hands move and hears the clock strike.

4. Here is evidence that essence in the ordinary sense of the word relates to sorts, and is applicable to particular things only to the extent that they are grouped into sorts. If you take away the abstract ideas by which we sort individuals and rank them under common names, then the thought of anything essential to any of them instantly vanishes. We have no notion of one (·that is, of essential property·) without the other (·that is, of a sort or species·), and that plainly shows how they are related. It is necessary for me to be as I am; God and nature have made me so. But nothing that I have is essential to me. An accident or disease may greatly alter my colour or shape; a fever or fall may take away my reason or memory, or both; an apoplexy may leave me with neither sense nor understanding—indeed, with no life. Other creatures of my shape may be made with more and better, or fewer and worse, faculties than I have; and others may have reason and sense in a shape and body very different from mine. None of these are essential to the one, or the other, or to any individual whatever, till the mind refers it

163

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

to some sort or species of things. The moment that is done, something is found to be essential according to the abstract idea of that sort. Examine your own thoughts, and you will find that as soon as you suppose or speak of ·some quality as· ‘essential’, the thought of some •species, or •the complex idea signified by some general name, comes into your mind; and it is in reference to that that the quality in question is said to be essential. Is it essential to me, or any other particular corporeal being, to have reason? No. Just as it isn’t essential to this white thing I write on to have words on it. But if the particular thing is counted as being of the sort man, and has the name ‘man’ given to it, then reason is essential to it (assuming reason to be a part of the complex idea the name ‘man’ stands for). Similarly, it is essential to this thing I write on to contain words, if I give it the name ‘treatise’ and put it into that species. Thus, ‘essential’ and ‘not essential’ relate only to our abstract ideas and the names attached to them....

5. Thus, if for some people the idea of body is bare extension or space, then ·for them· solidity is not essential to body. If others give the name ‘body’ to the idea of solidity and extension, then ·for them· solidity is essential to body. Whatever makes a part of the complex idea the name of a sort stands for is essential to the sort, and nothing else is. If we found some matter that had all the qualities of iron except that it wasn’t affected by a magnet, would anyone raise the question of whether it lacked anything essential? It would be absurd to ask whether a really existing thing lacked something essential to it! Nor would it make sense to ask whether the unusual feature of this matter created an essential or specific difference [= ‘put the stuff into a different species’] or not, for our only criterion for what is essential or specific is given by our abstract ideas. To talk of specific differences in nature, without reference to general ideas and names, is to talk unintelligibly. What is sufficient to make an essential difference in nature between any two particular things, ·considered just in themselves, and· without reference to any abstract idea looked upon as the essence and standard of a species? When all such patterns and standards are laid aside, particular things considered barely in themselves will be found to have all their qualities equally essential: in each individual, all the qualities will be essential, or—more accurately—none of them will be so. It may be reasonable to ask whether obeying the magnet is essential to iron, but it is very improper and insignificant to ask whether it is essential to the particular bit of matter that I sharpen my pen with, without considering it under the name ‘iron’ or as belonging to a certain species....

6. I have often mentioned a ‘real essence’ that is distinct in substances from those abstract ideas of them that I call their ‘nominal essence’. By this real essence I mean the real constitution of a thing, which is the foundation of all those properties that are combined in and constantly found to co-exist with the nominal essence; that particular constitution that every thing has within itself, without reference to anything else. But ‘essence’, even in this sense, relates to a sort and presupposes a species. It is that real constitution on which the properties depend, so it necessarily presupposes a sort of things, because properties belong only to species and not to individuals. [Here, and on some later occasions and perhaps on a few earlier ones, Locke uses ‘property’ in an old technical sense according to which ‘a property of iron’ means ‘a quality or attribute that has to be possessed by all specimens of iron’; it is supposed to follow from the essence of iron without actually being part of that essence. In this sense of the word, ‘a property of this’—said by someone who is pointing to a piece of iron—is meaningless.] For example, supposing

164

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

the nominal essence of gold to be a body of such and such a special colour and weight, with malleability and fusibility, the real essence is that constitution of the parts of matter on which these qualities and their union depend; and this is also the foundation of its solubility in aqua regia and other properties accompanying that complex idea. Here are essences and properties, but all on the supposition of a sort or general abstract idea. The latter is considered as immutable, but there is no individual bit of matter to which any of these qualities are attached in such a way as to be essential to it or inseparable from it. Indeed, we don’t know precisely what any real essence is; but we suppose that it is there and is the cause of the nominal essence; and that supposed link with the nominal essence is all that ties the real essence to the species.

7. Which of those essences is it by which substances are determined into sorts or species? Obviously, the nominal essence, for it alone is what the name of the species signifies. Nothing could possibly determine the sorts of things that we rank under a given general name except the idea which that name is designed as a mark for—namely, the nominal essence. Why do we say ‘This is a horse’, ‘That is a mule’, if not because the thing fits the abstract idea that the name is attached to?....

8. Here is more evidence that the species of things are nothing to us but a grouping of them under distinct names according to complex ideas in us, and not according to precise, distinct, real essences in them. We find that many of the individuals we group into one sort, call by one common name, and so accept as members of one species, are in some respects as much unlike one another as they are unlike things that are regarded as belonging to different species.... Chemists especially are often by sad experience convinced of this when, having found certain qualities in one portion of sulphur, antimony or vitriol, they have looked for it in vain in other portions.... If things were distinguished into species according to their real essences, it would be as impossible to find different properties in any •two individual substances of the same species as it is to find different properties in •two circles or •two equilateral triangles....

9. We don’t know the real essences of things, and so we can’t use real essences as the basis on which to rank and sort things and so to name them (for what sorting is for is naming). The nearest our faculties will let us get to knowing and distinguishing substances is a collection of the perceptible ideas [here = ‘qualities’] that we observe in them. And even if we collect these as carefully and precisely as we possibly can, that collection won’t be anywhere near to the true internal constitution from which those qualities flow.... There is no plant or animal, however lowly and insignificant, that doesn’t baffle the most enlarged understanding. Though our familiar dealing with things around us stops us from wondering about them, it doesn’t cure our ignorance. When we come to examine the stones we tread on or the iron we handle, we immediately find that we don’t know how they are constructed, and can give no reason for the different qualities we find in them. What is the texture of parts, the real essence, that makes lead and antimony fusible, wood and stones not? What makes lead and iron malleable, antimony and stones not? ·We haven’t the slightest idea·. And we all know how vastly less difficult and complex the constitutions of these substances are than the fine contrivances and inconceivable real essences of plants and animals. The •workmanship of the all-wise and powerful God in making the great fabric of the universe and every part of it outstrips the •capacity and comprehension of the most enquiring and intelligent man,

165

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

by more than the •best contrivance of the most ingenious man outstrips the •conceptions of the most ignorant. So it is in vain for us to claim to put things into sorts and classes, under names, on the basis of their real essences that we are so far from knowing or understanding. A blind man may as soon sort things by their colours!....

[In section 10 Locke dismisses, as heading in the wrong direction and also as unintelligible, the theory that species and genera depend on the ‘substantial forms’ of things.]

11. Consider our ideas of ·unembodied· spirits. The mind through reflection on itself gets simple ideas of perfections—that is, qualities that it is better to have than to lack—and its only notion of a spirit is one •made out of those simple ideas and •thought of as applying in higher degree to a sort of beings without matter’s coming into it. Even our most advanced notion of God comes from attributing to him in an unlimited degree the same simple ideas of the same perfections. By reflecting on ourselves we get the ideas of existence, knowledge, power, and pleasure, each of which we find it better to have than to lack, and the more we have of each the better; and by joining all these together, with infinity added to each, we get the complex idea of an eternal, omniscient, omnipotent, infinitely wise and happy Being. We are told that there are different species of angels; but we don’t know how to form distinct specific [here = ‘detailed’] ideas of them; not because •we fancy ourselves as the only kind of spirit there can be, but because •the only simple ideas we do or can have to apply to them are ones taken through reflection from ourselves. only way of thinking about other species of spirits is by attributing to them various perfections in higher or lower degree; and it seems to me that we think of God as different from them not in what simple ideas are applicable to each but only in the degree to which they are applicable—with all the perfections being thought of as possessed by God to an infinite degree, to angels with a lesser degree than that....

12. It isn’t inconceivable or impossible that there should be many species of spirits that are marked off from one another by distinct properties of which we have no ideas, just as the species of perceptible things are distinguished from one another by qualities that we know and observe in them. I think it probable that there indeed are more species of thinking creatures above us than there are of sentient and material creatures below us. Here is why. In all the visible physical world we see no chasms or gaps. All the way down from us the descent goes by easy steps, and a continued series of things that at each step differ very little from the ones just above. [The section continues with remarks about fish with wings, birds that swim, amphibians, sea-going mammals; non-human animals ‘that seem to have as much knowledge and reason as some that are called men’; the almost invisible line between the lowest animals and the highest plants, and so on. Locke continues:] When we consider God’s infinite power and wisdom, we have reason to think that it is suitable to the magnificent harmony of the universe, and the great design and infinite goodness of its architect, that the species of creatures should also by gentle degrees ascend upward from us towards his infinite perfection, as we see they gradually descend from us downwards. This would give us reason to be convinced that there are far more species of creatures above us than there are beneath, because our own level of perfection is ·less than half-way up, i.e. it is· much more remote from the infinite being of God than it is from the lowest kind of thing. And yet of all those different species we have, for the reasons I have given, no clear distinct ideas.

166

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

13. Let us return to the species of material substances. Are ice and water two distinct species of things? Most people would answer Yes, and rightly so; but an Englishman who grew up in Jamaica, had not experienced ice and did not know the word ‘ice’, might upon coming to England and finding the water in his basin had frozen overnight call it ‘hardened water’. He would not be treating ice as a new species, different from water, any more than....we think of liquid gold in the furnace as a distinct species from hard gold in the hands of a workman. This makes it clear that our different species are nothing but different complex ideas with different names attached to them. It is true that every substance that exists has its particular constitution which is the source of the perceptible qualities and the powers we observe in it; but the grouping of things into species—which is simply sorting them under different titles—is something we do on the basis of the ideas that we have of them. This is enough for us for us to pick them out verbally so that we can talk about them in their absence; but anyone who thinks we do it by their real internal constitutions, and that the verbal distinctions we make amongst species correspond to real-essence distinctions made by nature, is liable to make great mistakes, as I now show.

14. For •us to distinguish substantial beings into species according to the usual supposition that there are certain precise essences or forms of things by which •nature sorts all existing individuals into species, these ·four· things would be necessary.

15. First, we would have to be assured that when nature produces things it always designs ·or intends· them to have certain regulated established essences, which are to be the models of all things to be produced. We can’t assent to this until it is presented more clearly than it usually is.

16. Secondly, we would need to know whether nature always attains the essence that it designs in the production of things. The irregular and monstrous births that have been observed in various sorts of animals will always give us reason to doubt one or both of these—·that is, that an essence is intended, and/or that the intention is always fulfilled·.

17. Thirdly, we would need to have settled whether the creatures we call ‘monsters’—·congenitally deformed plants or animals·—are really of a separate species, according to the scholastic notion of the word ‘species’. Everything that exists has its particular constitution ·and so has a ‘real essence’ in the reasonable sense of that phrase·, but we find that some of these monstrous productions have few if any of the qualities that are supposed to result from and accompany the essence of that species to which they seem—judging by their descent—to belong.

18. Fourthly, the real essences of the things that we sort into species and give names to would need to be known—that is, we would need to have ideas of them. But since we are ignorant in these four points ·that I have raised in sections 15–18·, the supposed real essences of things won’t serve us as a basis for distinguishing substances into species.

19. There remains only one fall-back position: perhaps we could form perfect complex ideas of the properties of things that flow from their different real essences, and could distinguish them into species on that basis. [See note explaining ‘property’ in section 6.] But this can’t be done either. Because we don’t know the real essence itself, we can’t know what all the properties are that flow from it and are tied to it so tightly that if any one of them were absent we could conclude that the essence was not there and thus that the thing wasn’t of that species. To know what is the precise list of properties that depend on the real essence of gold (so that if any one of

167

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

them were lacking, the real essence of gold would be lacking, and so the stuff wouldn’t be gold), we would have to know what the real essence of gold is; and we do not. (By the word ‘gold’ here I must be understood to designate a particular piece of matter—e.g. the last guinea that was coined ·or the portion of matter circling my finger·. For if in this context I used the word in its ordinary meaning, as signifying that complex idea that we call ·the idea of· gold—that is, for the nominal essence of gold—the result would be a meaningless babble, ·because I would be discussing ‘the real essence and properties of gold’ with the word ‘gold’ understood in terms of the nominal essence of gold; and that would produce a conceptual mix-up, using one kind of essence in a discussion of the other kind. So I ask you to understand me as discussing ‘the real essence and properties of this’—and then I point to a particular piece of gold without calling it ‘gold’·. You see how hard it is to exhibit the meanings and the imperfections of words—in words!)

20. All this ·material in sections 14–19· shows clearly that we don’t distinguish substances into named species on the basis of their real essences; nor can we claim to put them exactly into species on the basis of internal essential differences.

21. Needing general words, and not knowing the real essences of things, all we can do is to make complex ideas out of collections of simple ideas that we find united together in existing things. This idea, though not the real essence of any substance that exists, is the specific essence to which the name belongs, and is interchangeable with that name. That gives us a test for the truth of ·claims about· these nominal essences. For example, some say that the essence of body is extension. If that is right, we can never go wrong through putting one for the other—the essence for the thing itself. Try substituting ‘extension’ for ‘body’: instead of saying ‘Body moves’ say ‘Extension moves’—how does that look? Someone who said ‘When one extension bumps into another extension, it makes it move’ would by his mere form of words show the absurdity of such a notion. The essence of anything (for us) is the whole complex idea marked by that name; and for substances that ‘whole’ includes not only various simple ideas but also the confused idea of substance, or of an unknown support and cause of the union ·of the qualities corresponding to the simple ideas·. Thus, the essence of body is not bare extension, but rather an extended solid thing. It is just as good to say ‘When one extended solid thing bumps into another, it makes it move’ as to say ‘When a body moves’ etc. Similarly, it is all right to say ‘A rational animal is capable of conversation’, for this doesn’t really differ from ‘A man is capable etc.’. But nobody will say ‘Rationality is capable of conversation’, because ‘rationality’ doesn’t make the whole essence to which we give the name ‘man’.

[In sections 22–3 Locke discusses problems of classification in the animal kingdom, highlighting abnormal births producing creatures that are not easy to classify. His main point is that we must approach these questions in terms of nominal essences, so that it is for us to decide how to answer them; there is no hidden fact of the matter. He mentions the possibility of classifying purely on the basis of parentage, and raises three objections to it. •It could work only for organisms; other problems about classification would remain. •It fails in the face of the offspring of copulation across species lines (‘If history doesn’t lie, women have conceived by monkeys’), and •at the end of section 23:] If the species of animals and plants are to be distinguished only by propagation, does that mean that I can’t know whether this is a tiger or that is tea unless I go to India to see the

168

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

parents of the one, and the plant from which the other was produced?

24. Looking at the whole picture, it is evident that what men make to be the essences of the various sorts of substances are •perceptible qualities that they collect, and that the vast majority of men sort substances without reference to •their real internal structures. Much less were any ‘substantial forms’ ever thought of except by those who have in this one part of the world—·western Europe·—learned the language of the schools [see explanation in iii.9.] And yet ignorant men who make no claim to insight into real essences and give no thought to substantial forms, but are content with distinguishing things by their perceptible qualities, often do better than the learned quick-sighted men who look so deeply into things and talk so confidently of something hidden and essential. They do better in that they are often better acquainted with the differences amongst substances, make finer discriminations amongst them on the basis of their uses, and know more what to expect from each,

25. Even if the real essences of substances could be discovered by thorough scientific research, we couldn’t reasonably think that the ranking of things under general names is regulated by those internal real constitutions, or by anything else but their obvious appearances. Languages in all countries were established long before sciences. So the general names that are in use amongst the various nations of men haven’t been the work of scientists or logicians or men who troubled themselves about forms and essences. Rather, each language’s more or less comprehensive terms have been created and given meanings by ignorant and illiterate people who sorted and named things on the basis of the perceptible qualities they found in them....

[In sections 26–7 Locke returns to the supposed facts about borderline cases, monstrous births, etc., drawing the same moral as before.]

28. But though these nominal essences of substances are made by the mind, they aren’t made as arbitrarily as are those of mixed modes. For the making of any nominal essence two things are necessary. First, that •the ideas of which it is composed be united in such a way as to constitute a single idea. Secondly, that •any instance of the complex idea ·making the meaning of some word· be composed of exactly the same particular ideas ·as any other idea making the meaning of that same word·, neither more nor less. ·As regards the second requirement·: If two abstract complex ideas differ in how many simple ideas they contain or in which ones, they make two different essences, not just one. Regarding the first requirement: When the mind makes its complex ideas of substances, it only follows nature and puts none together that are not supposed to be united in nature. Nobody—unless he wants to fill his head with chimeras and his conversation with unintelligible words—joins the voice of a sheep with the shape of a horse, or the colour of lead with the weight and fixedness of gold, offering these as the complex ideas of real substances. Men may make what complex ideas they please, and give them what names they will; but if they want to be understood when they speak of really existing things, they must to some extent conform their ideas to the things they want to speak of....

29. Although the mind of man, in making its complex ideas of substances, never puts any together that do not really or are not supposed to co-exist, exactly which ones it brings into the combination depends on the the individual person who is making the idea—on how careful he is, how hard he works, what his imagination is like. Men generally

169

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

content themselves with a few obvious perceptible qualities, and often if not always they omit others that are just as important and as firmly united ·to the rest· as those that they take. Of the two sorts of perceptible substances, one consists of organized bodies that are propagated by seed; and with these we take the shape as the leading quality and most characteristic part that determines the species. For vegetables and animals, therefore, all we need usually is an extended solid substance of such and such a shape. [Locke adds a side-swipe at the definition of ‘man’ as ‘rational animal’—see II.xxvii.8.] Whereas in plants and animals it is the shape that we most fix on and are mainly led by, in most other bodies (ones not propagated by seed) it is the colour. Thus where we find the colour of gold we are apt to imagine that all the other qualities contained in our complex idea are there also. It is because we commonly take shape and colour to be our rules of thumb of various species that when we see a good picture we readily say ‘This is a lion’, ‘That is a rose’, ‘This is a gold goblet and that a silver one’, going purely by the different shapes and colours presented to the eye by the paint-brush.

30. But though this serves well enough for rough and ready ways of talking and thinking, men are still far from having agreed on exactly what simple ideas or qualities belong to any sort of thing signified by a given name. That isn’t surprising, because it’s not easy to find out what the simple ideas are that are constantly and inseparably united in nature and always to be found together in the same subject. To do this one must devote time, take trouble, have skill, and be persistent. [Locke goes on to say that most men can’t provide all that, and so instead they classify things by their obvious outward appearances. The paucity of ‘settled definitions’, he says, should warn us against becoming embroiled in debates about species and genera, and invoking ‘forms’, and should make us think that ‘forms are only chimeras, which give us no light into the specific natures of things’. He continues:] It is true that many particular substances are so made by nature that they are like one another and so afford a basis for being grouped into sorts. But since our sorting of things—our making of determinate species—is done for the purpose of naming them and bringing them under general terms, I don’t see how it can properly be said that nature sets the boundaries of the species of things. Or if it does, our boundaries of species are not exactly nature’s. For we, needing general names that we can use right now, don’t wait for a perfect discovery of all the qualities that would best show us substances’ most important differences and likenesses. Rather, we ourselves divide them into species on the basis of certain obvious appearances, so that we can more easily communicate our thoughts about them under general names....

[In section 31 Locke says that if we look into the more complete ideas that people have in the background of their rough and ready ones, we shall find considerable differences; and when two people have different definitions for the same general word, there is no fact of the matter about which of the two complex ideas is more right. This helps to confirm that different essences of gold are of human artifacts ‘and not of nature’s making’.]

32. [In this section Locke writes about larger classes (genera) which can be divided up into smaller ones (species). The ‘lowest species’ are just the classes that we don’t divide up into still smaller ones.] If the simple ideas making the nominal essences of •the lowest species....depend on the how people choose to collect them together, it is even more obvious that this is so for ·the nominal essences of· •the more

170

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

comprehensive classes that the masters of logic call ‘genera’. These are complex ideas that are meant to be incomplete: you can see at a glance that some of the qualities that are to be found in the things themselves are purposely left out of generic ideas. To make •general ideas that cover several particulars, the mind leaves out the ideas of time and place and any others that would stop the resultant idea from fitting more than one individual; and similarly, to make •ideas that are even more general and can cover ·not just different individuals but· different sorts, the mind leaves out the qualities that distinguish the sorts from one another, and puts into its new collection only such ideas—·or, more accurately, ideas of only such qualities·—as are common to several sorts. The same reasons of convenience that made men bring various portions of yellow matter under one name, also led them to make a name that could cover both gold and silver and some other bodies of different sorts. This was done by leaving out the qualities that are special to each sort, and retaining in the complex idea only those that are common to them all. When the name ‘metal’ is assigned to this complex idea, there is a genus constituted; and its essence is a certain abstract idea that contains only •malleableness and •fusibility, along with •certain degrees of weight and fixedness that are shared by some bodies of various kinds, and it leaves out •the colour and •other qualities peculiar to gold or to silver or to other sorts comprehended under the name ‘metal’. This shows plainly that when men make their general ideas of substances they don’t follow exactly any patterns set for them by nature, for there is no body anywhere that has only malleableness and fusibility without other qualities that belong to it as inseparably as those two do.... So that in this whole business of genera and species •the genus is merely a partial conception of what is in •the species, and •the species is merely a partial idea of what is to be found in each •individual. So if you think that a man, and a horse, and an animal, and a plant, etc. are distinguished by real essences made by nature, you must think nature to be very free-handed with these real essences, making one for body, another for animal, and a third for horse, and generously bestowing all these essences on Bucephalus! But the real story about what is done in all these genera and species (or sorts) is that no new thing is made, but only more or less comprehensive signs by means of which we can talk, using few words, about very many particular things that fit the more or less general conceptions that we have formed for that purpose. Notice that the •more general term is always the name of a •less complex idea, and that each •genus is merely a partial conception of the •species that fall under it. So the only sense in which any of these abstract general ideas can be complete is its containing everything that is generally understood to be meant by a certain name; it can’t be complete in relation to what exists in nature.

[In sections 33–4 Locke expands his remarks about how we classify for our convenience, with examples, and a remark about the semantic richness of ‘the monosyllable man’.]

35. What I have said makes it evident that men make sorts of things. They do it by making the abstract ideas, which are the nominal essences and therefore make the species or sort. If we found a body having all the qualities of gold except malleableness, we would discuss whether it was gold or not. This could be settled only by the abstract idea to which everyone attached the name ‘gold’; so it would be gold to someone whose nominal essence for gold didn’t include malleableness, and not gold to someone whose specific idea did include malleableness. And who would be making these two different species under the name ‘gold’—who but men?....

171

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

36. This, briefly, is how things stand. Nature makes many particular things that are alike in many perceptible qualities, and probably also in their •internal structure and constitution. But it isn’t this •real essence that separates them into species; it is men who do that. On the basis of the qualities they find to be possessed in common by various individuals, men group things into sorts, so that they can talk about them conveniently. When men do this they employ comprehensive signs under which individual things come to be ranked, according to which abstract ideas they fit—like soldiers under regimental flags.

This soldier belongs to the blue regiment, that to the red one.

This is a man, that is a monkey.

In this, I think, consists the whole business of genus and species.

37. I don’t deny that nature, in its constant production of particular things, doesn’t always produce completely new kinds of things, but ·often· makes them very similar to one another. Still I think it is true that the boundaries of the species whereby men sort them are made by men....

38. One thing I am sure will seem very strange in this doctrine, namely the conclusion that each abstract idea, with a name attached to it, makes a separate species. But who can help it if truth will have it so? For so it must remain until somebody can show us that the species of things are distinguished by something else, and that general terms signify something other than our abstract ideas. I would like to know why a poodle and a hound are not of species as different as a spaniel and an elephant are. We have no more idea of the difference of essence between an elephant and a spaniel than we have of the difference of essence between a poodle and a hound, because all the essential difference that we know in each case—the difference whereby we recognize each animal and distinguish it from the other—is just the difference in what collection of simple ideas we have associated with those different names.

39. In addition to the ice/water example that I gave in section 13, here is another. A silent watch and a striking one are •one species to those who have only one name for both; but they are of •different species for someone who has the name ‘watch’ for one and ‘clock’ for the other, with a different complex idea for each. It may be said that the difference in the inner workings of these two puts them into different species; but the watch-maker has a clear idea of that difference, yet they are plainly of only one species ·even· for him if he has only one name for both. Why should inner workings suffice to make a new species? Some watches are made with four wheels, others with five: is this a specific difference to the watchmaker?.... Some have the balance loose, others have it regulated by a spiral spring and yet others by hogs’ bristles. Is this enough to make a specific difference to the watchmaker who knows these and other differences in the internal constitutions of watches? Each creates a real difference from the rest, certainly; but whether it is an essential (specific) difference or not relates only to the complex idea to which the name ‘watch’ is given. [The section continues with remarks about the choices one has in creating ever smaller species, illustrated with watch and with man.]

[In section 40 Locke remarks, partly on the basis of the preceding discussion, that ‘with the species of artificial things there is generally less confusion and uncertainty than with natural ones’. In section 41 he defends his view that there are species of artifacts as well as of ‘natural substances’ such as organisms.]

172

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

42. Of all ·the things to which we apply· our various sorts of ideas, only substances have proper names, by which one particular thing is signified. Where simple ideas, modes, and relations are concerned, it seldom happens that someone has occasion to mention this or that particular one in its absence. Also, the greatest part of mixed modes are actions, which perish in their birth; so they aren’t capable of a lasting duration in the way that substances (the actors) are....

43. Forgive me for having dwelt so long on this subject. Perhaps some of my discussion has been obscure, ·and I apologize for that too·. But think about how difficult it is to lead someone by words into thoughts about things ·considered in themselves, things· stripped of those specific differences we give them. If I don’t name the things I don’t say anything; and if I do name them I thereby classify them in some way, bringing to your mind the usual abstract idea of the species ·associated with the name I use·, which is contrary to my purpose. The proposal:

Let’s talk about a man while setting aside the ordinary meaning of the name ‘man’, which is the complex idea we usually attach to it; let’s consider man as he is in himself, and as he is really distinguished from others in his internal constitution or real essence, i.e. by something we don’t know

seems silly. But that is what must be done by someone who wants to •speak of the supposed real essences and species of things as thought to be made by nature, even if he only wants to •say that no such real essences are signified by the general names that substances are called by! Because it is difficult to do this by known familiar names, let me introduce an example through which I hope to make clearer the mind’s different handlings of specific names and ideas, and to show how the complex ideas of modes are sometimes copied from archetypes in the minds of other thinking beings (that is, to the common meanings of their accepted names), and sometimes from no archetypes at all. I plan also to show how the mind always copies its ideas of substances either from the substances themselves or from the meanings of their names....

[In sections 44–5 Locke presents a fiction in which Adam invents words meaning ‘suspicion’ and ‘disloyalty’ in advance of encountering instances of either; he sketches a possible history of the gradual entry of these words into common use.]

[In section 46 he gives a fiction about Adam being brought a piece of gold and thereupon inventing a word for it; and in 47 a possible subsequent history of that word—a history in which every newly discovered quality of the stuff is added to the complex idea that is to mark off the species. This, Locke says, would mean that the archetype for the idea is every discoverable property of the stuff; and that would condemn men’s actual idea of gold to being for ever ‘inadequate’ (see II.xxxi.13). In section 48 he adds that this procedure would also lead to people’s having different ideas of gold because their varying experiences of it lead to differences in what properties they know it to have.]

49. To avoid this, therefore, people have supposed that every species has a real essence from which its properties all flow, and they want their name of the species to stand for that. But they have no idea of that real essence; and their words ·can· signify nothing but their ideas; so all that they achieve by this attempt ·to stabilize the meaning of the species name by tying it to a real essence· is to put the name in the place of the thing having that real essence, without knowing what the real essence is. That is what men do when they speak of species of things as though they were made by nature and

173

Essay III John Locke vi: Names of substances

distinguished from one another by real essences.

50. Consider what is happening when we affirm All gold is fixed. We could mean •that fixedness is a part of the definition, part of the nominal essence the word ‘gold’ stands for; in which case our affirmation contains nothing but the meaning of the term ‘gold’. Or else we mean •that fixedness, though not part of the definition of the word ‘gold’, is a property of that substance itself: in which case we are plainly using the word ‘gold’ to stand in the place of a substance having the real made-by-nature essence of a species of things. Substituting for ‘gold’ in this way gives it a confused and uncertain meaning. So much so that, although with ‘gold’ thus understood the proposition Gold is fixed is an affirmation of something real, it is a truth that we shall never be able to apply in particular cases, and so isn’t something we can use or be certain of. However true it is that whatever has the real essence of gold is fixed, what use can we make of this when we don’t know what is and what is not ‘gold’ in this sense? If we don’t know the real essence of gold, we can’t possibly know which bits of matter have that essence or, therefore, which bits are truly gold ·in the sense of ‘gold’ now being examined·.

51. To conclude: Adam’s initial freedom to make complex ideas of mixed modes on the pattern of nothing but his own thoughts is a freedom that all men have had ever since. And his need to conform his ideas of substances to things outside him, as to archetypes made by nature, is a need that all men have had ever since. His liberty to give any new name he liked to any idea is one that we still have (especially when we are inventing a language, if we can imagine such a thing happening now), except that in a society with an already-established language the meanings of words should be altered only cautiously and sparingly. [The section concludes with a statement of the fairly obvious reason for this.]

174

Essay III John Locke vii: Particles

Chapter vii: Particles

1. Besides •words that name ideas in the mind, there are many others that we use •to signify how the mind connects ideas or propositions with one another. To communicate its thoughts to others, the mind needs not only •signs of the ideas it then has before it, but also •signs to show what in particular it is doing at that moment with those ideas. It does this in several ways. For example, ‘is’ and ‘is not’ are the general marks of the mind’s affirming or denying; and without these there would be in words no truth or falsehood. The mind also has ways of showing not only how it is connecting the parts of propositions to one another, but also how it is connecting whole sentences one to another, giving them various relations and dependencies so as to make a coherent discourse.

2. The words the mind uses to signify how it is connecting the various affirmations and negations that it is bringing together into a single continued reasoning or narration are generally called particles. The proper use of particles is the chief contributor to the clearness and beauty of a good style. To think well, it isn’t enough that a man has ideas that are clear and distinct, nor that he observes the agreement or disagreement of some of them. He must also think in sequence, and observe the dependence of his thoughts and reasonings upon one another. And to express such methodical and rational thoughts well, he needs words to show what connection, restriction, distinction, opposition, emphasis, etc. he gives to each part of his discourse. If he gets any of these wrong he will puzzle his hearers instead of informing them. So these words that aren’t the names of ideas are of constant and indispensable use in language, contributing greatly to men’s expressing themselves well.

3. This part of grammar has, I suggest, been as much neglected as some others have been over-diligently cultivated. It is easy for men to work their way systematically through cases and genders, moods and tenses, gerunds and supines. With these and their like the grammarians have been diligent; and even particles have in some languages been set out and classified with a great show of exactness. But although ‘preposition’ and ‘conjunction’ etc. are names well known in grammar, and the particles contained under them carefully sorted into their distinct subdivisions, someone who wants to show the right use of particles, and what significancy [Locke’s word] and force they have, ·must look elsewhere than in grammar books. He· must take a little more pains, scrutinize his own thoughts, and observe in accurate detail the various postures of his mind when he talks.

4. Dictionaries usually explain these words through words of another language that come nearest to their meaning; but that isn’t good enough, for what they mean is commonly as hard to grasp in the second language as in the first. They are all marks of something the mind is doing or indicating; so we need to attend diligently to the various views, postures, stands, turns, limitations, exceptions, and various other thoughts of the mind, for which we have no names—or no good ones. There is a great variety of these, far more than most languages have corresponding particles for; so it is no wonder that most particles have several meanings, sometimes almost opposite ones. In the Hebrew language there is a particle consisting of one single letter, which is said to have—was it seventy? anyway, certainly more than fifty different meanings.

175

Essay III John Locke Chapter viii: Abstract and concrete terms

5. ‘But’ is a particle, none more familiar in our language; and someone who calls it a ‘discretive conjunction’ and says that it corresponds to sed in Latin or to mais in French thinks he has sufficiently explained it. But it seems to me to indicate certain relations that the mind gives to various propositions or parts of them that it joins by this monosyllable. First, ‘BUT to say no more’; here the word indicates that the mind has stopped in its course, before reaching the ·intended· end of it. Secondly, ‘I saw BUT two planets’: here it shows that the mind limits the sense to what is expressed, with a negation of everything else. ·The next two examples are intended as two halves of a single sentence·. Thirdly, ‘You pray; BUT it is not that God would bring you to the true religion...’: this indicates a supposition in the mind of something’s not being as it should be. Fourthly, ‘... BUT that he would confirm you in your own’: this shows that the mind makes a direct opposition between that and what goes before it. Fifthly, ‘All animals have sense; BUT a dog is an animal’: here the word signifies little more than that the latter proposition is joined to the former as the minor ·premise· of a syllogism. [For example: ‘All men are mortal, But Socrates is a man, So Socrates is mortal’. This use of ‘But’ was fairly standard well into the 20th century, but seems now to have expired.]

6. No doubt this particle has many other significations as well,....but it isn’t my business to examine the word in all its uses, let alone to give a full explication of particles in general. What I have said about this word may lead us to reflect on the use and force of particles in language, and to think about the various actions of our minds when we are speaking—actions that we indicate to others by these particles. Some particles in some constructions, and others always, contain within them the sense of a whole sentence.

Chapter viii: Abstract and concrete terms

1. If the ordinary words of language, and our common use of them, had been attentively considered, they would have thrown light on the nature of our ideas. The mind has a power to abstract its ideas, and so they become essences, general essences, by which sorts of things are distinguished. Each abstract idea is distinct, so one such idea can never be another, so the mind will by its intuitive knowledge see the difference between any two ideas; and therefore no one whole idea can ever be affirmed of another. We see this in the common use of language, which doesn’t permit any abstract word, or name of an abstract idea, to be affirmed of another such. However certain it is that man is an animal, or is rational....everyone at first hearing sees the falsehood of ‘Humanity is animality’ and ‘Humanity is rationality’. All our ·legitimate· affirmations are concrete ones, which don’t affirm that one abstract idea is another, but join one abstract idea to another.... Where substances are concerned, the attributed abstract idea is most often the idea of a power; for example, ‘A man is white’ signifies that the thing that has the essence of a man has also in it the essence of whiteness,

176

Essay III John Locke Chapter ix: The imperfection of words

which is nothing but power to produce the idea of whiteness in the eyes of sighted people....

2. This difference among words points to a difference among our ideas. We find upon enquiry that our simple ideas all have abstract names as well as concrete ones: the former are substantives, ·i.e. nouns·, the latter adjectives; as ‘whiteness’ and ‘white’, ‘sweetness’ and ‘sweet’. The same holds for ideas of modes and relations—‘justice’ and ‘just’, ‘equality’ and ‘equal’.... For our ideas of substances we have very few if any abstract names. For though the schools have introduced ‘animality’, ‘humanness’, ‘corporeity’ [Locke gives these in Latin] and some others, they are infinitely outnumbered by the substance-names that the schoolmen didn’t make fools of themselves by trying to match with abstract ones. Those few that the schools constructed and put into the mouths of their scholars could never come into common use or win general approval. That looks to me like a tacit confession by all mankind that they have no ideas of the real essences of substances, since they have no names for any such ideas. They would have had such names if their awareness of their ignorance of them—·that is, of real essences of substances·—not kept them from trying anything so futile. And, therefore, although they had enough ideas to distinguish gold from a stone, and metal from wood, they approached in a gingerly fashion such terms as ‘goldenness’, ‘stonehood’, ‘metalicity’, and ‘woodness’ [Locke gives these in Latin]—names that would purport to signify the real essences of those substances, of which they knew they had no ideas.....

Chapter ix: The imperfection of words

1. From the preceding chapters it is easy to see what there is in language, and how the very nature of words makes it almost inevitable that many of them should be doubtful and uncertain in their meanings. To examine how words can be perfect or imperfect, we should first consider what our goals are in using them; for their fitness to achieve those goals is a measure of how perfect or imperfect they are. In earlier parts of this work I have often mentioned in passing a double use of words: we use them •for recording our own thoughts, and •for communicating our thoughts to others.

2. In the first of these, the recording our own thoughts as an aid to our memories, we are (so to speak) talking to; and for this purpose, any words will do. Sounds are voluntary and arbitrary signs of ideas, and a man can use any words he likes to signify his own ideas to himself. There will be no imperfection in them, if he constantly uses the same sign for the same idea, for in that case he can’t fail to have his meaning understood, which is the right use and perfection of language.

3. Secondly, as to communication by words, that too has a double use: •Civil. •Philosophical. By their ‘civil use’ I mean the use of words to communicate thoughts and ideas in a manner that serves for upholding ordinary conversation and commerce about the everyday affairs and conveniences of

177

Essay III John Locke Chapter ix: The imperfection of words

civil life. By the ‘philosophical’ use of words I mean the kind of use of them that can serve to convey precise notions of things, and to express in general propositions certain and undoubted truths that the mind may be satisfied with in its search for true knowledge. [In Locke’s time the meaning of ‘philosophical’ extended to ‘scientific’.] These two uses of language are very different, and one needs much less exactness than the other, as we shall see.

4. The chief end of language in communication is to be understood, and words don’t serve well for that end—whether in everyday or in philosophical discourse—when some word fails to arouse in the hearer the idea it stands for in the mind of the speaker. Sounds have no natural connection with our ideas; they get their meanings from the arbitrary decisions of men; so when they are doubtful and uncertain in their meaning (which is the imperfection I am are speaking of), the cause of this lies in the •ideas they stand for rather than in any •word’s being an inferior sign for a given idea—for in that respect they are all equally perfect. So, what makes some words more doubtful and uncertain in their meanings is the difference in the ideas they stand for.

5. The idea that each word stands for must be learned and remembered by those who want to exchange thoughts and have meaningful conversations with others in the language in question. ·There are four kinds of situation where· this is especially hard to achieve:

•where the idea a word stands for is very complex, and made up of many constituent ideas put together (·discussed in section 6·),

•where the ·constituent parts of the· idea the word stands for have no certain connection in nature, and so no settled standard anywhere in nature by which to correct the idea (·sections 7–10·),

•where the meaning of the word relates to a standard that isn’t easy to know (·sections 11–12·), and

•where the meaning of the word and the real essence of the thing are not exactly the same.

(These are difficulties that affect the meanings of various words that are nevertheless intelligible. I needn’t discuss ones that aren’t intelligible at all, such as a name for a simple idea that the hearer can’t acquire because of a lack in his sense-organs or his faculties....) In all these cases we shall find an imperfection in words in their particular application to our different sorts of ideas. When I get into the details, we shall find that the names of mixed modes are most liable to doubtfulness and imperfection for the first two of these ·four listed· reasons, and when the names of substances are defective it is usually for the third and fourth reasons.

6. Many names of mixed modes are liable to great uncertainty and obscurity in their meanings ·for either of two reasons·. One is that many complex ideas are extremely complex. For words to be serviceable in communication, they must arouse in the hearer exactly the same idea they stand for in the speaker’s mind. Without this, men fill one another’s heads with noise and sounds but don’t convey their thoughts or lay their ideas before one another. But when a word stands for a very complex idea whose constituent simpler ideas are themselves complex, it isn’t easy for men to form and retain that idea exactly enough for the name in common use to stand for exactly the same precise idea. That is why men’s names of very complex ideas, such as most of the moral words, seldom have exactly the same meaning for two different men. [See note on ‘moral’ at the end of v.12.] Not only does one man’s complex idea seldom agree with another’s, but it also often differs from the idea that he himself had yesterday or the one he’ll have tomorrow.

178

Essay III John Locke Chapter ix: The imperfection of words

7. Most names of mixed modes lack standards in nature in terms of which men could correct and adjust their meanings; and that makes them very various and doubtful. They are collections of ideas that the mind has put together to suit its own notions and in the furtherance of its own conversational purposes, not intending to copy anything that really exists but merely to name and sort things according to whether they agree with the archetypes or forms it has made.... Names that stand for collections of ideas that the mind makes at pleasure are bound to have doubtful meanings when such collections are nowhere to be found constantly united in nature.... What the word ‘murder’....signifies can never be known from things themselves. Many parts of the complex idea of murder are not visible in the murderous action itself: the intention of the mind, which is a part of ·the idea of· murder, has no necessary connection with the outward and visible action of the murderer; and the pulling of the trigger through which the murder is committed—possibly the only visible feature of the action—has no natural connection with those other ideas that make up the meaning of the word ‘murder’. All those ideas are united and combined only by the understanding, which unites them under one name; but when this is done without any rule or pattern it is inevitable that the meaning of the name should be different in the minds of different men.

8. It is true that common use—the ‘rule of propriety’—is of some help in settling the meanings in a language. It does this pretty well for ordinary conversation; but in the absence of any authority to establish the precise meanings of words, common use doesn’t suffice to fit them for philosophical discourses; because almost every name of any very complex idea has a great latitude in common use, and can be made the sign of widely different ideas without going beyond the bounds of propriety. Also, the rule of propriety itself is indeterminate: it is often matter of dispute whether this or that way of using a word conforms to propriety of speech. So the names of such very complex ideas are naturally liable to the imperfection of lacking securely known and stable meanaings, and don’t always stand for the same idea in ·the minds of· speaker and hearer, even when they want to understand one another....

9. Doubtfulness over the meanings of the names of mixed modes comes partly from how they are ordinarily learned. How do children learn languages? To make them understand what the names of simple ideas, or of substances, stand for, people ordinarily show children the thing of which they want them to have the idea; and then repeat the name that stands for it—‘white’, ‘sweet’, ‘milk’, ‘sugar’, ‘cat’, ‘dog’. But as for mixed modes, especially the most important of them, moral words, the sounds are usually learned first; and then to know what complex ideas they stand for the child must look to explanations by adults or (more commonly) is left to find out for himself through his own observation and hard work. And since not much observation or hard work is expended on the search for the true and precise meanings of names, these moral words are in most men’s mouths little more than bare sounds; and when they have any meaning it is for the most part very loose and undetermined, and thus obscure and confused. [The remainder of the section is a lively complaint about the consequences of this situation in academic debates, especially on theological and legal topics. It concludes:] In the interpretation of laws, whether divine or human, there is no end. Comments beget comments, and explanations provide fodder for yet further explanations.... Many a man who was pretty well satisfied about the meaning of a text of scripture....at a first reading has quite lost the

179

Essay III John Locke Chapter ix: The imperfection of words

sense of it through consulting commentators! ldots. I don’t say this with the thought that commentaries are needless, but only to show how uncertain the names of mixed modes naturally are, even in the mouths of those who had both the intention and the ability to speak as clearly as language would let them.

[Section 10 points out that Locke’s view is confirmed by the amount of trouble we take trying to understand what great writers of the past meant by their writings. This holds especially for ones dealing with ‘truths we are required to believe, or laws we are ·required· to obey’. Where less is at stake, we are less concerned with exact meanings.]

11. Whereas the meanings of the names of mixed modes are uncertain because there are no real standards existing in nature by which to adjust those ideas, the names of substances have doubtful meanings for a contrary reason—namely because the ideas they stand for are supposed to conform to the reality of things, and are referred to standards made by nature. In our ideas of substances we are not free as we are with mixed modes simply to choose what combinations we want as criteria to rank and name things by. If we want our names to be signs of substances and to stand for them, we must follow nature, suit our complex ideas to real existences, and regulate the meanings of their names with guidance from the things themselves. Here we do have patterns to follow, but they are patterns that make the meanings of the names very uncertain, because the patterns either can’t be known at all, or can be known only imperfectly and uncertainly.

12. The names of substances have a double reference in their ordinary use. First, sometimes they are made to stand for things’ real constitutions—the constitutions that are the centre and source of all the things’ properties. And so the complex ideas that are the meanings of substance-names are supposed to fit with these real constitutions, or ‘essences’ as they are apt to be called. But they are utterly unknown to us, so any sound that is meant to stand for one of them must be very uncertain in its application. It will be impossible to know what things are properly called ‘horse’ or ‘antimony’ when those words are put for real essences of which we have no ideas at all. Thus, when the names of substances are taken in this way, and referred to standards that can’t be known, their meanings can never be corrected and established by those standards.

13. Secondly, what the names of substances immediately signify are the simple ideas ·of qualities· that are found to co-exist in the substances; so these, united as they are in the substance in question, are the proper standards by which to test and adjust the meanings of substance-names. But these patterns don’t serve the purpose well enough to protect the names from a variety of uncertain meanings. The simple ideas that are united in a single substance are very numerous, and all have an equal right to enter into the complex idea that the specific name is to stand for; so people who want to talk about the same thing nevertheless form very different ideas about it; and so their name for it unavoidably comes to mean different things for different men. [In the remainder of this section Locke explains why so many simple ideas are eligible for inclusion in the meaning of a given substance name. Most of them concern powers to interact thus and so with other things; the number of such powers (for a given kind of substance) multiplied by the number of kinds of ‘other thing’ yields a formidable product; Locke calls it ‘almost infinite’. And when men freely choose to make certain selections from this multitude, Locke remarks, it is inevitable that their complex ideas of substances will be very

180

Essay III John Locke Chapter ix: The imperfection of words

various, and thus that the meanings of substance-names will be very uncertain.]

[Section 14 continues with the topic of the numerousness and variety of the eligible simple ideas.]

[In section 15 Locke concedes that most of our names for substances are determinate and uniform enough for everyday purposes, but ‘in philosophical enquiries and debates, where general truths are to be established and consequences drawn from positions laid down’, he insists, they are not.]

16. This is a natural and almost unavoidable imperfection in almost all names of substances, as soon as we move from confused or loose notions to stricter and more precise enquiries.... I was once in a meeting of very learned and able medical men when the question arose as to whether any liquor [= ‘fluid’] passes through the filaments of the nerves. After the debate had gone on for a good while, with a variety of arguments on each side, I suggested that before carrying on with this dispute they should first make sure that they all meant the same thing by ‘liquor’, and what they meant by it. (I had for some time suspected that most disputes are about the meanings of words more than they are about a real difference in the conception of things.) At first they were a little surprised at my proposal; everyone who was there thought he understood perfectly what the word ‘liquor’ stands for; and it is a tribute to their qualities of intellect that they didn’t treat the proposal as a very frivolous or extravagant one. They agreed to go along with my suggestion, and that led them to discover that the meaning of that word wasn’t as settled and certain as they had all imagined, and that each of them had made it a sign of a different complex idea. This showed them that the core of their dispute concerned the meaning of that term, and that they didn’t differ much in their opinions about some fluid and very finely divided matter passing through the channels of the nerves. It wasn’t so easy to agree on whether it was to be called ‘liquor’ or not, but they came to think that this wasn’t worth wrangling over.

[In section 17 Locke discusses gold, the number and variety of its qualities and powers, and the resulting potential for uncertainty and interpersonal difference in the meaning of ‘gold’.]

18. From what I have said it is easy to see that the names of simple ideas are the least liable to mistakes, for the following ·two· reasons. First: the ideas they stand for, each being just one single perception, are easier to acquire and to retain clearly than are the more complex ones. Second: they are never associated with any essence except the perception that they immediately signify, whereas the names of substances run into trouble through being associated with something else. Men who don’t use their words perversely or deliberately start quarrels seldom make mistakes involving the use and meaning of the names of simple ideas. ‘White’ and ‘sweet’, ‘yellow’ and ‘bitter’, carry a very obvious meaning with them, which everyone precisely comprehends or easily sees that he is ignorant of. But what precise collection of simple ideas ‘modesty’ or ‘frugality’ stand for in someone else’s use isn’t so certainly known. And however apt we are to think we know well enough what is meant by ‘gold’ or ‘iron’, the precise complex idea that others make them the signs of isn’t so certain; and I think it seldom happens that a speaker makes them stand for exactly the same collections as the hearer does....

19. The names of simple modes are second only to those of simple ideas in their freedom from doubt and uncertainty (and for the same reasons). This is especially true of names of shapes and numbers. Who ever mistook the ordinary

181

Essay III John Locke Chapter ix: The imperfection of words

meaning of ‘seven’ or of ‘triangle’? In general the least complex ideas in every kind have the least dubious names.

20. So •mixed modes that are composed of only a few obvious simple ideas usually have names whose meanings are not very uncertain. But the names of •mixed modes that include a great number of simple ideas are commonly of a very doubtful and undetermined meaning, as I have shown. The names of substances....are liable yet to greater imperfection and uncertainty, especially when we come to a philosophical use of them.

21. Given that the great disorder in our names of substances comes mostly from our lack of knowledge, and from our inability to penetrate into their real constitutions, you may be wondering why I call this an imperfection in our words rather than in our understandings. This question seems so reasonable that I think I must explain why I have followed this method. When I first began this treatise on the understanding, and for a good while after, it didn’t occur to me that it needed to include any consideration of words. But after I had dealt with the origin and content of our ideas, I began to examine the extent and certainty of our knowledge; and then I found that knowledge is so closely connected with words that very little could be said clearly and relevantly about it unless attention were first paid to the power of words and to how they have meaning. Knowledge has constantly to do with propositions; and though it is ultimately about things, it gets to things so much by the intervention of words that they seemed hardly separable from our general knowledge. At least words interpose themselves so much between our understanding and the truth that it’s trying to think about and grasp that their obscurity and disorder often cast a mist before our eyes (like fogged glass), and intrude on our understandings. In the fallacies that men inflict on themselves and others, and in the mistakes in their disputes and in their thinking, much of the trouble comes from the uncertain or wrong meanings of words. So much so, indeed, that we have reason to think that defects in words are a large obstacle to getting knowledge. It is especially important that we should be carefully warned about this ·confusion of language· because some people, so far from seeing it as a drawback, have studied the arts of increasing it, giving them the reputation of learning and subtlety, as we shall see in the next chapter. I’m inclined to think that if the imperfections of language, as the instrument of knowledge, were more thoroughly weighed, a great many of the controversies that make such a noise in the world would cease, and there would be a more open road than we now have to knowledge, and perhaps to peace also.

[In section 22 Locke says that the dependence of meaning on ‘the thoughts, notions, and ideas’ of the speaker implies that men must have trouble understanding speakers of their own language; and that the trouble is magnified when one tries to understand texts written far away and long ago in a foreign language. Therefore ‘it would become us to be charitable to one another in our interpretations or misunderstanding of those ancient writings’.]

23. The volumes of interpreters and commentators on the Old and New Testaments are manifest proofs of this. Even if everything said in the text is infallibly true, the reader can’t help being very fallible in his understanding of it. We shouldn’t be surprised that the will of God, when clothed in words, should be liable to the doubt and uncertainty that inevitably goes with verbal communication; bear in mind that even his Son, while clothed in flesh, was subject to all the weaknesses and drawbacks of human nature, except for sin. We ought to magnify God’s goodness in spreading

182

Essay III John Locke Chapter x: The misuse of words

before all the world such legible testimony of his works and his providence, and giving all mankind a light of reason that is bright enough so that anyone who seeks the truth, even if he didn’t have help from written word, couldn’t avoid concluding that there is a God and that he owes obedience to him. So •the precepts of natural religion are plain and very intelligible to all mankind, and seldom disputed; and •other revealed truths, conveyed to us by books and languages, are liable to the common and natural obscurities and difficulties that words bring with them. I think, then, that we would do well to be more careful and diligent in observing •the former, and less dogmatic, confident, and bullying in imposing our own sense and interpretations of •the latter.

Chapter x: The misuse of words

[The word ‘misuse’ replaces Locke’s ‘abuse’. The latter word was not as intensely judgmental then as it is today, so that Locke could use it often without sounding shrill, as ‘abuse’ does to our ears.]

1. In addition to language’s natural imperfection, and the obscurity and confusion that it is so hard to avoid in the use of words, there are several wilful faults and failures that men are guilty of, making words less clear and distinct in their meanings than they need to be. ·I shall deal with one of these in sections 2–4, a second in 5, a third in 6–13, a fourth in 14–16, a fifth in 17–21, a sixth in 22·.

2. The first and most palpable misuse is using words without clear and distinct ideas, or—even worse—using signs without anything being signified. This occurs in two ways.[The section continues with the first of the two, namely the founders of sects and systems who coin new words without giving them respectable meanings. If you want examples, Locke concludes:] you will get plenty of them from the schoolmen and metaphysicians, in which I include the disputing scientists and philosophers of recent times.

[In sections 3–4 Locke rails against those who take words that do have respectable common meanings and ‘by an unpardonable negligence’ use them ‘without any distinct meaning at all’. In everyday life and speech men do what is needed to make themselves understood; but in academic debates there is no pressure to be intelligible to others. On the contrary, talking without clear meaning is a device for protecting oneself against being revealed to be wrong. Locke concludes:] When a person has no settled notions, drawing him out of his mistakes is like expelling a homeless person from his home!

5. Secondly, another great misuse of words is inconstancy in the use of them. It is hard to find a discourse on any subject, especially a controversial one, in which the same words—often ones that are crucial to the argument—are not used sometimes for one collection of simple ideas and sometimes for another. [The section continues with an explanation of why this is ‘plain cheat and abuse’, and of what makes it so serious. Locke asks whether we would

183

Essay III John Locke Chapter x: The misuse of words

like to do business with someone who uses ‘8’ sometimes for eight and sometimes for seven. He continues:] In arguments and learned disputes the same sort of proceeding is often mistaken for wit and learning. I see it as a greater dishonesty than the misplacing of counters in calculating a debt; and the cheat is greater by the amount that truth is worth more than money.

6. Thirdly, another misuse of language is intentional obscurity—either giving old words new and unusual meanings without explaining them, or introducing new and ambiguous terms without defining them, or combining words in such a way as to defeat their ordinary meanings. The Aristotelian philosophy has been most conspicuous in doing this, but other sects haven’t been wholly clear of it. [In the rest of this section Locke continues the attack on people who shelter under the obscurity of their words, mentioning in passing the view that ‘body’ and ‘extension’ are synonymous, which he says is easily refuted by attention to the ordinary meanings of those words. See II.xiii.11.]

[Sections 7–8 continue the angry attack on those who make careers and reputations out of wilful obscurity.]

9.....The best way to defend strange and absurd doctrines is to guard them with legions of obscure, doubtful, and undefined words. Yet that makes these retreats more like dens of robbers or holes of foxes than like fortresses manned by sturdy warriors; and what makes it hard to get them—·the absurd doctrines·—out of their retreat isn’t their strength but rather the dark tangle of briars and thorns they are surrounded with. Because untruth is unacceptable to the mind of man, the only defence left for absurdity is obscurity.

[In sections 10–11 Locke speaks of ‘this learned ignorance’, and condemns the practice of those who advance their own causes, and sometimes win respect and admiration, by displays of idle subtlety through which they ‘render language less useful than its real defects would have made it’—an achievement of which illiterate people are not capable.]

12. This mischief hasn’t been confined to logical niceties, or mind-teasing empty speculations. Rather, it has •invaded the important affairs of human life and society, •obscured and tangled the significant truths of law and divinity, •brought confusion, disorder, and uncertainty into the affairs of mankind, and •harmed the two great guides, religion and justice—if not destroying them then at least making them mainly useless. Most of the commentaries and disputes concerning the laws of God and man have served only to make the meaning more doubtful, and to tangle the sense. All those intricate distinctions and fine points have merely brought obscurity and uncertainty, leaving the words more unintelligible and the reader more at a loss! That is why rulers are easily understood when giving ordinary spoken or written commands to their servants, but are not easily understood when they speak to their subjects in their laws....

13.....Mankind’s business is to know things as they are, and to do what they ought, and not to spend their lives in talking about things or tossing words to and fro. So wouldn’t it be good for us if the use of words were made plain and direct, and if our language—which we were given for the improvement of knowledge and as a bond of society—were not employed to •darken truth and •unsettle people’s rights, to •raise mists and •make both morality and religion unintelligible? Or if •these things do go on happening, wouldn’t it be good if they stopped being thought of as signs of learning or knowledge? ·That completes my discussion of the third of the misuses of words that I listed in section 1·.

184

Essay III John Locke Chapter x: The misuse of words

14. Fourthly, another great misuse of words is taking them for things. Although this in some degree concerns names of all kinds, it particularly affects names of substances. [As this section progresses, we find that by ‘taking words for things’ Locke means ‘uncritically assuming that certain noun phrases in which one has been indoctrinated stand for real things’. For example, someone brought up in the Aristotelian philosophy never doubts that phrases like ‘substantial form’, ‘vegetative soul’ and ‘abhorrence of a vacuum’ each stand for something real. Locke also gives examples from the vocabularies of Platonists and Epicureans.]

15. Attentive reading of philosophical writers gives one plenty of examples of how the understanding is led astray by taking names for things. I shall present just one familiar example. There have been many intricate dispositionutes about ‘matter’, as if there were some such thing really in nature, distinct from body; as it is evident that the idea for which the word ‘matter’ stands is different from that for which ‘body’ stands. If those two ideas were the same, the words would be interchangeable in all contexts, which they are not: it is all right to say ‘There is one matter of all bodies’ but not to say ‘There is one body of all matters’; we can say that one body is bigger than another, but it would sound wrong to say that one matter is bigger than another (and I don’t think anyone ever does say this). What makes the difference? Well, although matter and body aren’t really distinct—·that is, aren’t distinct things·—and so wherever there is one there is the other, yet the words ‘matter’ and ‘body’ stand for two different conceptions, one of them being incomplete, and a part of the other. For ‘body’ stands for a •solid extended shaped substance, of which ‘matter’ is a partial and more confused conception, apparently standing for the •substance and solidity of body, without taking in its •extension and shape. That is why we always speak of matter as one, because it contains nothing but the idea of a solid substance that is everywhere the same, everywhere uniform. So we don’t think or speak of different matters in the world, any more than we do of different solidities; whereas we do think and speak of different bodies, because extension and shape are capable of variation. But solidity can’t exist without extension and shape, ·so wherever there is matter there is body, as well as vice versa·. So when some philosophers took ‘matter’ to be the name of something really existing in that abstract form—·possessing only the qualities mentioned in the definition of ‘matter’·—they set off the obscure and unintelligible discussions and disputes that have filled the heads and books of philosophers concerning ‘materia prima’—first matter, conceived in Aristotelian philosophy as undifferentiated matter, lacking qualities that would differentiate parts of it from one another. I leave it to you to think about how many other examples of this trouble there have been. But I will say this: We would have many fewer disputes if words were taken for what they are, the signs of our ideas only, and not for things themselves. For when we argue about ‘matter’ or the like, we are really arguing only about the idea we express by that word, without regard for whether that precise idea agrees to anything really existing in nature....

[In section 16 Locke expresses pessimism about curing anyone of such a verbal fault if he has lived with it for many years. This, he says, is a major reason why it is so hard to get men to give up their errors, ‘even in purely philosophical opinions, and ones where their only concern is with truth’.]

17. Fifthly, another misuse of words is to set them in the place of things that they don’t and can’t signify. ·My only examples of this are attempts to use words to signify the

185

Essay III John Locke Chapter x: The misuse of words

real essences of substances; I shall discuss this through five sections·. When we affirm or deny a proposition about some sort of substance, knowing only its nominal essence, we usually tacitly try to, or intend to, name the real essence of that sort of substance. When a man says Gold is malleable, he means and wants to get across more than merely

What I call ‘gold’ is malleable,

though truly that is all the sentence amounts to. Rather, he wants it to be understood that

Gold, i.e. what has the real essence of gold, is

which amounts to saying that malleableness depends on and is inseparable from the real essence of gold. But since he doesn’t know what that real essence consists in, what he connects malleableness with in his mind is really not that unknown essence but only the sound ‘gold’ that he puts in place of it. [The section then discusses futile debates about the proper definition of ‘man’, which have to be understood—Locke says—as concerning what qualities are inevitable consequences of the real essence of man.]

18. It is true that the names of substances would be much more useful, and propositions made with them would be much more certain, if the ideas in our minds that they signified were the real essences of the substances. It is because of our lack of ·knowledge of· those real essences that our words convey so little knowledge or certainty when we talk about substances. So the mind is just trying to remove that imperfection as far as it can when it makes it a substance-name secretly stand for a thing having that real essence, as if that would somehow bring it nearer to the real essence.... Actually, far from •lessening our words’ imperfection, this procedure •increases it; for it is a plain misuse to make a word stand for something that it can’t be a sign of because our complex idea doesn’t contain it.

19. This lets us explain why with mixed modes any change in the simple ideas entering into the complex one results in a new species, as can plainly be seen with ‘manslaughter’, ‘murder’, ‘parricide’. The reason is that the complex idea signified by such a name is the real as well as nominal essence; and there is no secret reference of that name to any essence other than that. But with substances it is not so. It may happen that one man includes in his complex idea of what he calls ‘gold’ something that another omits, and vice versa; but they don’t usually think they are talking about different species. That is because they secretly mentally assume that the word ‘gold’ is tied to a real unchanging essence of an existing thing, on which depend the properties included in the complex idea(s). When someone adds to his complex idea of gold the ideas of fixedness and solubility in aqua regia, which he had previously left out, he isn’t thought to have changed the species he is talking about. Rather, he is thought only to have acquired a more complete idea by adding another simple idea that is always in fact joined with the others of which his former complex idea consisted. But relating the name to a thing of which we have no idea, far from helping us, merely serves to increase our difficulties. When the word ‘gold’ is used to stand merely for a more or less complete collection of simple ideas, it designates that sort of body well enough for everyday purposes; but when it is tacitly related to the real essence of that species, the word comes to have no meaning at all, because it is put for something of which we have no idea, so that it can’t signify anything in the absence of the actual gold. You may think that there is no difference here; but if you think about it carefully you will see that •arguing about gold in name—·that is, arguing about it in the abstract, without actually having any on hand·—is quite different from •arguing about an actual portion of the stuff, e.g. a piece of gold laid before us.

186

Essay III John Locke Chapter x: The misuse of words

20. Men are encouraged to ·try to· use names of species of substances to designate the real essences of the species by their supposition that nature works regularly in the production of things, and sets the boundaries to each species by giving exactly the same real internal constitution to each individual that we rank under one general name. ·See vi.14–18·. Yet anyone who observes their different qualities can hardly doubt that many of the individuals called by the same name differ in their internal constitutions as much as ones that are ranked under different specific names. But the supposition that exactly the same internal constitution always goes with the same specific name encourages men to take those names to represent those real essences, though really they signify only the complex idea in the speaker’s mind.... This is bound to cause a great deal of uncertainty in men’s discourses, especially of those who have thoroughly absorbed the doctrine of substantial forms, by which, they are sure, the species of things are fixed and distinguished.

[In section 21 Locke says that the ‘preposterous’ belief that we are referring to real essences is visibly at work when men ask such questions as whether a certain monkey or ‘monstrous foetus’ is a man or not. If they knew that they can only use ‘man’ to name their complex idea of man, they would see that there is nothing to wonder or argue about. He continues:] In this wrong way of using the names of substances, two false suppositions are contained. First, that nature makes all particular things according to certain precise essences, by which they are distinguished into species. Of course everything has a real constitution that makes it what it is, and on which its sensible qualities depend; but I think I have proved that this doesn’t underlie our sorting, distinguishing, and naming of the species. Secondly, this ·mistake· also tacitly insinuates that we have ideas of these proposed essences. What would the point be of enquiring whether this or that thing has the real essence of the species man if we didn’t suppose that such a specific essence was known to us? which yet is utterly false....

[In section 22 Locke presents his sixth misuse of words, which he says is ‘more general, though perhaps less observed’ than the others. It consists in assuming too confidently that others mean the same by a given word as one does oneself, a misuse of which both speakers and hearers are often guilty. He cites the word ‘life’ as one that turns out to be far from having exactly the same meaning in the minds of all English-speakers, though most people would feel almost insulted if they were asked to explain what they mean by ‘life’. It is important to ask such questions, Locke says, because:] This misuse of taking words on trust has nowhere spread so far nor with such ill effects as amongst men of letters. Why have there been so many, and such obstinate, disputes laying waste the intellectual world? The main cause has been the poor use of words. For though it is generally believed that there is great diversity of opinions in the books and debates the world is distracted with, it seems to me that the learned men on the opposite sides of controversies are merely speaking different languages. I suspect that if they got away from words and attended to things, and became clear about what they think, it would turn out that they all think the same—though they might differ in what they want.

23. To conclude this consideration of the imperfection and misuse of language: the ends of language in our discourse with others are chiefly 1 to make one man’s thoughts or ideas known to another, 2 to do that as easily and quickly as possible, and 3 thereby to convey knowledge of things. Language is either misused or deficient when it fails in any of these three purposes.

187

Essay III John Locke Chapter x: The misuse of words

23a. [This is really just a part of 23. The reason for marking it off seapraately willl appear shortly.] Words fail in the first purpose, and don’t bring one man’s ideas into the view of others, (1) when men have words in their mouths with no corresponding determinate ideas in their minds; (2) when they apply established words of a language to ideas to which common usage in that language doesn’t apply them, and (3) when they apply words very unsteadily, making them stand first for one idea and then for another.

24. Secondly, men fail to convey their thoughts as quickly and easily as they could, when they have complex ideas without having any distinct names for them. This is sometimes the fault of the language itself, which doesn’t contain a word with the required meaning; and sometimes the fault of the man, who hasn’t yet learned the word for the idea he wants to exhibit to his hearer.

25. Thirdly, no knowledge of things is conveyed by men’s words when their ideas don’t agree with the reality of things. This is basically a defect in our •ideas, which are defective in not being as true to the nature of things as they would be if we were more careful and thorough; but it also stretches out to become a defect in our •words too, when we use them as signs of real things that don’t exist and never did.

26. ·A comment on (1) in 23a·: Someone who has words of a language with no distinct ideas in his mind to be their meanings uses them in conversation only make a noise without any sense or meaning; and no matter how learned he may seem through his use of hard words or learned terms, none of this makes him knowledgeable, any more than a man would count as learned if he had in his study nothing but the bare titles of books, without having their the contents....

27. ·A comment on 24·: Someone who has complex ideas without particular names for them is no better off than a bookseller whose warehouse contains only unbound volumes, without titles, so that he could make them known to others only by showing the loose pages. This man is hindered in his discourse by lack of words to communicate his complex ideas, so that he is forced to make them known by an enumeration of the simple ideas that make them up, with the result that he often has to use twenty words to express what another man signifies in one.

28. ·A comment on (3) in 23a·: Someone who doesn’t constantly use the same sign for the same idea, instead using a word sometimes with one meaning and sometimes with another, ought to be viewed in academic and social circles with as much disapproval as someone who in commercial circles sells different things under the same name.

29. ·A comment on (2) in 23a·: Someone who applies the words of a language to ideas different from those to which the common use of that country applies them won’t be able to convey much to other people by the use of those words unless he defines them—even if he has much to convey....

30. ·A comment on 25·: Someone who imagines to himself substances such as never have existed, and fills his head with ideas that don’t correspond to the real nature of things, and gives these ideas settled and defined names, may fill his discourse and perhaps his hearer’s head with the fantastical imaginations of his own brain, but he’ll be far from advancing a step in real and true knowledge.

[Section 31 briefly recapitulates the content of sections 26–30.]

32. In our notions concerning substances we are liable to all those mishaps. For example, someone •who uses the word ‘tarantula’ without having any idea of what it stands for,....•who in a newly discovered country sees various sorts

188

Essay III John Locke Chapter x: The misuse of words

of animals and vegetables,....but can speak of them only by descriptions,....•who uses the word ‘body’ sometimes for pure extension and sometimes for extension and solidity together,....•who uses the word ‘horse’ with the meaning common usage gives to ‘mule’,....•who thinks the word ‘centaur’ stands for some real thing....

33. With modes and relations generally we are liable only to the first four of these troubles. 1 I may have in my memory the names of modes, for example ‘gratitude’ or ‘charity’ and yet have no precise ideas attached in my thoughts to those names. 2 I may have ideas and not know the words that express them. For example, I may have the idea of a man’s drinking till his colour and mood are altered, till his tongue trips, his eyes look red, and his feet fail him—and yet not know that the word for this is ‘drunkenness’. 3 I may have the ideas of virtues or vices, and have names for them also, but apply the names wrongly. For example when I apply the word ‘frugality’ to the idea that others signify by ‘covetousness’. 4 I may use any of those names in an inconstant manner. 5 But with modes and relations I can’t have ideas disagreeing with the existence of things; for modes are complex ideas that my mind makes at its pleasure, and relations come from considering or comparing two things together, and so they are also ideas of my own making; so these ideas can hardly be found to disagree with anything existing! I don’t have them in my mind as copies of things regularly made by nature, or as ·ideas of· properties inseparably flowing from the internal constitution or essence of any substance. I have them only as patterns lodged in my memory, with names attached to them, to apply to actions and relations as they come to exist....

34. Wit and imagination get a better welcome in the world than dry truth and real knowledge; so people will hardly think that the use of figurative language and ·literary· allusion constitutes an imperfection or misuse of language. In contexts where we seek pleasure and delight rather than information and improvement, such ornaments are indeed not faults. But if we want to speak of things as they are, we must allow that all the art of rhetoric (except for order and clearness)—all the artificial and figurative application of words that eloquence has invented—serve only to insinuate wrong ideas, move the passions, and thereby mislead the judgment; and so they are perfect cheats.... It is evident how much men love to deceive and be deceived, since rhetoric—that powerful instrument of error and deceit—has its established practitioners, is publicly taught, and has always been highly regarded. No doubt I will be thought rash or oafish to have spoken against it....

189

Essay III John Locke xi: Remedies

Chapter xi: The remedies of those imperfections and misuses

1. We have examined at length the imperfections, both natural and contrived, of languages. As speech is the great bond that holds society together, and the channel through which knowledge is conveyed •from man to man and •down the generations, it would be thoroughly worthwhile to consider seriously what remedies are to be found for the above-mentioned troubles.

2. I would cut a ridiculous figure if I tried to effect a complete reform of the language of my own country, let alone of the languages of the world! To require that men use their words always in the same sense, and only for determined and uniform ideas, would be to think that all men should have the same notions and should talk only of what they have clear and distinct ideas of; and no-one can try to bring that about unless he is vain enough to think he can persuade men to be either very knowing or very silent!....

3. Well, the shops and business offices can be left to their own ways of talking, and social chatter can be allowed to continue as it always has. But, though the schools and men of argument might object to any proposal to make their disputes shorter or fewer, I think that those who claim to search seriously after truth, or to maintain it, ought to study how they might say what they have to say without obscurity, doubtfulness, or ambiguity—to all of which men’s words are naturally liable if care is not taken.

[In sections 4–6 Locke adds colour and detail to his picture of the prevalence of misuses of language and of the damage that they do. In section 4 he says there is reason to suspect that ‘language, as it has been employed, has contributed less to the improvement than to the hindrance of knowledge amongst mankind’. Sections 5 and 6 expand this thought with angry passion.]

7. ‘Is a bat a bird?’ That isn’t the question—which it would be quite absurd to ask—whether a bat is something other than what it is, or has qualities other than those it has. There are two questions that could be being asked. 1 Between people who admit to being not quite clear about just what a bat is and just what a bird is, the question may arise as part of an endeavour to learn whether all the simple ideas to which in combination they both give the name ‘bird’ are all to be found in a bat. Understood in this way, it is a question asked only by way of enquiry, not dispute. 2 The question might come up between disputants one of whom says that a bat is a bird while the other denies this. In that case the question is purely about the meaning of ‘bat’ or of ‘bird’ or of both.... If the disputants agreed about the meanings of these two names, there couldn’t possibly be any dispute about them. [The section continues with the suggestion that most disputes are ‘merely verbal’, reflecting differences in what people mean by the same word.]

8. To provide some remedy for the defects of speech that I have mentioned, and to prevent the troubles that follow from them, I think it would be useful to conform to the following rules. First, a man should take care to use no word without a meaning, no name without an idea that he makes it stand for. [The remainder of the section sketches evidence that this rule is often broken.]

9. Secondly, it isn’t enough for a man to use his words as signs of some ideas; the ideas must be •if simple then clear and distinct, and •if complex then determinate—that

190

Essay III John Locke xi: Remedies

is, he must have a definite collection of simple ideas firmly in mind, and have attached to it a word that is his sign of just that collection and no other. [The section continues with remarks about the need for this, and about how it is flouted in people’s uses of words like ‘justice’. Locke describes the procedure one would have to go through to be sure and clear about one’s meaning for ‘justice’, and then continues:] I don’t say that a man should recall this analysis and run through it in detail every time he encounters the word ‘justice’; but he should at least be able to do that when he wants to, as a result of having examined the meaning of the word and settled the idea of all its parts in his mind.... This •exactness may be thought to be too much trouble, and therefore most men will let themselves off from settling the complex ideas of mixed modes so precisely in their minds. But until they do this they can expect to have a great deal of obscurity and confusion in their own minds and a great deal of wrangling in their conversations with others.

10. More is required for a right use of the names of substances than merely determined ideas. Here the names must also fit things as they exist; but I shall say more about this later ·in sections 19–25·. This •exactness is absolutely necessary in the search for philosophical and scientific knowledge, and in controversies about truth. It would be good if it also carried over into common conversation and the ordinary affairs of life, but I suppose that’s hardly to be expected. Unlearned notions suit unlearned talk; and although both are confused enough they still serve quite well the market and the village fête. Merchants and lovers, cooks and tailors, have the words they need to conduct their ordinary affairs; and I think the same might also be true of philosophers and disputants if they really wanted to understand and be clearly understood.

11. Thirdly, it isn’t enough that men have ideas, determined ideas, for which they make these signs stand; they must also do their careful best to give their words meanings that are as near as possible to the ones common usage has attached them to. For words, especially in languages already formed, are •no man’s private possession but rather •the common measure of commerce and communication, so no-one is at liberty to please himself about what to mean by them—and if you really need to change a word’s meaning you should declare that you are doing so. ·And that oughtn’t to happen often·. aim in speaking is or should be to be understood, and that will be thwarted if we give frequent explanations, demands, and other such awkward interruptions that occur when men don’t follow common usage....

[In section 12 Locke says (‘Fourthly’) that there imay be a legitimate need to declare clearly and explicitly what one means by some word. One may be introducing a useful new word, or using a common word in a new sense.]

13. The ideas that men’s words stand for are of different sorts, and there are corresponding differences in the ways of making clear, as needed, what those ideas are. Definition is ·generally· thought to be the right way to make known the proper meaning of a word; but •some words can’t be defined; •others have meanings that can’t be elucidated except through definition; and perhaps there is •a third kind of word that has something in common with each of the other two kinds ·in being capable of having their meanings explained through definitions or in other ways·. Let us see all this in action in connection with the names of •simple ideas, •modes, and •substances.

14. First, when a man uses the name of a simple idea, and sees that it isn’t understood or risks being misunderstood, he ought....to declare his meaning. I have shown that he can’t

191

Essay III John Locke xi: Remedies

do this with a definition (·iv.7·); and he has only two other resources. He can •name some object in which ·a quality signified by· that simple idea is to be found—e.g. telling a farmer what ‘feuillemorte’ means, by saying that it is the colour of withered leaves falling in autumn. But the only sure way of telling someone the meaning of the name of any simple idea is •by presenting to his senses an object which produces in his mind the idea that word stands for.

[In section 15 (‘Secondly’) Locke turns to mixed modes. Because they are constructions of ideas voluntarily put together by the mind, someone who employs a name of a mixed mode is perfectly placed to define it, i.e. set out explicitly what he means by it; and because they have no patterns in nature, their names can’t be explained in any other way. Locke objects fiercely to obscurity in ‘moral discourses’, because the topic is of great importance and there is no excuse for unclarity because the cure for it—verbal definition—is easy to provide.]

16. That is why I venture to think that morality is capable of demonstration, as well as mathematics. The precise real essences—·which are also the nominal essences·—of the things that moral words stand for can be perfectly known; and so the congruity and incongruity of the things themselves can be certainly discovered, which is to say that there can be perfect knowledge of them. It may be objected that the names of substances are often used in morality, and that they will introduce obscurity; but they won’t. When substances are involved in moral discourses, their various natures aren’t being enquired into but presupposed. For example, when we say that man is subject to law, all we mean by ‘man’ is a corporeal rational creature, with no concern for what the real essence or other qualities of that creature are. Whether a certain imbecile is a man in a physical sense is something the scientists may dispute about, but it doesn’t affect the moral man—so to call him—which is this immovable unchangeable idea, a corporeal rational being. For if we found a monkey or any other creature that had enough use of reason to be able to understand general signs and to draw conclusions using general ideas, he would no doubt be subject to law and in that sense be ‘a man’, however much he differed in shape from the rest of us. The names of substances, if they are used as they should be, can no more make trouble in moral discourses than they do in mathematical ones: if a mathematician speaks of a cube or globe of gold, he has his clear settled idea that doesn’t vary even if by mistake he is applying it to a particular body that isn’t gold.

[In section 17 Locke repeats and develops a little his view that the defining of names of mixed modes is important (especially in moral discourses) and easy, so that there is no excuse for not doing it:] It is far easier for men •to form an idea to serve as their standard for the name ‘justice’, so that actions fitting that pattern will be called ‘just’, than •to see Aristides and form an idea that will in all things be exactly like him. Aristides is as he is, whatever idea men choose to make of him! For •the former, all they need is to know the combination of ideas that are put together in their own minds; for •the latter they must enquire into the whole nature and abstruse hidden constitution and various qualities of ·Aristides·, a thing existing outside them.

[Section 18 repeats that verbal definition is our only way of making the meanings of such names clearly known.]

19. Thirdly, for explaining the meanings of the names of substances, as they stand for the ideas we have of their different species, each of the previously mentioned ways—showing and defining—is often needed. Within our

192

Essay III John Locke xi: Remedies

complex idea of a kind of substance there are usually a few •leading qualities to which we suppose the other ideas to be attached; and we readily apply the specific name to anything that has that •characteristic mark that we take to be the most distinguishing idea of that species. These salient or characteristic ideas (so to call them) are mostly of shape in the species of animals and plants, and of colour (and sometimes shape as well) in inanimate bodies, as I pointed out in vi.29 and ix.15.

20. Now, these leading perceptible qualities are •the chief ingredients in our ideas of species of substances, which makes them also •the most conspicuous and invariable elements in the definitions of our names of those species. The sound ‘man’ is in itself as apt to signify animality and rationality, united in the same subject as to signify any other complex idea; but when we use that sound to stand for creatures that we count as being of our own kind, it may be that outward shape is as essential an ingredient in our complex idea as any other. So it won’t be easy to show that Plato’s ‘featherless biped’ is a worse definition than ‘rational animal’ for the word ‘man’, as a label for creatures of that sort. For the leading quality that most often seems to determine that species is shape, rather than a faculty of reasoning; indeed, reason doesn’t show up in the early stages of human life, and in some it never shows up. If you don’t agree with this, I don’t see how you can avoid condemning as murderers those who kill new-born monsters (as we call them) because of their extraordinary shape, without knowing whether they have a rational soul—for that question can’t be answered at the birth of any infant, however it is shaped. And ·you can’t get out of this by pleading that the strange shape is evidence for the lack of a rational soul·: who has told us that a rational soul can’t inhabit a lodging that doesn’t have such and such a kind of exterior—i.e. that it can’t join itself to and inform a body unless the body has such and such an outward structure?

21. These leading qualities are best made known by showing, and can hardly be made known in any other way. Seeing a horse or an ostrich will give an idea of its shape a thousand times better than could be done in words; and the only way to get idea of the particular colour of gold isn’t by description but by frequently seeing it; which is why people who are used to gold can often tell true gold from counterfeit, pure gold from alloy, by sight alone, where the rest of us, though are eyes are all right, can’t see any difference because we don’t have the precise fine-grained idea of that particular yellow....

22. But many of the simple ideas that make up our specific ideas of substances are powers that are not immediately observable in the ordinary appearance of the things; so in explaining our names of substances we do better if part of the meaning is given by enumerating those simple ideas rather than showing the substance itself. If someone has acquired through sight the idea of the yellow shining colour of gold, and then adds to that—from my enumerating them—the ideas of great ductility, fusibility, fixedness, and solubility in aqua regia, he will have a more complete idea of gold than he could get just by seeing a piece of gold and thereby imprinting on his mind its obvious qualities. But if the formal constitution ·or real essence· of this shining, heavy, ductile thing lay open to our senses as does the formal constitution or essence of a triangle, the meaning of the word ‘gold’ might as easily be ascertained as that of ‘triangle’.

23. This reminds us of how much the foundation of all our knowledge of the physical world lies in our senses. Unembodied spirits are sure to have much better knowledge

193

Essay III John Locke xi: Remedies

and ideas of these things than we have; but we haven’t the slightest idea about how they might get such knowledge. The whole extent of our knowledge or imagination reaches only as far as our own ideas, which are limited to our ways of perception. It isn’t to be doubted that spirits of a higher rank than those immersed in flesh ·as we are· may have as clear ideas of the radical constitution of substances as we have of a triangle, and so perceive how all their properties and operations flow from that; but we can’t conceive how they could come by that knowledge.

24. But although definitions serve to explain our substancenames as they stand for our ideas, they do a poor job of explaining them as they stand for things. For our names of substances are not merely signs of our ideas; they are also used ultimately to represent things, and so are put in the place of things; therefore their meaning must agree with the truth of things as well as with men’s ideas. Where substances are concerned, therefore, we shouldn’t always rest content with the ordinary complex idea that is commonly accepted as the meaning of that word. Instead we should go a little further and enquire into the nature and properties of the things themselves, and thereby make our ideas of their species as complete as possible. For since their names are meant to stand not only for •the complex idea in other men’s minds that in their ordinary meaning they stand for, but also for •collections of simple ideas [here = ‘qualities’] that really do exist in things themselves, their names can’t be defined properly unless natural history is enquired into and their properties are discovered through careful examination. For avoiding troubles in discourse and disputes about natural bodies and substantial things, it isn’t enough merely to have learned the confused or otherwise imperfect idea that gives each word its common meaning, and to keep the words to those ideas in our use of them. We must also •acquaint ourselves with the natural history of each species that we speak about, ·on that basis· •rectify and settle our complex idea belonging to the name of the species, and when there is a need for it •explain to others what the complex idea is that we use the name to stand for. [The remainder of the section exclaims about what a great need for this is created by the sloppiness of most people’s talk and thought.]

25. So it would be a good thing if people who are experienced in scientific enquiries, and acquainted with the various sorts of natural bodies, would list the simple ideas—·or rather the corresponding qualities·—which they observe the individuals of each sort to have in common. That would remove much of the confusion that occurs when different people apply the same name to smaller or larger collections of perceptible qualities, in proportion to the breadth or the carefulness of their experiences of the species in question. But a dictionary of that sort—containing a natural history, so to speak—would require too many people, as well as too much time, cost, trouble and intelligence, ever to be hoped for. Lacking that, we must content ourselves with such definitions of the names of substances as explain the meanings that men give to them in use. It would be good if those, at least, were provided when there is a need for them; but this isn’t usually done. [Locke continues with remarks about the need for such clarifications; and about the shortage of them, which he traces to a misplaced confidence that the meanings of common words are settled and uniform, and to a misguided sense that there is something shameful in having about to ask about meanings. He goes on:] Though such a dictionary as I mentioned above would be too demanding to be hoped for these days, I still think it is reasonable to suggest that words standing for things that are

194

Essay III John Locke xi: Remedies

known and distinguished by their outward shapes should be expressed by little pictures of them. A vocabulary-list made in that way could perhaps teach the true meanings of many terms, especially in languages of remote countries or ages, more easily and quickly than do all the large and laborious comments of learned critics. Naturalists who treat of plants and animals have found the benefits of this procedure, and anyone who has had occasion to consult their pictures will have reason to concede that he has a clearer idea of apium or ibex from a little print of that plant or animal than he could have from a long definition of the names of either of them. [The section continues with further examples.]

[In sections 26–7 Locke says that men often change what they mean by a word in the course of a single discourse, and that sometimes they are ‘forced’ to do this because ‘the provision of words is so scanty in respect to the infinite variety of thoughts’. In some cases the context makes clear enough what change has occurred; but where it does not do so the speaker or writer ought to declare the change openly.]

195

An Essay Concerning Human Understanding

Book IV: Knowledge

John Locke

Copyright © 2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are reported on, between [brackets], in normal-sized type.
First launched: July 2004 Last amended: August 2007
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Chapter i: Knowledge in general 196
Chapter ii: The degrees of our knowledge 199
Chapter iii: The extent of human knowledge 203
Chapter iv: The reality of knowledge 216
Chapter v: Truth in general 221
Chapter vi: Universal propositions, their truth and certainty 225
Chapter vii: Maxims 231

Essay IV John Locke

Chapter viii: Trifling propositions 237
Chapter ix: Knowledge of existence 240
Chapter x: knowledge of the existence of a god 241
Chapter xi: knowledge of the existence of other things 247
Chapter xii: The improvement of our knowledge 253
Chapter xiii: Some other considerations concerning our knowledge 258
Chapter xiv: Judgment 260
Chapter xv: Probability 261
Chapter xvi: The degrees of assent 262
Chapter xvii: Reason 268
Chapter xviii: Faith and reason, and their distinct provinces 273
Chapter xix: Enthusiasm 276
Chapter xx: Wrong assent, or error 281
Chapter xxi: The division of the sciences 288

Essay IV John Locke Chapter i: Knowledge in general

Chapter i: Knowledge in general

1. Since the mind in all its thoughts and reasonings has no immediate object other than its own ideas, which are all it can contemplate, it is evident that our knowledge has to do only with them.

2. Knowledge, then, seems to me to be nothing but the perception of the connection and agreement, or disagreement and incompatibility, of any of our ideas. That is all it is. Where this perception occurs, there is knowledge; and where it doesn’t occur, we come short of knowledge—whatever we may fancy, guess, or believe. For when we know that white isn’t black, what do we perceive other than that these two ideas don’t agree? When we know with absolute demonstrative certainty that the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right ones, what do we do except perceive that •equality to two right angles necessarily agrees to and is inseparable from •the three angles of a triangle?

3. This agreement or disagreement can be better understood through noting that there are four sorts of it:

Identity, or diversity.

Relation.

Co-existence, or necessary connection.

Real existence.

4. The first sort of agreement or disagreement—namely, identity or diversity—enters into the act of the mind when it first has any views or ideas at all. What it does then is to perceive its ideas; and so far as it perceives them it knows each to be what it is, and thus also to perceive their differences from one another—perceiving of each that it is not some other idea. This is so absolutely necessary that without it there could be no knowledge, no reasoning, no imagination, no distinct thoughts, at all. In this way the mind clearly and infallibly perceives each idea to agree with itself, and to be what it is; and perceives all different ideas to disagree, i.e. perceives the one not to be the other. It does this easily, without taking trouble over it or inferring it from something else; it does it at first view, through its natural ability to perceive and distinguish. And although students of scholastic philosophy have boiled this down to

What is, is, and

It is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be

—general rules that can be applied in any case where there is occasion to think about this—it is certain that the first exercise of this faculty concerns particular ideas. A man infallibly knows, as soon as ever he has them, that the ideas he calls ‘white’ and ‘round’ are the very ideas they are, and not others that he calls ‘red’ or ‘square’. And no •maxim or proposition could make him know this more clearly or surely than he already does without the help of any such •general rule. This, then, is the first agreement or disagreement that the mind perceives in its ideas, and always at first sight. If there is ever any doubt about it, will always turn out to concern the names, not the ideas....

5. The second sort of agreement or disagreement that the mind perceives in its ideas can be called relative. It is simply perceiving a relation between two ideas, which can be of any kind at all—of substances, modes, or anything else. For since any two ideas must eternally be known not to be the same, there would be no room for positive knowledge if we couldn’t perceive relations ·other than non-identity· between our ideas, and find out whether they agree or disagree in various respects of comparison that the mind brings to bear

196

Essay IV John Locke Chapter i: Knowledge in general

on them. [For Locke ‘comparing x with y’ is just bringing x and y together in a single thought, not necessarily likening them to one another. We use ‘compare’ in that way in the expression ‘get together to compare notes’.]

6. The third sort of agreement or disagreement that the mind can perceive in our ideas is co-existence or non-co-existence in the same subject. This belongs particularly to substances. When we say that gold is fixed, our knowledge of this truth amounts to no more than this: fixedness, or a power to remain in fire unconsumed, is an idea [here = ‘quality’] that always accompanies and is joined to that particular sort of yellowness, weight, fusibility, malleableness, and solubility in aqua regia that make our complex idea signified by the word ‘gold’.

7. The fourth and last sort is an idea’s agreement with actual real existence. These four sorts of agreement or disagreement include, I think, all the knowledge we have or can have. All we can ever know or say about any idea is one of these:

•that it is or that it isn’t the same as some other,

•that it does or that it doesn’t always co-exist with some other idea in the same subject,

•that it has this or that relation with some other idea,

•that ·something corresponding to· it has a real existence outside the mind.

Thus ‘Blue is not yellow’ is of identity; ‘Two triangles on equal bases between two parallells are equal’ is of relation; ‘Iron is magnetizable’ is of co-existence; and ‘God exists’ is of real existence. Though identity and co-existence are themselves relations, they are such special kinds of agreement or disagreement amongst ideas that they deserve to be brought in separately, not under relation in general. Before examining the various degrees of our knowledge, I must first consider the different meanings that the word ‘knowledge’ can have.

8. The word ‘knowledge’ is applied to several ways in which the mind can possess truth. 1. There is actual knowledge, which is the mind’s view of how any two of its present ideas agree or disagree, or of how they are related to one another. 2. A man is said to ‘know’ a proposition if he once had actual knowledge of it and has kept that in his memory so that whenever he again reflects on that proposition he immediately and confidently assents to it again. I think we might call this habitual knowledge. We with our finite understandings can think clearly and distinctly of only one thing at a time; so if we had knowledge ·at a given time· only of what we were actually thinking about ·at that time, thus having actual but not habitual knowledge·, we would all be very ignorant; and even the person who ‘knew most’ would know only one truth.

9. Of habitual knowledge there are also what ordinary folk would call two degrees. In one of them, truths are laid up in the memory in such a way that whenever they occur to the mind it ·again· actually perceives the relation between those ideas. This is the degree of habitual knowledge that we have of all those truths of which we have an intuitive knowledge, where a view of the ideas immediately reveals their agreement or disagreement one with another.

The other is knowledge of truths of which the mind was once convinced, and retains the memory of the conviction but doesn’t retain the demonstration [= ‘rigorous, logical, knock-down proof’]. A man who remembers certainly that he once took in the demonstration that the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles is certain that he knows it, because he can’t doubt its truth. It may be thought that in a case like this, where a man adheres to a truth after forgetting the demonstration that first led him to know it, he believes his memory rather than really knowing ·the truth

197

Essay IV John Locke Chapter i: Knowledge in general

in question·; and I used to think that this way of receiving a truth lies somewhere between opinion and knowledge—a kind of assurance that surpasses mere belief, for that relies on the testimony of someone else, ·but not reaching as far as knowledge·. But on a closer look I find that it doesn’t fall short of perfect certainty, and is in effect true knowledge. What is apt to mislead us about this case is that in it

the agreement or disagreement of the ideas isn’t perceived by an actual view of all the intermediate ideas that in the first instance enabled the agreement or disagreement of the ideas in the proposition to be perceived.

Rather,

it is perceived through other intermediate ideas that show the agreement or disagreement of the ideas contained in the proposition whose certainty we remember.

Take for example the proposition that the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles. Someone who has clearly perceived the demonstration of this truth knows it to be true even when that demonstration is gone out of his mind so that at present it isn’t actually in view and he can’t possibly recollect it. But he knows it in a different way from how he knew it before. The agreement of the two ideas joined in that proposition is perceived through the intervention of ideas other than those that at first led him to perceive the proposition’s truth. He remembers, i.e. he knows (for remembering is just reviving some past knowledge), that he was once certain of the truth of the proposition that the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right ones. Ideas don’t change and so the relations between them don’t change either; and his grasp of that is now the idea that shows him that if the three angles of a triangle were once equal to two right ones, they will always be so. And so he comes to be certain that what was once true about this is always true; ideas that once agreed will always agree; and consequently what he once knew to be true he will always know to be true as long as he can remember that he once knew it.

That is how particular demonstrations in mathematics provide general knowledge. So if the perception that the same ideas eternally have the same intrinsic natures and the same relations ·to one another· were not a sufficient ground for knowledge, there could be no knowledge of general propositions in mathematics; for no mathematical demonstration would be other than particular, and when a man had demonstrated a proposition about one triangle, his knowledge wouldn’t reach beyond that particular diagram. If he wanted to know it to be true of another similar triangle, he would have to make a diagram of that and go through the demonstration again. No-one could never come to know any general propositions in that way. Nobody would deny that Mr. Newton ·now· knows to be true any proposition that he now reads in his book, even though he doesn’t ·now· have openly before his mind the admirable chain of intermediate ideas through which he first discovered it to be true. The discovery, perception, and setting out of that wonderful connection of ideas is more than most people are capable of; so we may well think that a memory able to retain such a sequence of particulars is beyond the reach of human faculties. But obviously the author himself knows the proposition to be true, remembering that he once saw the connection of those ideas, just as certainly as he knows that a certain man wounded another, remembering that he saw him run him through with a sword. Still, memory isn’t always as clear as actual perception, and in all men it decays somewhat as time passes; and this is one factor that makes demonstrative knowledge less perfect than intuitive, as we shall see in the following chapter.

198

Essay IV John Locke Chapter ii: Degrees of knowledge

Chapter ii: The degrees of our knowledge

1. All our knowledge consists in the mind’s view of its own ideas, this being the brightest light and greatest certainty that we—with our faculties and our ways of knowing—are capable of. So it may be worthwhile to consider a little the degrees of its evidence—·that is, consider the factors that make items of knowledge more or less evident·. The differences in how clear—·i.e. how evident·—our knowledge is seem to me to come from differences in how the mind perceives the agreement or disagreement of ideas. Sometimes our mind perceives the agreement or disagreement of two ideas immediately—by themselves, without the intervention of any other ideas. I think we may call this intuitive knowledge, for in it the mind isn’t trying to prove or explore anything, but simply perceives the truth as the eye perceives light, just by being directed towards it. Thus the mind perceives—by bare intuition, without the intervention of any other idea—that white is not black, that a circle is not a triangle, that three are more than two and equal to one plus two. This kind of knowledge is the clearest and most certain that human frailty is capable of. Knowledge of this kind is irresistible: like bright sunshine it forces one to perceive it immediately, as soon as the mind looks that way; and it leaves no room for hesitation, doubt, or further enquiry because the mind is filled with the clear light of it. All the certainty and evidentness of all our knowledge depends on this intuition. The certainty it brings is so great that no-one can imagine—and so no-one could ask for—a greater. A man cannot conceive himself capable of a greater certainty than to know that a given idea in his mind is such as he perceives it to be; and that two ideas between which he perceives a difference are different and not precisely the same. Anyone who demands greater certainty than this doesn’t know what he is asking for; all he does is to show that he would like to be a sceptic but isn’t able to be so. Certainty depends wholly on this intuition; in the next degree of knowledge, which I call ‘demonstrative’, we attain knowledge and certainty only through intuition of all the connections of the intermediate ideas.

2. The next degree of knowledge occurs when the mind perceives the agreement or disagreement of any ideas, but not immediately. The mind doesn’t always see the agreement or disagreement between two ideas, even when it is discoverable; and in such a case it remains in ignorance, achieving at most a probable conjecture. The reason why the mind can’t always perceive, straight off, the agreement or disagreement of two ideas is that it can’t put the ideas together in such a way as to show their agreement or disagreement. In this case the mind has to discover the agreement or disagreement that it is searching for by bringing in one or more intervening ideas; and this is what we call reasoning. For example, the mind wants to know whether the three angles of a triangle agree or disagree in size with two right angles; and it can’t answer this by an immediate view in which the two items are compared, because the three angles of a triangle can’t be brought before the mind at one time and compared with any other one or two angles. So the mind has no immediate or intuitive knowledge of this. In this case the mind has to find some other angles to which the three angles of a triangle are equal, and to which two right angles are also equal, in this way coming to know the proposition it was enquiring about.

3. The intervening ideas that serve to show the agreement of any two others are called ‘proofs’; and when this procedure

199

Essay IV John Locke Chapter ii: Degrees of knowledge

shows plainly and clearly the agreement or disagreement, it is called ‘demonstration’. Mental agility in finding these intermediate ideas and applying them correctly is, I suppose, what is called ‘sagacity’.

4. Although this knowledge by intervening proofs is certain, it isn’t quite as clearly and brightly evident as intuitive knowledge, and we don’t assent to it quite so readily. In demonstration the mind does come to perceive the agreement or disagreement of the ideas it is thinking about, but for this it has to focus and pay attention. To achieve this knowledge the mind needs more than one passing view of the ideas; a steady application and pursuit are required; and a series of steps must be taken before the mind can in this way arrive at certainty and come to perceive the agreement or inconsistency between the two ideas.

5. Although in demonstrative knowledge all doubt is removed when by the intervention of the intermediate ideas the agreement or disagreement is perceived, before the demonstration there was a doubt. In that respect it differs from intuitive knowledge. If a mind has enough faculty of perception to be able to have distinct ideas, it can’t be in doubt about them, any more than someone with functioning eyes can be in doubt whether this ink and this paper have the same colour. If there is sight in the eyes, the mind will perceive the words printed on this paper as different from the colour of the paper; and similarly if a mind has the faculty of distinct perception, it will perceive ·at first glance and without hesitation· the agreement or disagreement of those ideas that produce intuitive knowledge....

6. The perception produced by demonstration is also very clear, but it often falls a long way short of that evident shine and complete confidence that always accompany intuitive knowledge. It can be compared with a face reflected along a sequence of mirrors: each successive reflection brings a lessening of the perfect clearness and distinctness of the first in the sequence, and if we go far enough we shall find that the reflection is quite dim, and isn’t at first sight so knowable, especially to weak eyes. That is how it is with knowledge supported by a long proof.

7. When reason achieves demonstrative knowledge, there is intuitive knowledge every step of the way concerning the agreement or disagreement of each successive pair of intermediate ideas. Without that, we would need a proof of each intermediate step, ·which would create an infinite regress·. Once the mind has had this intuitive certainty, it needs only to remember it to make visible and certain the agreement or disagreement of the two ideas in question. For a complete demonstration, the mind must •perceive the immediate agreement of each pair of ideas in the sequence (starting with one of the ideas in the demonstrated the proposition and ending with the other) and •carry with it a memory of the entire procedure, with no part being left out. In long deductions this is hard to do, which is why demonstrative knowledge is more imperfect than intuitive knowledge, and why men often welcome a falsehood as something they have demonstrated.

8. I suppose it was the need for this intuitive knowledge at each step in demonstrative reasoning that gave rise to the mistaken axiom that all reasoning is ex praecognitis et praeconcessis [= ‘from things already known and agreed to’]. I shall show how much of a mistake that is when I come to consider maxims (vii), and show that people are wrong in supposing them to be the foundations of all our knowledge and reasoning.

9. It has been generally taken for granted that only mathematics is capable of demonstrative certainty, but ·I don’t

200

Essay IV John Locke Chapter ii: Degrees of knowledge

agree; and here is why·. It is not the privilege of the ideas of number, extension, and shape alone to have intuitively perceivable agreements and disagreements; and although demonstration has been thought to have little to do with anything else—so that mathematicians are almost the only ones who even try to demonstrate anything—that may be due to our failure to work hard and methodically on demonstrations in topics outside mathematics, rather than to a lack of evidentness in those topics. For whenever we have ideas whose agreement or disagreement the mind can perceive immediately, the mind is capable of intuitive knowledge; and whenever it can intuitively perceive the agreement or disagreement that ideas have with intermediate ideas, the mind is capable of demonstration, which isn’t limited to ideas of extension, shape, number, and their modes.

10. The reason why it has been generally looked for only in mathematics is, I suppose, not only the general usefulness of those sciences, but also the fact that when we compare the equality or inequality of the modes of numbers every little difference is very clear and perceivable. It isn’t so with extension, but even here ·demonstrative geometry is possible, because· the mind has found out ways to examine and show demonstratively the exact equality of two angles, or lengths, or figures. Also, both of these—numbers and figures—can be recorded by visible and lasting •marks through which the ideas under consideration are perfectly determined; which they seldom are when marked only by •names and words.

11. But with other simple ideas, whose modes and differences are made and counted by degrees and not quantity—·for example, in contrasts like ‘x is much redder than y’ rather than like ‘x has 2.37 times the volume of y’·—we don’t have such finely accurate ways of determining their differences or their exact equality. Those other simple ideas are appearances of sensations produced in us by the size, shape, number, and motion of corpuscles each of which is too small to be perceptible on its own; so their different degrees must also depend on variations in some or of all those causes; and since we can’t observe the variations in particles of matter each of which is too tiny to be perceived, we can’t have any exact measures of the different degrees of these simple ideas. [The section continues with an invented story about the causes of colour sensations, with special emphasis on whiteness. After making his point with this, Locke comments on one aspect of it:] I don’t say that the nature of light consists in very small round globules....for I am not now offering a physical account of light or colours. But I can’t conceive—and if you can, please show me how—of any way for bodies outside us to affect our senses other than through the immediate contact of the sensible bodies themselves (as in tasting and feeling) or the impact of some insensible particles coming from them (as in seeing, hearing, and smelling).

[In sections 12–13 Locke develops his point that •we can make fine discriminations amongst primary qualities, and •they are the causes of our ideas of secondary qualities, but that •this doesn’t help us to discriminate finely among the latter because we don’t know in detail what their causes are—what shapes or velocities of particles etc. He concludes:] Where the difference is so great as to produce in the mind clearly distinct ideas, whose differences can be perfectly retained, there these ideas of colours (e.g. blue and red) are as capable of demonstration as ideas of number and extension. What I have here said of whiteness and colours, I think, holds true of all secondary qualities and their modes.

14. Intuition and demonstration are our two degrees of knowledge; whatever falls short of these, however confidently

201

Essay IV John Locke Chapter ii: Degrees of knowledge

accepted, is merely faith or opinion, not knowledge. This holds at least for all general truths. But there is another perception of the mind, concerning the particular existence of finite beings outside us, which does not reach the whole way to either of the foregoing degrees of certainty, yet is called ‘knowledge’. It does indeed go beyond mere probability. There can be nothing more certain than that the idea we receive from an external object is in our minds; this is intuitive knowledge. But is there anything more than just that idea in our minds? Can we certainly infer from that idea the existence of something outside us corresponding to it? Some men think this is a real question, because people sometimes have such ideas in their minds at times when no such thing exists, no such object affects their senses. But I think that we are provided with a degree of evidentness that puts us past doubting. For I ask you, are you not irresistibly conscious to yourself of a different perception when you look at the sun by day from what you have when you think about it at night? when you actually taste wormwood or smell a rose, and when you only think about that taste or smell? An idea revived in our minds by our own memory differs from one coming into our minds through our senses, the difference being as obvious as that between any two ideas. If anyone says ‘A dream can do the same thing, and all these ideas could be produced in us without any external objects’, I invite him to dream that I answer him thus:

•It doesn’t matter much whether I remove your doubt, because where everything is a dream, reasoning and arguments are of no use, and truth and knowledge are nothing. Also, •I believe you will allow a very obvious difference between dreaming of being in a fire and being actually in it.

If he has made up his mind to appear so sceptical as to maintain that what I call being actually in the fire is nothing but a dream, and that we cannot certainly know from that experience that any such thing as fire actually exists outside us, I answer:

We certainly find that pleasure or pain follows upon the application to us of certain objects whose existence we perceive (or dream that we perceive!) through our senses; and this certainty is as great as we need for practical purposes, which are the only purposes we ought to have.

[The last clause renders Locke’s words: ‘and this certainty is as great as our happiness or misery, beyond which we have no concernment to know or to be.’] So I think we may add to the former two sorts of knowledge this third one, knowledge of the existence of particular external objects through the perception and consciousness we have of the actual entrance of ideas from them ·through our senses·. That gives us three degrees of knowledge: intuitive, demonstrative, and sensitive....

15. Since •our knowledge is based on and directed towards our ideas only, doesn’t it follow that •it must conform to our ideas, so that where the ideas are clear and distinct, or obscure and confused, our knowledge will be so too? No—·that is only half true·. Knowledge consists in the perception of the agreement or disagreement of two ideas, so its clearness or obscurity consists in the clearness or obscurity of that perception, not of the ideas themselves. Thus, a man whose ideas of the angles of a triangle and of equality to two right angles are as clear as any mathematician’s, may have only an obscure perception of their agreement, and so have only a very obscure knowledge that they do agree—·i.e. that the angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles·. But ideas that are confused—whether because of obscurity or for some other reason—can’t produce clear or distinct knowledge; because if two ideas are confused, the mind can’t perceive

202

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

clearly whether they agree. In short: someone who doesn’t accompany •his words with definite ideas can’t use •them to make propositions of whose truth he can be certain.

Chapter iii: The extent of human knowledge

1. Knowledge lies in the perception of the agreement or disagreement of our ideas. From this ·five· things follow. First, our knowledge can’t extend further than our ideas do.

2. Secondly, our knowledge can’t extend further than our perceptions of the agreement or disagreement of ideas. Such perceptions come •by intuition, or the immediate inter-relating of any two ideas, •by reason, examining the agreement or disagreement of two ideas by the intervention of some others, or •by sensation, perceiving the existence of particular things.

3. Thirdly, we can’t have •intuitive knowledge involving all our ideas and answering all our questions about them, because we can’t perceive all their relations to one another by juxtaposition, that is, by immediately relating one to another. Thus having ideas of an obtuse-angled and an acute-angled triangle, both drawn from equal bases and between parallels, I have intuitive knowledge that one of these ideas is not the other, but I can’t know in that way whether they are equal or not, because their agreement or disagreement in equality can never be perceived by immediately relating them to one another. Their shapes differ in a manner that prevents us from immediately and exactly comparing their areas; and so we need some intervening qualities to measure them by, and that is •demonstration, or knowledge by reasoning.

4. Fourthly, our knowledge by reasoning can’t reach to the whole extent of our ideas either, because between two different ideas that we want to examine we can’t always find intermediaries that will let us link one with the other, with intuitive knowledge at every link; and when we can’t do that, we fall short of knowledge and demonstration.

5. Fifthly, because sensitive knowledge reaches no further than the existence of things actually present to our senses, it is even narrower in extent than either of the other two.

6. All this makes it evident that the extent of our knowledge falls short not only of the reality of things but even of the extent of our own ideas. knowledge is limited to our ideas, and can’t be broader or better than they are; and this sets very narrow limits to what we can know—narrow in relation to the whole of what is the case, and even in relation to knowledge that we can reasonably suppose to be possessed by some created understandings, ones that aren’t tied down to the dull and narrow information that we get from a few crude modes of perception, such as our senses are. Still, we would be well off if our knowledge did at least extend out to those limits, leaving us with few doubts and questions concerning the ideas that we have; but ·in fact, as I observed at the start of this section, it comes a long way short of that. Concerning the ideas that we do have· there are plenty of

203

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

questions that we can’t answer and (I believe) that we never shall be able to answer.

No doubt human knowledge, given our present circumstances and constitutions, can be taken further than it has been up to now, if men would work as hard on •improving the means of discovering truth as they now do on •supporting or disguising falsehoods, and on •maintaining systems, interests, and parties to which they have committed themselves. But I don’t think it is an insult to human excellence to be sure, as I am, that our knowledge would never reach to all we might want to know concerning the ideas that we have, or be able to surmount all the difficulties and answer all the questions that might arise concerning any of them. We have the ideas of a square, a circle, and equality; and yet perhaps we shall never be able to find a circle equal to a square and certainly know that it is so. We have the ideas of matter and thinking, but possibly we shall never be able to know whether any mere material being thinks; for it is impossible for us, by contemplating our own ideas with no help from revelation, to discover ·what kind of thing a human being is. That is, to discover· whether •God has given to a suitably laid out system of matter a power to perceive and think, or rather •has attached to such a system a thinking immaterial substance. It isn’t much harder for us to conceive that God can, if he pleases, •add to matter a power of thinking, than to conceive that he should •add to it another substance with a power of thinking; for we don’t know what thinking consists in, or to what sorts of substances the almighty has been pleased to give the power to think—a power that no created being can have except through the generous will of the creator. ·The choice here is between two accounts of what a human being is. 1 It is a material thing that thinks. 2 It is a material thing linked with a second thing that thinks; but we must take 2 as also saying that how the second substance thinks—what perceptions it has—depends on physical changes in the material thing to which it is linked, as when your visual perceptions are extinguished when you close your eyes·. I see no contradiction in supposing that ·God·, the •first eternal thinking being or omnipotent spirit should, if he pleased, give some degrees of sense, perception, and thought to certain systems of created senseless matter, put together as he thinks fit. (Though, as I think I prove in x.14 etc., it is a contradiction to suppose that matter—which is obviously in its own nature devoid of sense and thought—should be that •eternal first-thinking being.) How could anyone know that this is false?—

1 Some perceptions—e.g. pleasure and pain—could occur in some bodies themselves when they are appropriately affected;

while knowing that this is true?—

2 Some perceptions—e.g. pleasure and pain—could occur in an immaterial substance upon [= ‘when triggered by’] the motion of parts of a body.

As far as we can conceive, all bodies can do is to bump into and affect other bodies; and motion, according to the utmost reach of our ideas, can produce nothing but motion. So when we suppose it 2 to produce pleasure or pain, or the idea of a colour or sound, we have to stop employing our reason, go beyond our ideas, and attribute it wholly to the good pleasure of our Maker. ·It is beyond question that when I turn my head my visual ideas alter, and so· we must allow that God has brought it about that motion produces effects •that we can’t conceive of its being able to produce. Well, then, what reason have we to conclude that he could not ·as on supposition 1· order those effects to be produced in a subject •that we can’t conceive to be capable of having them, as well as—·supposition 2·—in a subject that we can’t

204

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

conceive of as being affectable in any way by the motion of matter?

I don’t say this so as to lessen the belief in the soul’s immateriality; I am speaking here not of probability but of knowledge; and ·I am motivated by two beliefs·. •I think that it is suitable to the modesty of philosophy not to pronounce dogmatically on topics where we lack the evidentness that could produce knowledge. •I also think it is useful for us to learn how far our knowledge does reach; for our present state, not being one of divinely inspired vision, requires us often to ·settle for something less than knowledge, and to· be content with faith and probability. And it’s not surprising that we aren’t equipped to arrive at demonstrative certainty in answering the present question about the soul’s immateriality.

All the great ends of morality and religion are well enough secured without philosophical proofs of the soul’s immateriality, because it is obvious that at the start of the world God •made us to exist here—and to continue for many years—as thinking beings equipped with senses, and •can and will restore us to that same state of sentience ·or feeling· in another world, making us capable there of feeling the rewards and punishments he has planned for men according to their doings in this life. If that is certain, it isn’t so enormously important to settle the question about the immateriality of the soul, one way or the other, as some zealots on each side of the question have tried to make the world believe. •On one side, the zealots give too much play to their own thoughts, which are completely immersed in matter, and can’t allow for the existence of anything that isn’t material. •On the other are those who, because they can’t find thought within the natural powers of matter, however hard they look for it, are bold enough to conclude that not even God the omnipotent can give perception and thought to a substance that has the quality of solidity. If you consider how hard it is in our thoughts to reconcile •sensation to •extended matter, and how hard to reconcile •existence to •anything that has no extension at all, you will admit that you are very far from knowing for sure what your soul is! This issue seems to me to lie beyond the reach of our knowledge; and anyone who will allow himself to think freely, and to look into the dark and intricate part of each hypothesis, will hardly find his reason directing him firmly for or against the soul’s materiality. Whether he thinks of the soul as an unextended substance, or as thinking extended matter, he will encounter difficulties that will drive him to the contrary side. This is an unattractive way that some men have of managing their thoughts: finding one hypothesis inconceivable, they throw themselves violently into the arms of the contrary hypothesis, even though it is (to an unbiased understanding) just as unintelligible. This serves not only to show how weak and scanty our knowledge is, but also the insignificant triumph of arguments of that sort.... What good does it do someone to •avoid the seeming absurdities and to him insurmountable obstacles he meets with in one opinion by •taking refuge in the contrary opinion, which is built on something every bit as inexplicable and as far from his comprehension? It is past controversy that we have in us something that thinks; our very doubts about what it is confirm the certainty of its existing, though we must accept our ignorance of what kind of being it is. It’s pointless to set oneself up as a sceptic about this, just as it’s unreasonable in most other cases to deny outright the existence of something because we can’t comprehend its nature. What substance doesn’t have in it something that manifestly baffles our understandings?.... Knowledge, ·as I said at the start of this section·, isn’t only limited to the paucity and imperfections of our ideas, but even comes short of that. How far, then, does it reach?

205

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

7. The affirmations or negations we make concerning our ideas can be grouped into four kinds: •identity, •co-existence, •relation, and •real existence. I shall examine how far our knowledge extends in respect of each of these, ·dealing with the first in section 8, the second in 9–17, the third in 18–20, the fourth in 21·.

8. First, as to •identity and diversity: in this kind of agreement or disagreement of our ideas, our intuitive knowledge extends as far as our ideas themselves. There can be no idea in the mind that it doesn’t instantly, by an intuitive knowledge, perceive to be what it is and to be different from any other.

9. Secondly, as to the agreement or disagreement of our ideas in •co-existence: we don’t have much knowledge of this kind, though what we do have is the greatest and most important part of our knowledge of substances. ideas of the sorts of substances are merely certain collections of simple ideas united in one subject and so co-existing together—for example, our idea of flame is a body that is hot, luminous, and moving upward; of gold a body that has such and such a weight, and is yellow, malleable, and fusible. When we want to know anything more about these or any other sorts of substances, we are simply asking: what other qualities or powers do these substances have (or lack)? Which is just to ask what other simple ideas do (or don’t) co-exist with the ones that make up that complex idea.

10. Although this is a considerable proportion of our totality of systematic knowledge, the actual amount of it that we have is small, almost to vanishing point. That is because very few of the simple ideas of which our complex ideas of substances are composed have in their own nature a visible necessary connection or inconsistency with any other simple ideas whose co-existence with them we would like to know about.

11. The ideas that our complex ideas of substances are composed of, and that are the focus of most of our knowledge concerning substances, are those of their secondary qualities. I have shown that these all depend on the primary qualities of the substances’ minute and imperceptible parts; or if not on them, on something yet more remote from our comprehension. So we can’t possibly know which of them have a necessary union or inconsistency with which others: not knowing the root they spring from—not knowing what size, shape and texture of parts give rise to the qualities that make our complex idea of gold—we can’t know what other qualities result from (or are incompatible with) that same root and so consequently must always co-exist with that complex idea we have of it (or else are inconsistent with it).

12. Besides our ignorance of the primary qualities of the imperceptible parts of bodies, on which all their secondary qualities depend, there is another and more incurable kind of ignorance that keeps us even further from having certain knowledge about the co-existence of different ideas [here = ‘qualities’] in the same subject. It comes from there being no discoverable connection between any secondary quality and the primary qualities on which it depends.

13. We can conceive that the size, shape, and motion of one body might cause a change in the size, shape, and motion of another. The parts of one body separate when another body pushes into it, and a motionless body starts moving when another body bumps into it—there seems to be some connection here ·between intruding and separating, and between bumping and moving·. And if we knew these primary qualities of bodies, we might have reason to hope we could learn a great deal more of their operations on one another. But our minds can’t discover any connection between these primary qualities of bodies and the sensations

206

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

they produce in us; and so we can never establish certain and undoubted rules of the consequence or co-existence of any secondary qualities, even if we did discover the size, shape, and motion of the invisible parts that immediately produce them. We are so far from knowing what shape, size, or motion of parts produce a yellow colour, a sweet taste, or a sharp sound, that we can’t conceive how any size, shape, or motion of any particles could possibly produce in us the idea of any colour, taste, or sound; there is no conceivable connection between the one and the other.

14. So it is useless to try to learn through our ideas (which is the only true way of getting certain and universal knowledge) what other ideas are to be found constantly joined—·coexisting·—with our complex idea of any substance. We need knowledge of two things before we can certainly know the necessary co-existence of any secondary qualities: 1 substances’ real constitutions of minute parts on which their secondary qualities depend, and 2 necessary connections between those and the secondary qualities. We don’t have knowledge of 1, and even if we did, we couldn’t have knowledge of 2.... Our knowledge in all these enquiries reaches very little further than our experience. Indeed, a few primary qualities have a necessary dependence and visible connection with one another—•shape necessarily presupposes •extension, •moving or being moved through collision presupposes •solidity—and we can by intuition or demonstration discover the co-existence of these and a few others. But there aren’t many of them; and for the rest we have to rely on our senses to tell us what qualities substances contain.... For example, we see the yellow colour of a piece of gold, and on testing it find its weight, malleableness, fusibility, and fixedness; but because no one of these ideas has any •evident dependence or •necessary connection with the others, we can’t know for sure that whatever has any four of these qualities will have the fifth also. This may be highly probable; but the highest probability doesn’t amount to certainty, and without that there can be no true knowledge. This co-existence can be known only so far as it is perceived; and if it isn’t perceived in general by the necessary connection of the ideas, our only way of perceiving it is in particular subjects through the observation of our senses.

15. As to •incompatibility, or •impossibility of co-existence, we know that any subject may have at one time only one primary quality of each sort: each particular extension, shape, number of parts, and motion excludes all other extensions, shapes, etc. The same certainly holds for the sensible ideas [here = ‘qualities’] that are special to each sense: if a subject has one such quality it can’t at the same time have another of the same sort; so no one subject can have two smells or two colours at the same time. You may object that an opal has two colours at the same time. Yes, indeed, an opal can present different colours at the same time to differently placed eyes; but I would point out that the differently placed eyes are receiving particles of light from different parts of the opal. So it isn’t the same part of the object, and so not the very same thing, which at the same time appears both yellow and blue. For a single particle of a body can’t modify or reflect the rays of light in two ways at the same time, any more than it can have two different shapes and textures at the same time.

16. Then there are the powers of substances to change the sensible qualities of other bodies. Much of our research into substances is directed towards those powers, and our results constitute a considerable branch of our knowledge. ·But· I suspect that our knowledge about such powers

207

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

reaches little further than our experience. Because the active and passive powers of bodies, and their ways of operating, are based on a texture and motion of parts that we can’t discover, we can seldom perceive their dependence on or inconsistency with any of the ideas that make our complex idea of the given sort of substance, the one that is to us its essence. I have argued for this in terms of the corpuscularian hypothesis—·the theory that all the workings of the material world are to be understood in terms of collisions between tiny portions of matter, tiny corpuscles·—because that’s the theory that is thought to go furthest in intelligibly explaining those qualities of bodies; and I fear that the human understanding hasn’t the power to replace it by one that could give us a fuller and clearer discovery of the necessary connection and co-existence of the powers that are found to be united in various sorts of bodies.... I doubt whether the faculties that we have will ever be able to advance much our general knowledge (as distinct from particular experience) of these matters. Experience is what we must depend on in this part—·that is, in connection with co-existence of qualities·....

17. If we are at a loss regarding the powers and operations of •bodies, it is easy to infer that we are much more in the dark concerning •spirits. The only ideas that we naturally have of these are ones that we draw from ideas of •ourselves by reflecting on the operations of our own souls within us, as far as they can come within our observation. On the strength of my hints ·in II.xxiii.13 and elsewhere· you might like to consider how far down the scale the spirits that inhabit our bodies come, amongst the various and possibly innumerable kinds of nobler beings, and how far short they come of the endowments and perfections of angels and infinite sorts of Spirits above us.

18. As to the third sort of our knowledge—·that is, the third of the four listed in i.7 above·—namely the agreement or disagreement of ideas in respect of any other relation: this is the largest field of our knowledge, but it is hard to determine how much further it can extend. The advances made in this part of knowledge depend on our skill in finding intermediate ideas that show the relations between ideas whose co-existence is not being considered; and it is hard to know when we are at an end of such discoveries, that is, when reason has all the helps it is capable of for finding proofs or examining the agreement or disagreement of ideas that are remote from one another. Those who are ignorant of algebra can’t imagine the wonders of this sort that it can achieve; and it isn’t easy to determine what further improvements and helps, bringing progress to other branches of knowledge, the sagacious mind of man may yet discover. I believe that the ideas of quantity are not the only ones that admit of demonstration and knowledge; and that other realms of enquiry—perhaps more useful ones—would also afford us certainty, if only vices, passions, and domineering interest didn’t oppose or menace such endeavours.

Here are two ideas that are clear in us: •the idea of a supreme being, infinite in power, goodness, and wisdom, who made us and on whom we depend, and •the idea of ourselves, as understanding rational creatures. If we thought hard about these and explored them, I think they would provide foundations for our duty and rules of action, in such a way as to make morality one of the sciences capable of demonstration [= ‘rigorous proof’]. Within such a morality the measures of right and wrong could, I am sure, be derived from self-evident propositions by valid inferences as incontestable as those in mathematics, in a way that would satisfy anyone who was willing to bring to moral studies the same attentiveness and lack of bias that he

208

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

brings to mathematics. The relations between other modes can certainly be perceived, as well as relations concerning number and extension, and I don’t see why they shouldn’t also be capable of demonstration, if we devised good methods for examining their agreements and disagreements. ‘Where there is no property, there is no injustice’ is a proposition as certain as any demonstration in Euclid; for the idea of property being a right to something, and the idea of injustice is the invasion or violation of that right, it is evident that on the strength of these two ideas and the names annexed to them I can as certainly know this proposition to be true as that a triangle has three angles equal to two right ones. Again, ‘No government allows absolute liberty’: the idea of government is the establishment of society on certain rules or laws that require conformity to them, and the idea of absolute liberty is for anyone to do whatever he pleases; so I am as capable of being certain of the truth of this proposition as of any in the mathematics.

19. What has given the advantage in this respect to the ideas of quantity ·over those of morality·, and made them thought to be more capable of certainty and demonstration, is the following pair of differences.

First, ideas of quantity can be represented by perceptible marks that have a greater and nearer correspondence with them than any words or sounds whatsoever. Diagrams drawn on paper are copies of the ideas in the mind, and not liable to the uncertainty that words carry in their meanings. When an angle, circle, or square is drawn in lines, it lies open to the view, and can’t be mistaken. It remains unchangeable, and can be considered and examined at leisure, the proof looked over again, and every part of it scrutinised more than once without any danger of change in the ideas. This can’t happen with moral ideas. We have no perceptible marks that resemble them, but only words to express them by. And though the words, once they have been written, stay the same, the ideas they stand for may change in the same man, and they are usually different in different persons.

Secondly, moral ideas are commonly more complex than those of the figures ordinarily considered in mathematics, and from this two inconveniences follow. •The first is that their names are of more uncertain meaning, because the precise collection of simple ideas they stand for isn’t so easily agreed on; so that the sign that is always used for them in communication (and often in thinking too) fails to carry steadily with it the same idea. This leads to the sort of disorder, confusion, and error that would ensue if a man purporting to prove something about a heptagon left out one of its angles in making his diagram, or gave the figure one angle more than its name ordinarily imports and than he intended it to have when he first thought of his proof. This often happens, and is hardly avoidable, with very complex moral ideas, where people will use a single word with varying meanings, including at one time a simple idea (an angle, so to speak) which they omit later on. •Secondly, the complexity of moral ideas creates another inconvenience, namely that the mind can’t easily retain those precise combinations ·of simple ideas· as exactly and perfectly as is needed for the examination of the relations and correspondences, agreements or disagreements, of several of them with one another—especially when this has to be judged by long deductions and the intervention of other complex ideas to show the agreement or disagreement of two remote ones.

It is evident that mathematicians are greatly helped to avoid this by their use of diagrams which keeps the shapes they are studying fixed; without that help, their memory would often have great difficulty to retaining their arguments

209

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

so exactly while their mind went over the parts of them step by step. ·Help is also needed in arithmetic·. When someone does a long calculation—whether in addition, multiplication, or division—every part is only a progression of his mind, taking a view of its own ideas and considering their agreement or disagreement; and the bottom line of the calculation is just the result of the whole, made up of those clearly perceived particular relations. But if one didn’t record the various parts of the calculation by marks whose precise meanings are known, marks that last and remain in view when the memory would have let them go, it would be almost impossible to carry so many different ideas in the mind without confusing or dropping out some parts of the calculation, thereby making all our reasonings about it useless. These marks give the mind no help in perceiving the agreement of any two or more numbers, their equalities or proportions. The mind has that only through intuition of its own ideas of the numbers themselves. But the numerical marks are helps to the memory, to record and retain the various ideas that enter into the proof, enabling the man to know how far his intuitive knowledge has taken him, so that he may without confusion go on to what is yet unknown, and eventually have in one view before him the result of all his perceptions and reasonings.

20. One of the disadvantages in moral ideas—one that has led people to think that moral truths can’t be rigorously proved—can to a large extent be remedied by definitions, setting down the collection of simple ideas that each term is to stand for and then using the term steadily and constantly for that precise collection. And we can’t predict what methods algebra or something of that kind may some day suggest, to remove the other disadvantages. I am confident that if men would search for moral truths by the same methods as they search for mathematical truths, and with the same freedom from bias, they would find that moral truths •have a stronger connection one with another, •are more apt to follow necessarily from our clear and distinct ideas, and •come nearer to being perfectly demonstrable than is commonly thought. [Locke then expresses pessimism about the chances that this will happen much, because there is a shortage of intellectual honesty. He equates truth with beauty and falsehood with ugliness, defending this through a heavy-handed joke; then continues:] While the parties of men cram their beliefs down the throats of everyone they can get into their power, without allowing them to examine their truth or falsehood, and won’t let truth have a fair run for its money in the world or allow men the freedom to search for it, what improvements of this kind can be expected? What hope have we for greater light to shine in the moral sciences? In most places in the world, the part of mankind that lives in subjection ·of the kind I have been describing· would live in Egyptian darkness ·of the mind· along with the ·as-it-were·-Egyptian bondage ·of their bodies·, if it weren’t for the candle of the Lord that he has set up in men’s minds, a light that the breath or power of man cannot wholly extinguish.

21. As to the fourth sort of knowledge that we have, namely knowledge of the real actual existence of things: we have •an intuitive knowledge of our own existence, and •a demonstrative knowledge of the existence of a God, but of the existence of anything else we have only •sensitive knowledge, which is limited to objects that are present to our senses.

22. Our knowledge being so narrow (as I have shown), we may get more light on the present state of our minds if we look a little into the dark side, and survey our ignorance. This is infinitely larger than our knowledge, so ·it is all too

210

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

easy for us to stray into areas where our ignorance prevails·. It might help to quieten disputes and increase useful knowledge if we learned how far we have clear and distinct ideas, and on that basis confine our thoughts to things that are within the reach of our understandings. That would be better than launching out into that abyss of darkness where we have no eyes to see or faculties to grasp anything, out of a presumption that nothing is beyond our comprehension. To be convinced that such a presumption is foolish, we needn’t go far. If you know anything, you know first and foremost that you don’t have to look hard for instances of your ignorance. The lowliest and most obvious things that come our way have dark sides that the keenest sight can’t penetrate. The sharpest and broadest intellects of thinking men find themselves puzzled and at a loss concerning every particle of matter! We’ll be less surprised by this when we consider the causes of our ignorance. On the basis of what I have said, I think there are three causes:

First, lack of ideas.

Secondly, lack of a discoverable connection between the ideas we have.

Thirdly, failure to trace and examine our ideas.

23. First, there are many things that we are ignorant of because of a lack of ideas. ·My discussion of this will run to the end of section 27, with the present section on ideas that we can’t have, followed by four on ideas that we could but don’t have·. All our simple ideas are confined (as I have shown) to those we receive •from bodies through sensation, and •from the operations of our own minds through reflection. These few narrow inlets are disproportionate to the whole vast extent of what there is, as you will easily be brought to agree unless you are so foolish as to think that your span—·what you can experience and understand·—is the measure of all things. It isn’t for us to know what other simple ideas creatures in other parts of the universe may have, through senses and faculties that are more numerous or more perfect than ours, or just different. To think there are none such because we have no conception of them is like a blind man’s arguing that there is no such thing as sight and colours because he has no ideas of them. ignorance and darkness doesn’t block or limit the knowledge that others have, any more than the blindness of a mole is an argument against the sharp-sightedness of an eagle. If you think about the infinite power, wisdom, and goodness of the creator of all things, you will find reason to think that he didn’t expend it all on such an inconsiderable, lowly, and impotent a creature as you will find man to be—man, who in all probability is one of the lowest of all thinking beings. We simply don’t know what faculties other species of creatures have that enable them to penetrate into the nature and innermost constitutions of things, or what ideas they may get from things that are far different from ours. But we do know, having found out for sure, that we need more views of things than those we actually have if we are to make more complete discoveries of their natures. And we may be convinced that the ideas we can acquire through our faculties are very disproportionate to things themselves, when ·we consider that· a positive, clear, distinct idea of substance itself, which is the foundation of all the rest, is concealed from us. Because our lack of such ideas isn’t just a cause of our ignorance but a part of it, we can’t describe the missing ideas. But we can confidently say this much: the intellectual and sensible worlds—·that is, the realm of thought and the realm of bodies·—are perfectly alike in one thing, namely that the part that we see of each of them is tiny compared with what we don’t see, and the whole of what our thoughts or our senses tell us about each of them is,

211

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

compared with the rest, a point—almost nothing!

24. Another great cause of ignorance is the lack of ideas that we are capable of having. As •the lack of ideas that our faculties can’t give us shuts us off from the views of things that it is reasonable to think are had by other, more perfect beings, so •the lack of ideas that I am now discussing keeps us in ignorance of things we think of as knowable by us. Size, shape, and motion we do have ideas of; but we don’t know what is the particular size, shape, and motion of most of the bodies in the universe, which makes us ignorant of the various powers, mechanisms, and ways of operation through which the effects that we see daily are produced. These are hidden from us in some things by their being too remote, and in others by their being too small. When we consider the vast distance of the known and visible parts of the world, and the reasons we have to think that what lies within our ken is only a small part of the universe, we shall then discover a huge abyss of ignorance. A first glimpse of the great masses of matter that constitute the stupendous frame of the physical universe launches us into speculations in which our thoughts get lost:

What, in detail, are those great bodies made of?

How far do they extend?

How do they move?

What starts them moving? What keeps them moving?

What effects do they have on one another?

If we narrow our speculations, confining our thoughts to this little province—I mean this system of our sun and the planets that visibly move around it—what sorts of plants, animals, and thinking corporeal beings, infinitely different from those on our little spot of earth, may there probably be on other planets? But while we are confined to this earth we can know nothing about these, even of their outward shapes and parts, because there is no natural means, either by sensation or reflection, for certain ideas of them to enter our minds. They are out of the reach of those inlets of all our knowledge.

25. If by far the greatest part of the various kinds of bodies in the universe escape our notice by being too far away, there are others that are equally concealed from us by their smallness. These imperceptible corpuscles are the active parts of matter, and are the great instruments of nature on which depend not only all of bodies’ secondary qualities but also most of their natural operations. So our lack of precise distinct ideas of their primary qualities keeps us incurably ignorant of what we want to know about them. If we could discover the shape, size, texture, and motion of the minute constituent parts of any two bodies, we would know some of their operations on one another without putting them to the test, as we now know the properties of a square or a triangle. If we knew the mechanical structure of the particles of rhubarb, hemlock, opium, and a man, as a watch-maker knows the structure of a watch, we would be able to tell before-hand that rhubarb will purge, hemlock kill, and opium make a man sleep; as well as a watch-maker can tell that a little piece of paper laid on the balance will keep the watch from going.... The dissolving of silver in aqua fortis and gold in aqua regia, and not vice versa, would might then be no more difficult to know than it is for a locksmith to understand why this lock can be opened by this key and not by that one. But while we lack senses acute enough to discover the minute particles of bodies and to give us ideas of their fine structure, we must be content to be ignorant of their properties and ways of operation, being assured only of what we can learn from a few experiments. ·And what we can learn for sure in that way is limited indeed. We conduct

212

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

some experiments and get results·, but we can’t be certain that they will have the same results on future occasions. This blocks us from having certain knowledge of universal truths about natural bodies; and about these our reason carries us very little beyond particular matters of fact.

26. This inclines me to think that however far we get, through hard work, with practical and experimental science about physical things, we shan’t be able to get any knowledge of them that is scientific [= ‘rigorously organized, and united by high-level theories’.] That is because we lack perfect and adequate ideas of the very bodies that are nearest to us and most under our control. We have only very imperfect and incomplete ideas of the bodies that we have sorted into classes under names, and think ourselves best acquainted with. Perhaps we have •distinct ideas of the various sorts of bodies that we can examine through our senses, but I suspect that we don’t have •adequate ideas of any of them. ·See II.xxix and xxxi·. And though •the former of these serve us for everyday use and discourse, while we lack •the latter we can’t have scientific knowledge, and we’ll never be able to discover general, instructive, unquestionable truths concerning bodies. We mustn’t lay claim to certainty and demonstration in these matters. By the colour, shape, taste, smell, and other sensible qualities we have as clear and distinct ideas of sage and hemlock as we have of a circle and a triangle. But having no ideas of the particular primary qualities of the minute parts of either of these plants, nor of other bodies that we would apply them to, we can’t tell what effects they will produce; and when we see those effects, we can’t even guess—let alone know—how they are produced. Thus having no ideas of the particular mechanical structures of the minute parts of bodies that we can see and touch, we are ignorant of their constitutions, powers, and operations. Of more remote bodies we are even more ignorant, not even knowing their outward shapes or their large-scale structural features.

27. This shows us at a glance how disproportionate our knowledge is to the whole extent of material things. Now think about the infinitely many spirits that may and probably do exist; they are still further from our knowledge, and we can’t even form distinct ideas of their various kinds. From this we learn that the cause of ignorance now under discussion—·namely, lack of ideas·—conceals from us in an impenetrable obscurity almost the whole world of thinking things, which is certainly greater and more beautiful than the world of material things. We have a few superficial ideas of spirit that we get from ourselves through reflection, and then use as a basis for putting together the best idea we can manage of ·God·, the father of all spirits, the eternal independent author of them and us and all things; but apart from those few ideas we have no certain information even as to the existence of other spirits, except by revelation. Angels of all sorts are naturally beyond our discovery; and all those thinking beings of which there are likely to be more kinds than there are of bodily substances are things of which our natural faculties give us no certain account at all. From considering the words and actions of other people, every man has a reason to be satisfied that there are minds and thinking beings in other men as well as himself. And any thinking person must know, from his knowledge of his own mind, that there is a God (·see x·). But who can come to know, through his own search and ability, that there are different levels of spiritual beings between us and the great God? Much less do we have distinct ideas of the various natures, conditions, states, powers, and constitutions in respect of which they are like and unlike one another, and

213

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

like and unlike us. Concerning their different species and properties, therefore, we remain in absolute ignorance.

28. ·Of the three causes of ignorance listed at the end of section 22, we now come to the second, to which I shall devote two sections·. Another cause of ignorance, no less important than the first, is the lack of a discoverable connection between ideas that we do have. Whenever that is lacking, we are utterly incapable of universal and certain knowledge, and are, as with ignorance from lack of ideas, left only to observation and experiment; and we don’t have to be told how narrow and confined that is, and how far from general knowledge. I shall give a few instances of this cause of our ignorance, and then drop it. It is evident that the size, shape, and motion of various bodies in our environment produce various sensations in us, as of colours, sounds, tastes, smells, pleasure and pain, etc. These mechanical qualities of bodies have no affinity with the ideas they produce in us; there is no connection—that is, none we could know about just by thinking about it—between any impact of any sort of body ·on our sense organs· and any perception of a colour or smell that we find in our minds. So •all we can distinctly know about such operations is what we can learn from our experience, and •we can reason about them only as effects produced by the decree of an infinitely wise agent—a decree which utterly surpasses our comprehension. ·That is, we can’t reason about them in terms of necessary connections that we could grasp by thinking them through; for us they have to be matters of brute empirically discovered fact, set up by God for good reasons, no doubt, but not reasons that we know or understand·. So much for the bodily causes of our ideas of secondary qualities. On the other side, the operation of our minds on our bodies is equally far from being something we could know about just by thinking. The nature of our ideas can’t explain •how a thought could produce a motion, any more than it could explain •how a body could produce a thought. If experience didn’t convince us that thought does produce motion, we could never learn this just by thinking about thought and motion. These and their like do have a constant and regular connection in the ordinary course of things, but that connection can’t be found in the ideas themselves, which appear to have no necessary dependence one on another; so we have to attribute their connection to the free choice of God, who has created them and made them operate as they do, in a way that our weak understandings can’t conceive.

29. With some of our ideas there are certain relations and connections that are so visibly included in the nature of the ideas themselves that we can’t conceive of any power that could separate the ideas from those relations and connections. It is only with these ideas that we are capable of certain and universal knowledge. Thus the idea of a triangle necessarily carries with it equality of its angles to two right ones. We cannot conceive of this relation—this connection of these two ideas—to be changeable, or to depend on any arbitrary power that chose to make it thus but could have made it otherwise. But •the coherence and continuity of the parts of matter, •the production of sensation of colours and sounds etc. by impulse and motion, indeed •the basic rules governing the passing on of motion through impact—in none of this can we discover a natural connection with any ideas that we have; so we have to ascribe them to the arbitrary will and good pleasure of ·God·, the wise architect. (Presumably I needn’t mention the resurrection of the dead, the future state of the earth, and such other things, which everyone agrees depend wholly on the decisions of a ·divine· free agent.) When our observations show a certain regularity

214

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iii: Extent of human knowledge

in events, we can infer that the events unroll according to a law that has been set for them, but it’s a law that we don’t know. So: though causes work steadily, and effects constantly flow from them, we can’t find in our ideas what connects them and makes some depend on others; so our only knowledge of them has to come from experience. From all this it is easy to see what a darkness we are involved in, how little we can know about the things that exist. So we don’t insult our knowledge when we modestly think that we are so far from being •able to comprehend the whole nature of the universe that we aren’t •capable of a philosophical [= ‘scientific’] knowledge of the bodies in our environment and in ourselves.... In these matters we can go no further than particular experience informs us regarding matters of fact, and by analogy guess what effects similar bodies are likely to turn out to produce. But as to a perfect science of natural bodies (not to mention spiritual beings) we are, I think, so far from being capable of any such thing that it’s a waste of time to pursue it.

30. ·Now we come to the third of the causes of ignorance listed at the end of section 22·. Where we have adequate ideas, and where there is a certain and discoverable connection between them, we are nevertheless often ignorant because we don’t trace ideas that we have or could have, and because we don’t search out the intermediate ideas that could show us what relation of agreement or disagreement they have one with another. That is how many people are ignorant of mathematical truths—not through any imperfection in their faculties, or uncertainty in the subject-matter, but because they haven’t diligently acquired, examined, and suitably compared the relevant ideas. The principal cause of this, I think, has been the poor use of words. Men can’t truly seek or certainly discover the agreement or disagreement of ideas while their thoughts flutter about, or are bogged down in sounds that have doubtful and uncertain meanings. Mathematicians, by abstracting their thoughts from names and accustoming themselves to set before their minds the ideas themselves that they want to consider, have avoided much of that perplexity, muddle, and confusion that has so much hindered men’s progress in other branches of knowledge. For as long as they persist in using words with undetermined and uncertain meanings, they can’t sort their own opinions into true and false, certain and ·merely· probable, consistent and inconsistent. [The section continues with rhetorical exclamations against common intellectual failures generated by imperfect uses of language.]

31. Under the heading ‘the extent of human knowledge’ I have been discussing how far our knowledge extends across the various sorts of existing things. There is a different kind of ‘extent’ that it can also have, concerning how universal it is. Insofar as it is to be universal, it must follow the nature of our ideas ·rather than things existing outside us·. If we perceive the agreement or disagreement of ideas that are abstract, our knowledge is universal. For what is known of such general ideas will be true of every particular thing in whom that essence—i.e. that abstract idea—is to be found; and what is once known of such ideas will be perpetually and for ever true. For general knowledge, therefore, we must search only in our minds—we can get it only by examining our own ideas. Truths pertaining to •essences of things—that is, to abstract ideas—are eternal, and are to be discovered only by contemplating those essences; just as the •existence of things is to be known only from experience. I shall have more to say about this in the chapters where I shall speak of general and real knowledge—·vi and iv respectively·.

215

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iv: Reality of knowledge

Chapter iv: The reality of knowledge

1. I imagine that by now you’ll be apt to think that I have been building a castle in the air, and will want to offer me a challenge ·that runs to the end of this section·. What is the point of all this fuss? Knowledge, you say, is only the perception of the agreement or disagreement of our own ideas. But who knows what those ideas may be? Is there anything so extravagant as the imaginations of men’s brains? Where is the head that has no chimeras in it? Or if there is a sober and a wise man, what difference will there be, by your rules, between his knowledge and that of the most extravagant fancy in the world? They both have their ideas, and perceive their agreements and disagreements with one another. If these two men differ, the advantage will be on the side of the man with a hot imagination: he has more ideas, and livelier ones, than the other, and so by your rules he will be the more knowing of the two! If it is true that all knowledge lies only in the perception of the agreement or disagreement of our own ideas, •the visions of a fanatic and •the reasonings of a sober man will be equally certain. It doesn’t matter how things are; as long as a man observes the agreements in his own imaginings, and talks accordingly, it is all truth, all certainty. Such castles in the air will be strongholds of truth, as secure as the demonstrations of Euclid. That a harpy is not a centaur is by these standards as certain an item of knowledge, and as much a truth, as that a square is not a circle. But what use is all this fine knowledge of men’s own imaginings to someone enquiring into the reality of things? It doesn’t matter what men’s fancies are; only the knowledge of things should be prized. What gives value to our reasonings, and makes one man’s knowledge preferable to another’s, is its concerning things as they really are, not dreams and fancies.

2. To this I answer that if our knowledge of our ideas were to terminate in them, and to reach no further when something further is intended, our most serious thoughts would indeed be of little more use than the dreams of a crazy brain. But I hope to make it evident that this route to certainty, through the knowledge of our own ideas, goes a little further than bare imagination; and I believe it will appear that all the certainty that we have of general truths lies in nothing else.

3. Obviously the mind knows things not •immediately but only •through the intervention of its ideas of them. So our knowledge is real only to the extent that our ideas conform to the reality of things. But what shall be the criterion for this? How shall the mind, which perceives nothing but its own ideas, know that they agree with things themselves? This seems like a hard thing to discover; but I think there are two sorts of ideas that we can be sure do agree with things.

4. The first are simple ideas. Since the mind (as I have shown) can’t make these by itself, they must necessarily result from things operating on the mind in a natural way, and producing in it those perceptions that the wisdom and will of our maker ordains them to be adapted to. From this it follows that simple ideas aren’t fictions of our imaginations, but the natural and regular productions of things outside us, really operating on us; and so they carry with them all the conformity that is intended, and all that our state requires. They represent things to us under those appearances that they are fitted to produce in us; and that lets us distinguish the sorts of particular substances, to discern the states they are in, and so to handle them in ways appropriate to

216

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iv: Reality of knowledge

our needs. Thus the idea of whiteness in the mind exactly corresponds to the power in a body to produce it there, and that gives it all the real conformity it can have, and all it ought to have, with things outside us. This conformity between our simple ideas and the existence of things is sufficient for real knowledge.

5. Secondly, all our complex ideas except those of substances are archetypes of the mind’s own making, not intended to be the copies of anything or to have originated from anything; so they can’t lack any conformity that is needed for real knowledge. Something that isn’t designed to represent anything but itself can’t ever represent wrongly, or lead us into error about something by being unlike it; and all our complex ideas are like that, except those of substances. [The remainder of the section continues with this theme, repeating things already said in II.xxxii.13–14.]

6. I expect it will be easily granted that our knowledge of mathematical truths is not only certain but real—not the mere empty vision of meaningless chimeras of the brain. And yet if we think about it we shall find that it is only about our own ideas. The mathematician considers the properties of a rectangle or circle only as they are in idea [= ‘as ideas’, or = ‘as they are represented by ideas’] in his own mind. For he may never in his life have found a precise circle or rectangle. Yet the knowledge he has of the properties of a circle or of any other mathematical figure are nevertheless true and certain, even of real existing things; because the •real things that such propositions refer to are •things that really agree to the archetypes in his mind. Is it true of his idea of a triangle that its three angles are equal to two right ones? ·If so, then· it is true also of a triangle, wherever it really exists. An existing figure that doesn’t exactly conform to that idea of a triangle in his mind is irrelevant to that proposition. And so he is certain that all his knowledge about such ideas is real knowledge: because he is referring to things only so far as they agree with those ideas of his, he is sure that what he knows concerning •those figures when they have a merely ‘ideal’ existence in his mind will also hold true of •things that have real existence in the world of matter....

7. It follows from this that moral knowledge is as capable of real certainty as mathematics. For certainty is just the perception of the agreement or disagreement of our ideas; and demonstrating something is just perceiving such agreement through the intervention of other intermediate ideas; so our moral ideas, which resemble mathematical ones in being archetypes themselves and therefore being adequate and complete, resemble them also in having agreements and disagreements that yield real knowledge.

8. To attain knowledge and certainty we have to have •determined ideas [= ‘ideas that are distinct and settled’]; and, to make our knowledge real we need to have •ideas that match their archetypes. Don’t be surprised that I place the certainty of our knowledge in the consideration of our ideas, with so little care and regard (apparently) for the real existence of things. The thoughts and disputes of those who claim to make it their business to enquire after truth and certainty are mainly directed at general propositions and notions in which existence is not at all concerned. The discourses of the mathematicians about the squaring of a circle, conic sections, or any other part of mathematics, don’t concern the existence of any of those figures; their demonstrations, which depend on their ideas, are the same whether or not there is any square or circle existing in the world. In the same manner the truth and certainty of moral discourses abstracts from the lives of men, and from the existence in the world of the virtues they discuss.... If it is true in

217

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iv: Reality of knowledge

speculation, i.e. in idea, that murder deserves death, it will also be true in reality of any actual action that conforms to the idea of murder....

9. You may object: ‘If moral knowledge is placed in the contemplation of our own moral ideas, and if those ideas (like all modes) are of our own making, what strange notions will there be of justice and temperance? What confusion of virtues and vices if everyone can make what ideas of them he pleases?’ I reply that there will be no confusion or disorder in the things themselves, or in the reasonings about them, ·if different people have different ideas of justice, temperance, or the like·; any more than in mathematics the proofs would be spoiled, or the properties and relations of the figures changed, if someone made a ‘triangle’ with four corners, or a ‘trapezium’ with four right angles. What such a man would be doing—to put it in plain English—is changing the names of the figures, calling by one name a figure that mathematicians ordinarily call by another. Let a man make the idea of a figure with three angles of which one is a right angle, and call it anything he pleases—the properties of that idea and the proofs about it will be the same as if he had called it ‘right-angled triangle’. I admit that changing the name, because it is an impropriety of speech, will at first disturb someone who doesn’t know what idea the name stands for; but as soon as the figure is drawn the consequences and demonstration are plain and clear. The same holds for moral knowledge. [Locke gives an example, He also remarks that misusing words in moral discourses is apt to cause ‘more disorder’ than it would in mathematics, because in the former we don’t have diagrams to help us out. He continues:] But despite all this, labelling any of those ·moral· ideas in a manner contrary to the usual meanings of the words of the language in question doesn’t prevent us from having certain and demonstrative knowledge of their various agreements and disagreements....

10. Where God or some other law-maker has defined a moral name, he has thereby created the essence of the species to which that name applies, and in such a case it is not safe to apply or use the word in any other way. In other cases it is merely an improper use of language to give a word a meaning other than that of the common usage of the country. And when this happens, it doesn’t disturb the certainty of the knowledge that we can still have by contemplating and inter-relating ideas, even misnamed ones.

11. ·After two kinds of idea that we may be sure agree with things, we come to·: complex ideas of a third sort which, because they relate to archetypes outside us, may differ from their archetypes, in which case our knowledge about them falls short of being real. Such are our ideas of substances: they consist of collections of simple ideas supposedly taken from the works of nature, but they may vary from reality by containing more or different ideas than are to be found united in the things themselves. That is how they can and often do fail to conform exactly to things themselves.

12. For reality of knowledge concerning modes, all we need (I repeat) is to put together ideas that aren’t inconsistent with one another, even if they have never before existed in that combination. The ideas of sacrilege and perjury etc. were as real and true ideas before any such acts occurred as they are now. But our ideas of substances are supposed to copy archetypes outside us, so they must be taken from something that exists or has existed. They mustn’t consist of ideas put together at the pleasure of our thoughts without being based on any real pattern, even if we can see no inconsistency in such a combination. Here is why. We don’t know what real constitution of substances it is on which our

218

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iv: Reality of knowledge

simple ideas depend, and which is the real cause for some of them to be united and others excluded; so there are very few ·collections of qualities· that we can be sure are, or are not, inconsistent in nature, any further than experience and empirical observation reach. So the reality of our knowledge about substances is based on our having complex ideas of them that are true, i.e. made up of such simple ones as have been discovered to co-exist in nature. Such ideas, even when they aren’t very exact copies, are still the basis for such real knowledge of substances as we have. I have shown that we don’t have much of it; still, as far as it goes it is real knowledge. Whatever ideas we have, the agreement we find them to have with others will still be knowledge. If the ideas are abstract it is general knowledge.... Whatever simple ideas have been found to co-exist in any substance we can confidently join together again, and so make abstract ideas of substances. For whatever once had a union in nature may be united again.

13. We would think of things with greater freedom and less confusion than perhaps we do, if we didn’t let words confine our thoughts and abstract ideas, as though there couldn’t be any sorts of things other than the ones that have already been named. ·Here is an example of such confinement, and of release from it·. It might be thought a bold paradox, if not a very dangerous falsehood, if I should say that some changelings who have lived forty years together without any appearance of reason are something between a man and a beast. [In Locke’s time ‘changeling’ was a label for anyone whose congenital deficits include a level of intelligence too low for speech to be learned.] In saying this I am opposing a prejudice that is based purely on the false supposition that ‘man’ and ‘beast’ stand for distinct species that have been set out by real essences in such a way that no other species can come between them. The idea of the shape, motion, and life of a man without reason is as much a distinct idea, and makes as much a distinct sort of things from man and beast, as the idea of the shape of an ass with reason would be different from either that of man or beast, and be a species of an animal distinct from both. To see this, we need to abstract from those names and from the supposition of specific essences made by nature wherein all things with the same name exactly and equally partake, and stop thinking that there is a certain number of these essences in which all things have been formed, as though poured into moulds.

14. You will now want to ask: ‘If changelings may be supposed to be something between man and beast, what are they?’ I answer, changelings; which is as good a word to signify something different from the meaning of ‘man’ or ‘beast’ as those two names are to have meanings different one from the other. [Locke goes on to say that this ought to be the end of the matter, but that his chosen example gets people’s hackles up for religious reasons, so he will discuss it some more. The way we classify the changeling, he says in section 15, will be thought by some to have implications for the changeling’s chances of eternal life; but this is wrong. If it is based on the idea that the changeling is entitled to immortality because it/he has a rational soul, as shown by its/his human shape, Locke has a sharp reply.] To conclude that there is a rational soul in a changeling because he has the outside of a rational creature, though his actions throughout his life carry far fewer marks of reason than can be found in many a beast, is no more reasonable that to conclude that a human corpse, which gives no more appearance or action of life than does a statue, nevertheless has a living soul in it because of its shape.

219

Essay IV John Locke Chapter iv: Reality of knowledge

16. ‘But the changeling is born of rational parents, and must therefore have a rational soul.’ What logic are you following here? It isn’t one that is generally accepted, for if people accepted it they wouldn’t be so bold, as everywhere they are, as to destroy ill-formed and mis-shaped productions. ‘Yes, but the ones they destroy are monsters.’ Let them be so; then what will your drivelling, unintelligent, ineducable changeling be? Shall a defect in the body make a monster; while a defect in the mind does not (even though the mind is the more noble, and in common parlance the more essential, part)? Shall the lack of a nose or a neck make a monster and put the creature out of the rank of men, when the lack of reason and understanding does not? [The section continues with renewed criticisms of the view that bodily shape indicates whether a creature has a rational soul. Locke raises slippery-slope difficulties, which he sums up in this general comment:] I would gladly know what are those precise bodily features which according to this hypothesis are, and those which are not, capable of having a rational soul joined to them. What sort of outside is the certain sign that there is, or that there isn’t, such an inhabitant within? For until that is established we talk at random of ‘man’. [The section concludes with a reminder of Locke’s main interest in all this, namely to show the troubles that come from ‘the common notion of species and essences’.]

17. I have mentioned this here because I think we need to be extremely careful not to be imposed on by words, or by ‘species’ in our ordinary notions of them. For I am inclined to think that there lies one great obstacle to clear and distinct knowledge, especially about substances, and from there have arisen many of the difficulties about truth and certainty. If we regularly separated our thoughts and reasonings from words we might remedy much of this inconvenience within our own thoughts; but our discourse with others would still be disturbed if we retained the opinion that species and their essences were anything but our abstract ideas (such as they are) with names annexed to them.

18. Wherever we perceive the agreement or disagreement of any of our ideas, there is certain knowledge. Wherever we are sure those ideas agree with the reality of things, there is certain real knowledge. I think I have shown what certainty, real certainty, consists in, by showing the marks of agreement between our ideas and the reality of things. Whether or not it has mattered to anyone else, showing what real certainty consists in was one of the things that I thought there was a great need for, a need that I wanted to meet.

220

Essay IV John Locke Chapter v: Truth in general

Chapter v: Truth in general

1. What is truth? was an enquiry many ages ago [by Pontius Pilate—John 18:38]; and truth is what all mankind search for, or say they do; so it must be worth our while to examine carefully what it consists in, and to learn enough about its nature to see how the mind distinguishes truth from falsehood.

2. ‘Truth’ then seems to me, in the proper sense of the word, to signify nothing but the joining or separating of signs according to whether the things signified agree or disagree one with another. The joining or separating of signs that I am talking about here is what by another name we call ‘proposition’. So that truth properly belongs only to propositions. There are two sorts of these, namely mental and verbal, corresponding to the two sorts of signs that we commonly use, namely ideas and words.

3. To form a clear notion of truth, we have to consider truth of thought and truth of words separately from one another. But it’s hard to do this because in treating of mental propositions we inevitably use words, so that when we give an example of a mental proposition it immediately stops being barely mental and becomes verbal. A mental proposition is nothing but a bare consideration of the ideas as they are in our minds, stripped of names; so it loses the nature of a purely mental proposition as soon as it is put into words.

4. What makes it even harder to deal with mental and verbal propositions separately is that most (if not all) men use words instead of ideas ·even· in their private thinking and reasonings, at least when they are thinking about something that involves complex ideas. This is a pointer to the imperfection and uncertainty of our complex ideas, and it can, if we carefully make good use of it, serve as a mark to show us what things we have clear and perfect established ideas of, and what not. For if we carefully observe how our mind goes about thinking and reasoning, I think we shall find that when we make propositions within our own thoughts about white or black, sweet or bitter, a triangle or a circle, we often frame in our minds the ideas themselves, without reflecting on their names. But when we want to make propositions about more complex ideas—for example man, vitriol, fortitude, glory—we usually put the name in place of the idea. That is because •the ideas these names stand for are mostly imperfect, confused, and undetermined, leading us to reflect instead on •the names, because they are more clear, certain, and distinct, and come more readily to mind than the pure ideas do. And so we employ these words instead of the ideas themselves, even when we want to meditate and reason within ourselves, silently making mental propositions. As I have already noted, what leads us to do this when thinking about •substances is the imperfection of our ideas: we make the name stand for the real essence, of which we have no idea at all. In the case of •modes, it—·i.e. substituting names for ideas·—is brought about by the great number of simple ideas that make them up. Where many simple ideas are compounded into one complex one, the name comes to mind much more easily than the complex idea itself does. The idea •requires time and attention to be recollected and exactly represented to the mind, even for •people have taken trouble to do this on previous occasions; and it •can’t be done at all by those who, though they have at their command most of the common words of their language, •may never once in all their lives have troubled themselves to

221

Essay IV John Locke Chapter v: Truth in general

consider what precise ideas most of those words stand for.... Those who talk on and on about ‘religion’ and ‘conscience’, ‘church’ and ‘faith’, ‘power’ and ‘right’, ‘obstructions’ and ‘humours’, ‘melancholy’ and ‘choler’, might have little left in their thoughts and meditations if we could persuade them to think only of •the things themselves, and set aside •the words with which they so often confused others—and often enough confused themselves too!

5. But to return to the consideration of truth: we must, I say, observe two sorts of propositions that we can make. First, mental propositions, in which the ideas in our understandings are put together (or separated) by the mind that perceives or judges concerning their agreement (or disagreement)—all without the use of words. Secondly, verbal propositions: these are ·made up of· words, the signs of our ideas, which are put together (or separated) in affirmative (or negative) sentences. By affirming or denying in this way, these audible signs are as it were put together or separated from one another. So that proposition consists in joining or separating signs, and truth consists in putting them together or separating them according as the things they stand for agree or disagree.

6. Your experience will satisfy you that your mind, by perceiving or supposing the agreement or disagreement of any of its ideas, does silently put them into a kind of affirmative or negative proposition. I have tried to describe this process using the terms ‘putting together’ and ‘separating’; but this action of the mind, which is so familiar to every thinking and reasoning man, is easier to •conceive by reflecting on what happens in us when we affirm or deny than it is to •explain in words. When a man has in his head the idea of two lines, specifically the side and diagonal of a square of which the diagonal is an inch long, he may have the idea also of the division of that diagonal line into a certain number of equal parts—into five, ten, a hundred, a thousand, or any other number—and may have the idea of that one-inch line’s being divisible (or of its not being divisible) into equal parts such that a certain number of them will be equal to the line making the side of the square. Now whenever he perceives, believes, or supposes •such a kind of divisibility to agree or disagree with •his idea of that line, he (so to speak) joins or separates •the idea of that line and •the idea of that kind of divisibility; and in so doing he makes a mental proposition, which is true or false depending on whether or not such a kind of divisibility really does agree with that line. When ideas are put together or separated in the mind according as they or the things they stand for do agree or not, that is mental truth, as I call it. But truth of words is something more, namely affirming or denying words one of another, according as the ideas they stand for agree or disagree. This again is of two kinds: either •purely verbal and trifling, which I shall speak of in chapter viii; or •real and instructive, which is the object of the real knowledge that I have already discussed.

7. Here again the doubt that arose about knowledge will be apt to re-arise about truth. The following objection will be raised (·it runs to the end of the section·): If truth is nothing but the joining and separating of words in propositions, according as the ideas they stand for agree or disagree in men’s minds, the knowledge of truth is not so valuable as it is taken to be, and not worth the time and trouble men employ in the search of it; for by this account it amounts merely to the conformity of words to the chimeras of men’s brains. Everyone knows what odd notions many men’s heads are filled with, and what strange ideas all men’s brains are capable of! But if we stop at that, all we know

222

Essay IV John Locke Chapter v: Truth in general

by this rule is the truth of the visionary world of our own imaginations—truth that may as well concern •harpies and centaurs as men and horses. For •those and their like may be ideas in our heads, and agree or disagree there, and so have propositions made about them that are as true as ones involving ideas of real beings. And it will be every bit as true to say All centaurs are animals as that All men are animals, and the certainty of one proposition will be as great as that of the other. For in both propositions the words are put together according to the agreement of the ideas in our minds; and the agreement of the idea of animal with that of centaur is as clear and visible to the mind as its agreement with the idea of man; and so these two propositions are equally true, equally certain. But what use is that sort of truth to us?

8. What I have said in chapter iv to divide knowledge into real and imaginary might suffice here, in answer to this doubt, to divide truth into real truth and chimerical or (if you please) merely nominal truth; for the two distinctions rest on the same foundation. But it may be appropriate here again to bear in mind that though our words signify nothing but our •ideas, they are designed by us to signify •things; so the truth they contain, when put into propositions, will be only verbal when they stand for ideas in the mind that don’t agree with the reality of things. And therefore truth as well as knowledge may be divided into verbal and real; where merely verbal truth is what we have that when terms are joined according to the agreement or disagreement of the ideas they stand for, without regard for whether our ideas ·represent things that· really do or could have an existence in nature. We have real truth when these signs are joined according as our ideas agree, and ·things corresponding to· our ideas can exist in nature—which with substances we can’t know except by knowing that such have existed.

9. Truth is marking down in words the agreement or disagreement of ideas as it is. Falsehood is the marking down in words the agreement or disagreement of ideas otherwise than it is. And so far as these ideas, thus marked by sounds, agree to their archetypes, to that extent the truth is real. The knowledge of this truth consists in •knowing what ideas the words stand for and •perceiving the agreement or disagreement of those ideas according as it is marked by those words.

10. Because words are looked on as the great channels of truth and knowledge, and because in conveying and receiving truth (and often in reasoning about it) we use words and propositions, I shall look further into the certainty of real truths contained in propositions—asking what it consists in and where it can be found—and I’ll try to show what sort of universal propositions we can be certain of the real truth or falsehood of. I shall begin with general propositions, these being the ones that most employ our thoughts. The mind mainly pursues general truths, because they are the ones that enlarge our knowledge the most, and through their comprehensiveness satisfy us of many particulars at once, enlarge our view, and shorten our way to knowledge. ·They will be my topic in chapter vi·.

11. Besides truth taken in the strict sense I have discussed, there are ·two· other sorts of ‘truths’. Moral truth is speaking of things according to the persuasion of our own minds, though the proposition we utter doesn’t agree with the reality of things. Metaphysical truth is nothing but the real existence of things, in conformity with the ideas to which we have annexed their names. This may seem to consist in the very being of things ·rather than in truth about them·; but on closer inspection it turns out to include a silent proposition in which the mind joins that particular thing to a certain

223

Essay IV John Locke Chapter v: Truth in general

idea—the idea the mind had previously assigned to the thing along with a name for it. These ·two further· points about truth have either been discussed earlier or are not much to our present purpose, which is why I merely mention them in passing.

224

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vi: Universal propositions

Chapter vi: Universal propositions, their truth and certainty

1. The best and surest way to get clear and distinct knowledge is through examining and judging ideas by themselves, setting their names aside entirely; but because of the prevailing custom of using sounds in place of ideas, this ‘best way’ is very seldom followed. Everyone can see how common it is for names to be used instead of the ideas themselves, even when men ·don’t need words for communicative purposes, because they· are thinking and reasoning in their own heads. This happens especially when the ideas are very complex, and made up of a large collection of simple ones. This makes the consideration of words and propositions so necessary a part of the topic of knowledge that it is very hard to speak intelligibly of it without explaining them.

2. All our knowledge is either of particular truths or of general ones. I here set aside the former of these. The latter—general truths—are what we (for good reasons) mostly seek after. They can never be well known, and can very seldom be grasped at all, except as conceived and expressed in words. So it isn’t out of our way, in examining our knowledge, to enquire into the truth and certainty of universal propositions—·I’m talking about verbal propositions, not mental ones·.

3. The doubtfulness of terms is a danger everywhere, including here—·where the term ‘certainty’ could trip us up·. So I need to explain that certainty is twofold: there is certainty of truth and certainty of knowledge. •Certainty of truth occurs when words are put together in propositions in such a way as to express, exactly and accurately, the agreement or disagreement of the ideas they stand for. To have •certainty of knowledge is to perceive the agreement or disagreement of ideas, as expressed in a proposition. This we usually call ‘knowing’ (or ‘being certain of’) the truth of a proposition.

4. We can’t be certain of the truth of any general proposition unless we know the precise extent of the species its terms stand for; so we have to know the essence of each species, which is what constitutes the species and sets its boundaries. With simple ideas and modes this isn’t hard to do. For in these the •real and •nominal essence are the same; or—to put the same thing in other words—the abstract idea that the general term stands for is the •only essence (and sets the only boundary) that the species can be supposed to have; so that there can be no doubt about how far the species extends, or what things fall under each term—namely, all and only things that exactly fit the idea the general term stands for.

But in the case of substances, where the species is supposed to be constituted, fixed, and bounded by a •real essence distinct from the •nominal one, the extent of the general word is very uncertain. That’s because we don’t know this real essence, so we can’t know what does and what doesn’t belong to that species, or, therefore, what may and what may not be affirmed of it with certainty. Speaking of a man, or gold, or any other species of natural substances, as supposedly constituted by a precise and real essence that nature regularly imparts to every individual of that kind, making it belong to that species, we can’t be certain of the truth of any affirmation or negation made of it. For ‘man’ and ‘gold’, taken in this way as naming species of things constituted by real essences that differ from the complex idea in the mind of the speaker, stand for....we don’t know

225

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vi: Universal propositions

what they stand for! And the extent of these species, with such boundaries, are so unknown and unsettled that we can’t with any certainty affirm that all men are rational, or that all gold is yellow. But where the nominal essence is kept to as the boundary of each species, and men apply a general term only to particular things in which is found the complex idea the term stands for, there’s no danger of mistaking the boundaries of each species and no doubt about whether any given proposition is true. I have chosen to explain this uncertainty of propositions in the scholastic terminology of ‘essences’ and ‘species’ so as to bring out the absurdity and inconvenience of thinking of them as anything but abstract ideas with names attached. [The section concludes with a defence of this choice: it might make things needlessly difficult for people who aren’t ‘possessed with scholastic learning’, but so many are tainted with it that it seemed best to try to rescue them from their mistakes.]

5. When the names of substances are made to stand for species that are supposed to be based on unknown real essences, they can’t be used to convey certainty to the understanding. How can we be sure that this or that quality is in gold, when we don’t know what is and what isn’t gold? Since in this way of speaking nothing is gold except what partakes of an essence that we don’t know, we can’t be sure whether any bit of matter in the world is gold, because we are incurably ignorant about whether it has that which ·supposedly· entitles anything to be called ‘gold’, namely that real essence of which we have no idea.... And even if we did (which is impossible) know for sure which bits of matter are gold by this standard, i.e. which have the real essence that we don’t know, still we couldn’t be sure that this or that quality could with truth be affirmed of gold ·in general·, because we couldn’t know that this or that quality or idea has a necessary connection with a real essence of which we have no idea at all.

6. On the other hand, when the names of substances are used properly, for the ideas men have in their minds, though this enables them to have clear and determinate meanings it doesn’t provide us with many universal propositions of whose truth we can be certain. Not because we are uncertain about what things are signified by them (·because in this use of them we are not·), but because the complex ideas they stand for are combinations of simple ones that have very few discoverable connections or inconsistencies with other ideas.

7. The complex ideas that our names of the species of substances properly stand for are collections of such qualities as have been observed to co-exist in an unknown substratum that we call ‘substance’. But what other qualities necessarily co-exist with such combinations we can’t know for sure unless we can discover their natural dependence. With primary qualities we can know very little of this, and in all the secondary qualities we can discover no connection at all, for the reasons mentioned in chapter iii. [Locke then repeats what he said in iii.13, concluding thus:] And so we can have doubt-free certainty about very few general propositions concerning substances.

[Sections 8–9 illustrate this thesis of Locke’s with examples concerning gold. It is widely believed that All gold is fixed (that is, not easily volatilized), but if fixedness isn’t part of the complex idea defining ‘gold’, then we can’t know that all gold is fixed; we can’t connected fixedness with the nominal essence of gold directly, for it has no discoverable connection with that complex idea; and we can’t connect it via the supposed real essence, because we don’t know what that is and so can’t know what connections it enters into. And if (section 9) ‘fixed’ is included in the complex idea defining

226

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vi: Universal propositions

‘gold’, then indeed we do know for certain that all gold is fixed, but this is now an uninteresting truth on a par with A centaur is four-footed.]

10. By putting more co-existing qualities into one complex idea under one name, we make the meaning of the word in question more precise and determinate, but we don’t increase its ability to yield universal certainty regarding other qualities that are not contained in our complex idea. That’s because we don’t perceive their connection or dependence on one another, being ignorant both of •the real constitution in which they are all founded, and also of •how they flow from that constitution. For the main part of our knowledge about substances is not, as with other things, merely •knowledge of the relation between two ideas that could exist separately; rather, it is •knowledge of the necessary connection and co-existence of several distinct ideas [here = ‘qualities’] in the same subject, or of the impossibility of their co-existing in that way. If we could begin at the other end, and discover what a given colour consists in, what makes a body lighter or heavier, what texture of parts makes it malleable, fusible, fixed, and soluble in this sort of liquid and not in that—if we had an idea like this of bodies, we might form abstract ideas of them that would be a basis for more general knowledge, and enable us to make universal propositions that carried truth and certainty with them. But while our complex ideas of the sorts of substances are so remote from that internal real constitution on which their sensible qualities depend, and are made up of merely an imperfect collection of apparent qualities that our senses can discover; there can be few general propositions concerning substances of whose real truth we can be certainly assured, because there are so few simple ideas of whose connection and necessary co-existence we can have certain and undoubted knowledge.

Among all the secondary qualities of substances and the powers relating to them, I don’t think we can name any two whose necessary co-existence or impossibility of co-existence we can certainly know (except for pairs belonging to the same sense, which necessarily exclude one another, as I have shown elsewhere). No-one, I think, given a body’s colour, can certainly know what smell, taste, sound, or tangible qualities it has, or what alterations it can make in or receive from other bodies. The same holds for sound, or taste, and so on. Since our specific names of substances stand for collections of just such ideas, it is no wonder that we can very seldom use them in general propositions of undoubted real certainty. Still, when the complex idea of a sort of substance contains a simple idea whose necessary co-existence with some idea other can be discovered, then a universal proposition can with certainty be made concerning it: for example, if we discovered a necessary connection between malleableness and the colour or weight of gold (or any other part of the complex idea signified by ‘gold’), we could make a certain universal proposition concerning gold in this respect; and the real truth of this proposition, ‘All gold is malleable’, would be as certain as the real truth of ‘The three angles of any triangle are equal to two right angles’.

11. If we had ideas of substances that let us know •what real constitutions produce the sensible qualities we find in them, and •how the latter qualities flowed from those constitutions, we could find out their properties [= ‘qualities that every member of a species must possess’] more certainly than we can now through our senses. In that case, we could know the properties of gold without making experiments on it—indeed without there being any such stuff as gold in existence—just as we can know the properties of a triangle without appealing to any triangle that exists in the physical world; the idea in our

227

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vi: Universal propositions

minds would serve for the gold as well as it does for the triangle. But we are so far from being admitted into the secrets of nature that we hardly ever get close to starting to enter into them. ·Here are some of the reasons for the great gap between what we know and what there is to be known·.

We usually consider each substance that we meet with as an entire thing on its own, having all its qualities in itself and independently of other things. This leads us to overlook most of the operations of invisible fluids in which they are immersed—fluids whose motions and operations influence most of the qualities that we observe in substances and make our basis for classifying and naming them. Put a piece of gold anywhere by itself, separated from the influence of all other bodies, and it will immediately lose its colour and weight and (for all I know to the contrary) its malleableness too. Water, whose fluidity is to us an essential quality, would if left to itself cease to be fluid.

And if •inanimate bodies owe so much of their present state to other bodies outside them that their appearance would be changed if those other bodies were removed, it is even more so with •plants, that are nourished, grow, and produce leaves, flowers, and seeds in a constant succession—·all in dependence on their environment·. And if we look a little more closely into the state of •animals we shall find that they depend—for life, motion, and the main qualities to be observed in them—wholly on outer causes and qualities of other bodies, so much so that they can’t survive for a moment without them. Yet we ignore those other bodies, and don’t bring them into the complex ideas we form of those animals. Take the air for just a minute from the most living creatures and they quickly lose sense, life, and motion. knowledge of this has been forced on us by our need to breathe. But how many other external (and possibly very distant) bodies do the springs of these admirable ·living· machines depend on—bodies that aren’t commonly observed, or even thought of? And how many such bodies are there that can never be discovered by the most thorough enquiry? The inhabitants of this spot in the universe, though many millions of miles from the sun, nevertheless depend so much on the suitably damped-down movements of particles coming from it, or agitated by it, that if this earth were moved to a position just a little further from or nearer to that source of heat, probably most of the animals on earth would immediately perish. ·The evidence for this is that· we often find that animals are destroyed when their place on our little globe exposes them to too much or too little of the sun’s warmth. The ·magnetic· qualities observed in a loadstone must have their source far beyond the confines of that body. [Locke was sure of that because he was sure that there are no forces of attraction.] Various sorts of animals are ravaged by invisible causes: some, we are told, meet certain death just by crossing the equator; others certainly die if they are moved into a neighbouring country. All this shows that for these animals to be what they appear to us to be, and to retain the qualities by which we recognize them, they require the concurrence and operations of various bodies that are ordinarily thought to have nothing to do with them.

So we are thoroughly off-course when we think that things contain within themselves the qualities that appear to us in them; and it is no use our searching for that constitution within the body of a fly, or of an elephant, which gives rise to the qualities and powers we observe in them. To understand them properly we may even have to look not only beyond our earth and atmosphere but even beyond the sun or the remotest star our eyes have yet discovered. We can’t determine the extent to which the existence and operation of particular substances on our planet depends on causes that are utterly beyond our view. We perceive some of the

228

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vi: Universal propositions

movements and large-scale operations of things here around us; but as for the streams ·of matter or influence or whatever· that keep all these curious machines in motion and in repair, we haven’t the least notion of where they come from or how they are conveyed and what form they take. For all we know to the contrary, it may be that the great parts and wheels (so to speak) of this stupendous structure of the universe are so connected and inter-dependent in their influences and operations that things in our locality would put on quite another face, and cease to be what they are, if some one of the incomprehensibly remote stars were to cease to move as it does. This is certain: however self-sufficient things seem to be in themselves, they are indebted to other parts of nature for the features of them that we attend to most. Their observable qualities, actions, and powers are due to something outside them; we know of no part of nature that is so complete and perfect that it doesn’t owe its existence and its excellences to its neighbours; if we want to understand the qualities of any body, we mustn’t let its surface mark the boundary of our thoughts—we need to look much further out than that.

[Section 12 rams home the conclusion that we know almost nothing of the real essences of substances. Even apart from our ignorance of distant bodies that may be relevant, ‘we can’t even discover the size, shape, and texture of substances’ minute and active parts’.]

13. So we shouldn’t wonder that very few general propositions about substances are certain; our knowledge of their qualities and properties seldom goes further than our senses reach. Enquiring and observant men may by strength of judgment penetrate further, and, on probabilities taken from wary observation and well-assembled hints, guess correctly at what experience hasn’t yet revealed to them. But this is still just guessing; it is only opinion, and hasn’t the certainty that is needed for knowledge. For all general knowledge lies only in our own thoughts, consisting merely in the contemplation of our own abstract ideas. [The rest of this section develops the point: we don‘t have ideas of substances that can support genuine knowledge about them.]

14. Before we can have any tolerable knowledge of this kind, we must know first

•what changes the primary qualities of one body regularly produce in the primary qualities of another, and how;

and secondly

•what primary qualities of bodies produce certain sensations or ideas in us.

Knowing all this is knowing all the effects of matter in its different conditions of size, shape, cohesion of parts, motion and rest! I think everyone will agree that we can’t possibly have that knowledge unless it comes to us through ·divine· revelation. Furthermore, even if God revealed to us •what sort of shape, size, and motion of corpuscles can produce in us the sensation of a yellow colour, and •what sort of shape, size, and texture on the surface of any body can give such corpuscles the motion appropriate for producing that colour, that still wouldn’t be enough to enable us to know with certainty any universal propositions about the various sorts of bodies. For such knowledge we would also need to have faculties acute enough to perceive the precise size, shape, texture, and motion of the minute parts of bodies by means of which they operate on our senses. ·Why would we need such faculties? Because we would need a perceptual intake of those facts· in order to build them into our abstract ideas of bodies—·ideas that have to be the immediate source of any certain universal knowledge·.

229

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vi: Universal propositions

I have mentioned here only corporeal substances, whose operations seem to lie more within reach of our understandings; for when we try to think about the operations of spirits—how they think, and how they move bodies—we find ourselves at a loss straight off. But ·there isn’t really much of a difference, because· when we have thought a bit more closely about how bodies operate, and examined how little—even with bodies—we can grasp clearly beyond matters of particular fact that we learn through our senses, we’ll have to admit that with bodies too our ‘discoveries’ don’t amount to much more than perfect ignorance and incapacity!

15. This is evident: the abstract complex ideas of substances, for which their general names stand, don’t include their real constitutions, and so they can give us very little universal certainty—because our ideas of them don’t include whatever it is that produces the qualities we observe in them and want to know about. For example, let the idea to which we give the name ‘man’ be a body of the ordinary shape, with sense, voluntary motion, and reason joined to it. This being the abstract idea, and consequently the essence of our species man, we can make very few general certain propositions concerning man, taken in this sense. We don’t know

the real constitution that underlies •sensation, •power of movement, •reasoning, and •that special shape, producing them and uniting them in a single subject,

so there are very few other qualities with which we can perceive them to have a necessary connection. Therefore we can’t with certainty affirm that •all men sleep intermittently, that •no man can be nourished by wood or stones, or that •for all men hemlock is a poison; because these ideas have no connection or incompatibility with our nominal essence of man, this abstract idea that ‘man’ stands for. With propositions like these we must appeal to tests with particular subjects, and that can’t take us far. For the rest, we must settle for probability.... There are animals that safely eat hemlock, and others that are nourished by wood and stones; but as long as we lack ideas of the various sorts of animals’ real constitutions, on which such qualities and powers depend, we mustn’t hope to reach certainty in universal propositions about them. We can reach such propositions only from ideas that have a detectable connection with our nominal essence or with some part of it; but there are so few of these, and they are so insignificant, that we can fairly look on our certain general knowledge of substances as almost non-existent.

[Section 16 sums up the main conclusions of the chapter, without adding to them.]

230

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vii: Maxims

Chapter vii: Maxims

1. Propositions of a certain kind—labelled ‘maxims’ or ‘axioms’—have been taken to be principles of science; and because they are self-evident they have been thought to be innate, though I know of nobody who has undertaken to show what makes them so clear and compelling. It may be worthwhile to enquire into the reason for their evidentness, to see whether it is special to them alone, and also to examine how far they influence and govern our other knowledge.

2. Knowledge, as I have shown, consists in the perception of the agreement or disagreement of ideas. Now, when that agreement or disagreement is perceived immediately, by itself and without the intervention or help of any other ideas, then our knowledge is self-evident. Anyone will see this who merely thinks of one of the propositions that he assents to at first sight, without any proof. For he will find each time that his assent comes from the agreement (or disagreement) which his mind, by bringing the ideas together in a single thought, immediately finds in them corresponding to the affirmation (or negation) in the proposition.

3. Is this self-evidence special to the propositions that commonly pass under the name of ‘maxims’ and have the title of ‘axioms’ conferred on them? Plainly it is not: various other truths that aren’t counted as axioms are equally self-evident. To see this, let us go over the sorts of agreement or disagreement of ideas that I discussed earlier, namely •identity, •co-existence, •relation, and •real existence. ·I shall give these a section each·. We shall discover that not only the small number of so-called ‘maxims’ are self-evident, but a virtually infinite number of other propositions are so as well.

4. The immediate perception of the agreement or disagreement of identity is based simply on the mind’s having different ideas; so this provides us with as many self-evident propositions as we have different ideas. Everyone that has any knowledge at all has as its foundation various different ideas; and the first act of the mind (without which it can never be capable of any knowledge) is to know each of its ideas by itself, and to distinguish it from others. Everyone finds in himself that •he knows the ideas he has; that •he knows also when any idea is in his understanding, and what it is; and that •when two or more ideas are there he knows them distinctly without confusing them with one another. So he can never be in doubt, when some idea is in his mind, that it is there and is the idea that it is; and when two different ideas are in his mind, he can’t doubt that they are there and aren’t one and the same idea. All such affirmations and negations are made without any possibility of doubt, uncertainty, or hesitation, and must necessarily be assented to as soon as understood—that is, as soon as we have in our minds definite ideas that the terms in the proposition stand for. [The remainder of this long section elaborates the account already given, emphasizing that an idea’s identity with itself, and its distinctness from every other idea, don’t depend on how general or particular the idea is. This sort of self-evidence, then, can be found not only in the very general propositions that are called ‘maxims’ or ‘axioms’ but also in much less general ones that aren’t accorded that honour. The section concludes:] I appeal to everyone’s own mind to confirm that the proposition A circle is a circle is as self-evident a proposition as that consisting of more general terms, Whatsoever is, is; and again that the proposition Blue

231

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vii: Maxims

is not red is a proposition that the mind can no more doubt, as soon as it understands the words, than it can doubt the axiom It is impossible for the same thing to be and not be; and so on for all the others.

5. As to co-existence, or a necessary connection between two ideas such that a subject in which one of them exists must have the other also: the mind almost never immediately perceives any agreement or disagreement of this sort. So we have very little intuitive knowledge of this kind; nor are there many propositions of this kind that are self-evident. There are some, however: if our idea of body includes the idea of filling a place equal to the contents of its outer surface then I think it is a self-evident proposition that two bodies can’t be in the same place ·at the same time·.

6. As to the relations of modes, mathematicians have formulated many axioms concerning the one relation equality. For example, Equals taken from equals, the remainder will be equal; this and its kind are deemed to be maxims by the mathematicians, and they are unquestionable truths. But I don’t think that anyone who considers them will find that they are more clearly self-evident than that One and one are equal to two; and that If you take two from the five fingers of one hand and two from the five fingers of the other hand, the remaining numbers will be equal. These and a thousand other such propositions may be found concerning numbers—propositions that compel assent at the very first hearing, and carry with them at least as much clearness as the mathematical axioms.

7. As to real existence, since that has no ·necessary· connection with any of our other ideas except the ideas of ourselves and of a first being, we don’t even have •demonstrative knowledge of the real existence of any things other than ourselves and God, much less self-evident ·or •intuitive· knowledge; and therefore concerning those other things there are no maxims.

8. In the next place let us consider what influence these received maxims have on the other parts of our knowledge. The rule established by the scholastic philosophers that all reasonings are ex praecognitis et praeconcessis [= ‘from what is known in advance and what is agreed to in advance’] seems to base all other knowledge on these maxims, and to suppose them to be praecognita. I think two claims are being made here: •that these axioms are the truths that are first known to the mind, and •that the other parts of our knowledge depend on them. ·I shall argue against both of these, giving them a section apiece·.

9. Our own experience shows us that they aren’t the truths first known to the mind (see I.ii). Anyone can see that a child certainly knows that a stranger is not its mother and that its sucking-bottle is not the rod long before it knows that it is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be! And there are ever so many truths about numbers that the mind is perfectly acquainted with, and fully convinced of, before it ever gives thought to the general maxims from which mathematicians in their proofs sometimes derive them. The reason for this is very plain. What makes the mind assent to such propositions is just its perception of the agreement or disagreement of its ideas, according as it finds them affirmed or denied of one another in words it understands; and every idea is known to be what it is, and every two different ideas are known not to be the same; so it necessarily follows that the self-evident truths that are first known must be the ones whose constituent ideas are first in the mind. And the ideas that are first in the mind, obviously, are those of particular things, from which by slow degrees the understanding proceeds to a few general ideas. These, being

232

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vii: Maxims

taken from the ordinary and familiar objects of sense, are settled in the mind with general names annexed to them. Thus the ideas that are first received and distinguished, and so made the subjects of knowledge, are particular ones; next come specific or somewhat general ones. ·Ideas that are more general come later still, because the more general an idea is the greater the abstraction that is needed to form it. And·: for the novice minds of children, abstract ideas aren’t as obvious or easy as particular ones are. If they seem easy to grown men that is only because they have been made so by constant and familiar use. For when we reflect on general ideas accurately and with care we’ll find that they are artifacts, contrivances of the mind, which have a lot of difficulty in them and don’t offer themselves as easily as we tend to think. For example, it requires some effort and skill to form the general idea of a triangle (though this isn’t one of the most abstract, comprehensive, and difficult), for it must be neither oblique nor rectangle, neither equilateral, equicrural, nor scalenon; but all and none of these at once. In effect, it is something imperfect, that cannot exist; an idea in which some parts of several different and inconsistent ideas are put together. The mind certainly needs such ideas, and hurries to get them as fast as it can, to make communication easier and to enlarge knowledge. But there is reason to suspect that abstract ideas are signs of our imperfection; and at least I have said enough to show that the most abstract and general ideas are not those that the mind is first and most easily acquainted with, nor what its earliest knowledge is about.

10. It plainly follows from this that these vaunted ‘maxims’ are not the principles and foundations of all our other knowledge. If there are many other truths that are as self-evident as the maxims are and known before we know them, the maxims can’t be the principles from which we deduce all other truths. Is it impossible to know that one and two are equal to three except through some such axiom as the whole is equal to all its parts taken together? Plenty of people know that one and two are equal to three, without having heard or thought of any axiom by which it might be proved; and they know it as certainly as anyone knows that the whole is equal to all its parts or any other maxim, knowing it on the same basis of self-evidence. For the equality of those ideas—·the equality of one and two with three·—is as visible and certain to everyone without that or any other axiom as it is with it. Furthermore, when someone comes to know that the whole is equal to all its parts he doesn’t then know that one and two are equal to three better or more certainly than he did before. If there are relevant differences in those ideas, the ideas of whole and part are more obscure, or at least harder to get securely in the mind, than those of one, two, and three. [In the remainder of this section Locke repeats his reason for holding that particular self-evident truths are not known on the strength of axioms or maxims; and says that in that case we must either •give up the doctrine that all knowledge is based on ‘praecognita or general maxims’ or else •count every immediately self-evident truth as a maxim, in which case there will be innumerably many maxims.]

11. Then what shall we say? Are these general maxims useless? By no means; though perhaps their use is not what it is commonly thought to be. But my calling into question what some men have claimed for maxims may draw the protest that I am overturning the foundations of all the sciences; so it may be worthwhile to consider them in relation to other parts of our knowledge, and to examine in more detail what purposes they do serve and what purposes they don’t. ·I shall do this in one long section, first treating

233

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vii: Maxims

three purposes that maxims do not serve, then two that they do·.

(1) It is evident from what I have already said that maxims are of no use to prove or confirm less general self-evident propositions.

(2) It is equally clear that they have never been the foundations on which any branch of knowledge has been built. [Locke then pours scorn on the view that a branch of knowledge could be based on What is, is or its like. In theological disputes, maxims can ‘serve to silence wranglers’, he concedes, but:] I think that nobody will infer from this that the Christian religion is built on these maxims, or that our knowledge of it is derived from these principles. It is from revelation we have received it, and without revelation these maxims could never have helped us to it. When we find out an idea by whose intervention we discover the connection of two others, this is a revelation from God to us through •the voice of reason. For then we come to know a truth that we didn’t know before. When God declares any truth to us this is a revelation to us through •the voice of his spirit, and we are advanced in our knowledge. But in neither case do we receive our light or knowledge from maxims. In one case, the things themselves provide it, and we see the truth in them by perceiving their agreement or disagreement. In the other case, God himself provides it immediately to us, and we see the truth of what he says in his unerring truthfulness.

(3) Maxims don’t help men forward in the advancement of sciences, or in the discovery of previously unknown truths. Mr. Newton, in his supremely admirable book, has demonstrated various propositions that are new truths, previously unknown to the world, and are further advances in mathematical knowledge. But he wasn’t helped to discover these by such general maxims as What is, is or The whole is bigger than a part—these weren’t the clues that led him into the discovery of the truth and certainty of those propositions. Nor did they give him the knowledge of his demonstrations: he achieved that by finding out intermediate ideas that showed the agreement or disagreement of the ideas expressed in the propositions he demonstrated. This is the greatest way in which human understanding enlarges its knowledge and advances the sciences; and maxims don’t come into it. Those who have this traditional admiration of these propositions, and think that no step can be made in knowledge without the support of an axiom, ought to distinguish •the method of acquiring knowledge from •the method of communicating it; and •the method of creating a science from •that of teaching it to others as far as it is advanced. Then they would see that general maxims were not the foundations on which the first discoverers raised their fine structures, or the keys that ·first· unlocked those secrets of knowledge. Though afterwards, when universities were built, and sciences had their professors to teach what others had found out, they often made use of maxims. That is, they laid down certain propositions that were self-evident, or were to be received as true; and then with these settled in the minds of their pupils as unquestionable truths, the professors occasionally employed them to convince the pupils of truths in particular instances that were not so familiar to their minds as those general axioms which had been inculcated in them and carefully settled in their minds. Yet these particular instances, when well reflected on, are just as self-evident as the general maxims used to confirm them; and it was in those particular instances that the first discoverer found the truth, with no help from the general maxims. And so can anyone else who considers them attentively.

·So much for what maxims cannot do·. I come now to the use that is made of maxims.

234

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vii: Maxims

(1) They are useful, as I have just noted, in the ordinary methods of teaching sciences as far as they are advanced; but of little or none in advancing them further.

(2) They are of use in disputes, for silencing obstinate wranglers and bringing those contests to some conclusion. [In the remaining four pages of this enormous section Locke •paints a satirical picture of men—in ‘the Schools’—engaging in formal debates, each displaying great ingenuity and little shame in trying to vanquish his opponents by any means he can devise, and conjectures that in such situations maxims were found to be useful as setting limits to how far disputants could go in the direction of falsehood and absurdity; •distinguishes this use of maxims from one in which they bring new knowledge; •derides the idea that any branch of knowledge could be based on the likes of Whatever is, is; •argues that less general maxims, such as The whole is equal to all its parts, are merely ‘verbal propositions’ that merely set out facts about the meanings of the words they contain; and •offers to explain why the title of ‘maxim’ tends to be reserved for the most general self-evident propositions rather than for all of them.]

12. One more thing worth noting about these general maxims is that, far from increasing our knowledge or our hold on it, they can serve to confirm us in mistakes. This can happen when our notions are wrong, loose or unsteady, and we give our thoughts over to the sound of •words instead of fixing them on settled determinate •ideas of things. When people are using words in that way ·as substitutes for ideas·, general maxims can be employed to prove contradictions! ·In this section and the next two I shall discuss one example of this phenomenon·.

Someone who follows Descartes in forming in his mind an idea of extension which he calls an idea of body can easily demonstrate that there is no vacuum, i.e. no space that has no body in it, by means of the maxim What is, is. ·Here is how·. The idea to which he attaches the name ‘body’ is merely the idea of extension, so he knows quite certainly that space can’t exist without body ·in his sense of ‘body’·. For he knows his own idea of extension clearly and distinctly, and knows that it is what it is and not another idea, though he calls it by the three names ‘extension’, ‘body’, and ‘space’. Because these three words stand for one and the same idea, they can be affirmed of one another with the same self-evidence and certainty as each can be affirmed of itself. So that when one uses all three names to stand for one and the same idea, the proposition ‘Space is body’ is just as true an identity as the proposition ‘Body is body’, though only the latter bears the identity on its surface.

13. But if someone comes along with an idea that he attaches to the name ‘body’, including in it not only extension but also solidity, he will have little trouble demonstrating that there can be a vacuum, or space with no body in it—just as little, indeed, as Descartes had in demonstrating the contrary! The idea that he calls ‘space’ is merely the simple idea of

extension,

and the idea he calls ‘body’ is the complex idea of

extension and resistibility (or solidity) together in the same subject.

These are two ideas, not one; they are as distinct in the understanding as are the ideas of one and two, white and black, or corporeity and humanity (if I may use those barbarous terms). So the right way to bring them together in a proposition, whether in our minds or in words, is not by •identifying them with one another, but rather by •denying that they are identical. That is the proposition Extension or space is not body, which is as true and self-evidently certain

235

Essay IV John Locke Chapter vii: Maxims

as the maxim It is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be can make any proposition.

14. So you see that with the help of these two certain principles, What is, is and The same thing cannot be and not be we can demonstrate that there can’t be a vacuum and that there can be one. But neither of those principles will actually prove to us what bodies, if any, do exist. For that we are left to our senses, to reveal to us as much as they can. All there is to those universal and self-evident principles is our constant, clear, and distinct knowledge of our own more general or comprehensive ideas. They can’t assure us of anything that happens outside the mind; their certainty is based purely on the knowledge we have of each idea by itself, and of its distinctness from other ideas. We can’t be mistaken about that •while the ideas are in our minds, though we can be and often are mistaken •when we retain the names without the ideas, or use the names confusedly sometimes for one idea and sometimes for another. When we do the latter, the force of these axioms ·or maxims·, which touches only the words and not their meanings, serves only to lead us into confusion, mistake, and error. I point this out in order to show you that these maxims, praised as they are as great guardians of truth, won’t secure us from error in a careless loose use of our words.

In all that I have said about •how little use maxims are for the improvement of knowledge, and •how dangerous they are when applied to undetermined ideas, I have been far from saying or meaning they should be laid aside—as some have accused me of saying ·in earlier editions of this work·. I shan’t make the futile attempt to cut them back in any area where they do have a ·legitimate· influence. But I am not offending against truth or knowledge when I •say that I have reason to think that the usefulness of maxims is not such as to justify the great stress that seems to be laid on them, and when I •warn men not to misuse them in confirming themselves in errors.

[In section 15 Locke contends that maxims are safe to use in an intellectual environment where all the ideas concerned are agreed, clear, settled, and so on; but, he adds, they are also unhelpful there because in that kind of environment the arguments can proceed clearly and well without the aid of maxims. In sections 16–18 he goes through a variant on the ‘vacuum’ example that he gave in sections 12–14, this time with people disagreeing about what men can be like because they start with different ideas of man. His portrayal of them as working out the implications of their ideas with help from maxims is no more plausible here than it was with the vacuum dispute.]

19. We can conclude that where our ideas are determined in our minds, and have known names attached to them in a steady manner, maxims are not needed or useful to prove the agreement or disagreement of any of our ideas. Someone who can’t see the truth or falsehood of such propositions without the help of such maxims won’t be able to see it with the maxims’ aid either. If he doesn’t know the truth of other propositions ·such as that White is not black· without proof, he presumably doesn’t know the truth of the maxims without proof either, because they are no more self-evident than the others are. That is why intuitive knowledge neither requires nor admits of any proof.... If you suppose that it does, you take away the foundation of all knowledge and certainty. And if you need any proof to make you certain in your assent to the proposition that Two are equal to two, you will also need a proof to make you accept that What is, is....

[In section 20 Locke repeats his earlier thesis that intellectual contexts where maxims might be invoked divide into •those where they are useless and •those where they are dangerous.]

236

Essay IV John Locke Chapter viii: Trifling propositions

Chapter viii: Trifling propositions

1. I leave it to you to decide whether the maxims treated of in the preceding chapter are as useful to real knowledge as they are generally supposed to be. But I think I may confidently affirm that there are some universal propositions which, though they are certainly true, add no light to our understandings, bring no increase to our knowledge. ·There are two kinds of such propositions. I shall discuss one in sections 2–3, the other in 4–7·.

2. First, all purely identical propositions. We can see at a glance that these appear to contain no instruction in them—·to give us no news·. For a proposition that affirms a term of itself tells us only what we must certainly have known already, before the proposition was put to us; and this is so whether the proposition •contains any clear and real idea or rather is •merely verbal—·that is, is a mere construct of words with no backing in ideas. (This is different from the notion of ‘verbal proposition’ spoken of in v.5·.) Indeed that most general proposition What is, is may serve sometimes to show a man the absurdity he is guilty of when he ·implicitly· denies something of itself. (This would happen only through circumlocution or ambiguity, because nobody is willing to defy common sense so openly as to affirm visible and direct contradictions.) But neither that received maxim nor any other identical proposition teaches us anything....

[In section 3 Locke mocks identical propositions, pointing out that even a very ignorant person can come up with a million of them, all certainly true and all useless—A soul is a soul, A spirit is a spirit, and so on. He continues:] This is mere trifling with words. It is like a monkey shifting an oyster from one hand to the other: if he could speak, perhaps he would say ‘Oyster in right hand is subject, and oyster in left hand is predicate’, thus making the self-evident proposition Oyster is oyster; and yet with all this he wouldn’t have been the least bit wiser or more knowledgeable. That way of handling the matter would have satisfied the monkey’s hunger about as well as it would a man’s understanding—monkey and man would have improved in bulk and in knowledge together! [The section continues with a further •three derisive paragraphs attacking the idea that in developing some branch of knowledge it is useful to go about reminding oneself or others that substance is substance, that body is body, and so on; and •two paragraphs in which Locke defends his calling such propositions ‘trifling’, and defends himself against critics of the first edition of the Essay, who had attacked him for saying that all identical proposition are trifling but hadn’t grasped how narrowly Locke was construing the phrase ‘identical proposition’.]

4. Another sort of trifling proposition occurs when a part of a complex idea is predicated of the name of the whole; a part of the definition is predicated of the word defined. This includes every proposition in which a more comprehensive term (the genus) is predicated of a less comprehensive one (the species). What information, what knowledge, does a man get from the proposition that Lead is a metal if he knows the complex idea that ‘lead’ stands for? All the simple ideas that belong to the complex one signified by the term ‘metal’ are nothing but what he had already included in his meaning for the name ‘lead’. Indeed, when someone knows the meaning of ‘metal’ and not of ‘lead’, telling him that Lead is a metal is a short way to explain the latter....

237

Essay IV John Locke Chapter viii: Trifling propositions

5. ·Not only predicating •the genus of the species·—it is equally trifling to apply to some term •any other part of its definition, that is, to predicate of the name of some complex idea a simple idea that is part of it—for example All gold is fusible. Fusibility is one of the simple ideas that make up the complex one that ‘gold’ stands for, so affirming it of gold can only be playing with sounds.... If I know that the name ‘gold’ stands for this complex idea of body, yellow, heavy, fusible, and malleable, I won’t learn much from being solemnly told that all gold is fusible! The only use for such propositions is to point out to someone that he is drifting away from his own definition of one of his terms. However certain they are, the only knowledge they convey concerns the meanings of words.

[Section 6 insists further on the uninformativeness of these ‘trifling’ propositions, exemplified by Every man is an animal and A palfrey is an ambling horse, each of which Locke takes to be true by definition of its subject term. He concludes with a contrast:] But when someone tells me things like

•Any thing in which sense, motion, reason, and laughter are united has a notion of God,

•Any thing in which sense, motion, reason, and laughter are united would be put to sleep by opium,

he has indeed made an instructive proposition. Neither having the notion of God nor being put to sleep by opium is contained in the idea signified by the word ‘man’—·namely the idea of thing in which sense, motion, reason, and laughter are united·. So propositions like those teach us something more than merely what the word ‘man’ stands for, and therefore the knowledge they offer is more than verbal.

7. Before a man makes a proposition he is •supposed to understand the terms he uses in it; otherwise he talks like a parrot, making noises in imitation of others rather than, like a rational creature, using them as signs of ideas in his mind. The hearer also is •supposed to understand the words as the speaker uses them; otherwise the speaker is talking gibberish and making unintelligible noises. So someone is trifling with words when he makes a proposition that contains no more than one of its terms does, which both speaker and hearer were supposed to know already—for example, A triangle has three sides, or Saffron is yellow. This is tolerable only when the speaker aims to explain his terms to a hearer who he thinks doesn’t understand them; and then it teaches only the meaning of that word, the use of that sign.

8. So we can know with perfect certainty the truth of two sorts of propositions. One is the trifling propositions whose certainty is only verbal, not instructive. Secondly, we can know for certain the truth of propositions that affirm something of something else where the former is a necessary consequence but not a part of the complex idea of the latter. For example, Every triangle has an external angle that is bigger than either of the opposite internal angles. This relation of the outward angle to each of the opposite internal angles isn’t part of the complex idea signified by the name ‘triangle’, so this is a real truth, conveying instructive real knowledge.

9. senses are our only source of knowledge of what combinations of simple ideas [here = ‘qualities’] exist together in substances; so the only certain universal propositions we can make about them are ones based on our nominal essences; and these truths are few in number, and unimportant, in comparison with ones that depend on substances’ real constitutions. Therefore, this holds for general propositions about substances: •when they are certain, they are mostly trifling; and •when they are instructive, they are uncertain.

238

Essay IV John Locke Chapter viii: Trifling propositions

In the latter case, we can’t have any knowledge of their real truth. however much constant observation and analogy may assist our judgment in guessing. That’s why it often happens that one encounters very clear and coherent discourses that amount to nothing. Names of substantial beings as well as others, so far as they have relative meanings—·as the meaning of ‘magnet’ is relative, because it includes ‘is able to attract iron·—can be joined negatively or affirmatively in true propositions in ways that their relative definitions make them fit to be joined; and propositions consisting of such terms can be deduced from one another just as clearly as can propositions that convey the most real truths. By this method one can make demonstrations and undoubted propositions in words without advancing an inch in one’s knowledge about things. For example, someone who has learned the following words, with their ordinary relative meanings attached to them—

‘substance’, ‘man’, ‘animal’, ‘form’, ‘soul’, ‘vegetative’, ‘sensitive’, ‘rational’

—can make many undoubted propositions about the soul without knowing anything about what the soul really is. Similarly, a man may find an infinite number of propositions, reasonings, and conclusions in books of metaphysics, school-divinity, and some sorts of natural science, yet end up knowing as little about God, spirits, or bodies as he did before he started.

10. Everyone is free to give his names of substances any meaning he likes. Someone who does this casually and thoughtlessly, taking meanings from his own or other men’s fancies and not from any enquiry into the nature of things themselves, can easily demonstrate them of one another according to the various respects and mutual relations he has given them. In doing this he can ignore how things agree or disagree in their own nature, and attend only to his own notions, with the names he has given them. But he doesn’t increase his own knowledge through this procedure, any more than someone increases his riches by taking a bag of counters and calling one ‘a pound’, another ‘a shilling’, a third ‘a penny’. This latter person can undoubtedly add correctly and reach a large sum on the bottom line, without being any richer—indeed, without even knowing how much a pound, a shilling, or a penny is, except that a pound contains twenty shillings and a shilling twelve pennies. One can do ·something analogous to· that with the meanings of words, by making them more or less comprehensive than one another.

11. Concerning most words that are used in discourses—especially argumentative and controversial ones—a further sort of trifling occurs. It is the worst sort, putting us even further from the certainty of knowledge we hope to attain through what we read. Most writers, far from instructing us in the nature and knowledge of things, use their words loosely and uncertainly. They don’t by using words constantly and steadily with the same meanings make plain and clear deductions of some from others, and make their discourses coherent and clear (even if not very instructive). Yet it wouldn’t be hard for them to do this, if it weren’t that it suits them to shelter their ignorance or obstinacy under the obscurity and confusion of their terms....

[In sections 12–13 Locke sums up the chapter, describing the two kinds of ‘barely verbal propositions’—the two already described in sections 2 and 4 respectively. The awkward final paragraph of section 13 boils down to this: If you want to say something in which your thoughts don’t ‘stick wholly in sounds’, something with a claim to ‘real truth or falsehood’, you must •have a known and considered idea attached to

239

Essay IV John Locke Chapter ix: Knowledge of existence

each word, and •affirm of the subject ‘something that isn’t contained in the idea’ of it (or, by clear implication, deny of the subject something whose negation isn’t contained in the idea of it).]

Chapter ix: Knowledge of existence

1. So far we have considered only the essences of things, a procedure that gives us no knowledge of real existence. That’s because essences are only abstract ideas, and thereby separated in our thoughts from particular existence; for abstraction when it is properly done doesn’t consider an idea in relation to any existence except its own existence in the understanding. While on that topic, we may note in passing that universal propositions of whose truth or falsehood we can have certain knowledge don’t concern existence; and further that all particular affirmations or negations that wouldn’t be certain if they were made general are only about existence ·and nothing more·, for they declare only the accidental union or separation in existing things of ideas [here = ‘qualities’] which in their abstract natures are not known to be necessarily united or separated.

2. Leaving the nature of propositions and different ways of predication to be considered at more length elsewhere, let us proceed now to enquire into our knowledge of the existence of things, and how we come by it. I say that

•intuition gives us knowledge that •we exist,

•demonstration gives us knowledge that •God exists, and

•sensation gives us knowledge of the existence of •other things.

·I shall discuss these in the next section, chapter x, and chapter xi respectively·.

3. We perceive our own existence so plainly and certainly that it neither needs nor is capable of proof. Nothing can be more evident to us than our own existence: I think, I reason, I feel pleasure and pain; can any of these be more evident to me than my own existence? If I doubt everything else, that very doubt makes me perceive my own existence and won’t let me doubt it. For if I know •I feel pain, it is obvious that I perceive own existence as certainly as I do the pain that I feel. ·Similarly·, when I know that •I doubt something, I perceive the existence of the thing that doubts as certainly as I do the thought that I call ‘doubt’. Experience convinces us, then, that we have an intuitive knowledge of our own existence, and an internal infallible perception that we are. In every act of sensation, reasoning, or thinking, we are conscious to ourselves of our own being, and in this matter we don’t fall short of the highest degree of certainty.

240

Essay IV John Locke Chapter x: knowledge of a god

Chapter x: knowledge of the existence of a god

1. Though God has given us no innate ideas of himself—has not stamped onto our minds from the outset words in which we can read his existence—yet having equipped us with the mental faculties that we have, he hasn’t left himself without witness ·to his existence·. We have sense, perception, and reason, and can’t be without a clear proof of him as long as we carry our selves with us. We can’t fairly complain of our ignorance about this great point, since God has so plentifully provided us with the means to discover and know him, so far as is needed for the goal of our existence and for the great matter of our happiness. But though this is the most obvious truth that reason reveals, and though (I think) its evidentness is equal to mathematical certainty, ·becoming certain of· it still requires thought and attention: the mind must deduce God’s existence in a rule-guided way from something that is intuitively known, for otherwise we shall be as uncertain and ignorant of this as of other propositions that are in themselves capable of clear demonstration. To show that we are capable of knowing—i.e. being certain—that there is a God, and to see how we can acquire this certainty, I think we need go no further than ourselves, and the undoubted knowledge we have of our own existence.

2. I think it is beyond question that man has a clear idea of his own existence; he knows certainly he exists, and that he is something. If you can doubt whether you are anything or not, I have nothing to say to you, any more than I would argue with pure nothing, or try to convince non-entity that it is something. If anyone •claims to be so sceptical as to deny his own existence (for •really to doubt this is manifestly impossible), I am willing to let him luxuriate in his beloved state of being nothing, until hunger or some other pain convinces him of the contrary! This then, I think I may take for a truth, which everyone’s certain knowledge assures him of and will not let him doubt, namely that he is something that actually exists.

3. In the next place, man knows by an intuitive certainty that bare nothing can no more •produce any real being than it can •be equal to two right angles. If a man doesn’t know that non-entity or the absence of all being cannot be equal to two right angles, he can’t possibly know any demonstration in Euclid. If therefore we know there is some real being, and that non-entity cannot produce any real being, that yields an evident demonstration that from eternity there has been something; for what didn’t exist from eternity had a beginning, and what had a beginning ·wasn’t produced by •nothing, and so· must be produced by •something other than itself.

4. Next, it is evident, that if one thing received •its existence and beginning from something else, it must also have received from something else •all that is in it and belongs to its being. All its powers must be have come from the same source. This eternal source of all being, therefore, must also be the source of all power; and so this eternal being must be also the most powerful.

5. A man finds perception and knowledge in himself, and that yields the next step in the proof: we are certain now that there is not only some being, but some knowing thinking being, in the world. So either •there was a time when there was no knowing being, and when knowledge began to be, or else •there has been a knowing being from eternity. If you ·take the former option, and· say that there was a time

241

Essay IV John Locke Chapter x: knowledge of a god

when no being had any knowledge—a time when the eternal being had no understanding—I reply that in that case it was impossible that there should ever have come to be any knowledge. For things wholly devoid of knowledge, and operating blindly and without any perception, to produce a knowing being—this is no more possible than that a triangle should have three angles bigger than two right angles. For it is as inconsistent with the idea of senseless matter that it should put sense, perception, and knowledge into itself as it is inconsistent with the idea of a triangle that it should put into itself greater angles than two right ones.

6. Thus by thinking about ourselves and what we infallibly find in our own constitutions, our reason leads us to the knowledge of the certain and evident truth that there is an eternal, most powerful, and most knowing being; and it doesn’t matter whether we call it ‘God’. The ·existence of the· thing is evident, and from properly thinking through this idea we can easily deduce all the other attributes that we ought to ascribe to this eternal being. If nevertheless anyone should be found so senselessly arrogant as to suppose that man alone is knowing and wise, yet is also the product of mere ignorance and chance, and that all the rest of the universe acts only by that blind chance, I shall offer him Tully’s firm and reasonable rebuke: ‘What can be more sillily arrogant and unbecoming than for a man to think that he has a mind and understanding in him while all the rest of the universe contains no such thing? Or that things he can barely comprehend with the utmost stretch of his reason should be moved and managed without any help at all from reason?’

From what I have said it is plain to me that we have a more certain knowledge of the existence of a God than of anything ·else· that our senses haven’t immediately revealed to us. Indeed, I think I can say that we more certainly know •that there is a God than •that there is anything else outside us. When I say ‘we know’, I mean that such knowledge lies within our reach, and that we can’t miss it if only we will apply our minds to it as we do to various other enquiries.

7. I won’t here examine the question of how far the idea of a most perfect being that a man may form in his mind does or does not prove the existence of a God,. Because of differences in men’s characters and ways of thinking, some arguments for a given truth carry more weight with one person, some with another. But I will say this: if you want to establish this truth and silence atheists, you are going about it in a poor way if you lay the whole stress of such an important point as this on that one foundation, basing your only proof of the existence of a deity on some men’s having that idea of God in their minds. (·I speak of some men’s idea of God because· clearly some men have no idea of God, and some worse than none, and the ideas of God that others do have are very different from one another.) ·It is a mistake· to let your over-fondness for that darling invention lead you to dismiss, or at least try to invalidate, all other arguments, and forbid us to listen to proofs (weak or fallacious, according to you) which our own existence and the perceptible parts of the universe offer so clearly and convincingly to our thoughts that I think it impossible for a thoughtful person to withstand them.... Our own existence provides us, as I have shown, with an evident and unchallengable proof of a deity, and I believe that nobody can avoid the force of that proof, provided he attends to it with the care he would give to any other demonstration with so many parts, Still, this is so fundamental a truth, and of such importance (with all religion and genuine morality depending on it), that I’m sure you will forgive me if I go over

242

Essay IV John Locke Chapter x: knowledge of a god

some parts of the argument again and develop them in more detail.

8. There is no truth more evident than that something must be from eternity. I never yet heard of anyone so unreasonable, or so willing to accept an obvious contradiction, as to believe there was a time at which there was absolutely nothing. To imagine that pure nothing, the perfect negation and absence of all beings, should ever produce any real existence—this is the greatest of all absurdities.

It being then unavoidable for all rational creatures to conclude that something has existed from eternity, let us next see what kind of thing it must be.

9. There are only two sorts of beings in the world that man knows or conceives. First, such as are purely material, without sense, perception, or thought, such as the clippings of our beards and parings of our nails.

Secondly, sensing, thinking, perceiving beings, such as we find ourselves to be. From now on I shall refer to these two groups as incogitative and cogitative beings respectively. These are perhaps better labels, at least for our present purpose, than ‘material’ and ‘immaterial’.

10. If there must be something eternal, it is very obvious to reason that it must be a cogitative being. For it is as impossible •to conceive that mere incogitative matter should ever produce a thinking intelligent being as •to conceive that nothing should of itself produce matter. If we suppose that some portion of matter, large or small, is eternal, we shall find that it in itself can’t produce anything. For example, let us suppose that the matter of the next pebble we meet with is eternal, closely united, and the parts firmly at rest together: if there were no other being in the world, wouldn’t it eternally remain what it is, a dead inactive lump? Can we conceive it—a purely material thing—as being able to add motion to itself, or to produce anything? Matter, then, can’t by its own powers start itself moving; the motion it has must also be from eternity, or else be produced and added to matter by some other being that is more powerful than matter. Well, let us suppose that motion is eternal too. Still matter—incogitative matter and motion—whatever changes it might produce in shape and size. could never produce thought. Knowledge will still be as far beyond the power of motion and matter to produce as matter is beyond the power of nothing or nonentity to produce. Consult your own thoughts, and see whether I am right: you can as easily conceive matter produced by nothing as thought to be produced by pure matter when before there was no such thing as thought, no intelligent being in existence! Divide matter into parts as small as you like (which we are apt to imagine is a sort of spiritualizing, or making a thinking thing, of it), and vary the shapes and movements of its parts as much as you please; still a globe, cube, cone, prism, cylinder, etc. whose diameters are only one billionth of an inch will affect other bodies of similar size in exactly the same way as do those with diameters of an inch or a foot, You may as rationally expect to produce sense, thought, and knowledge by putting together big particles of matter in certain shapes and movements as to produce it with particles that are the very tiniest that exist. They knock, impel, and resist one another, just as the bigger ones do, and that is all they can do. So

If we suppose that •nothing is first or eternal, •matter can never begin to be.

If we suppose •motionless matter to be first or eternal, •motion can never begin to be.

If we suppose •matter and motion to be first or eternal, •thought can never begin to be.

How about the possibility that matter has sense, perception,

243

Essay IV John Locke Chapter x: knowledge of a god

and knowledge ·not put into it by something else, but· basically and inherently and from itself? This is inconceivable, because in that case sense, perception and knowledge would have to be a property eternally inseparable from matter and from every particle of it. And here is a further reason. Although our general conception of matter makes us speak of it as one thing, really all matter is not one individual thing, and there is no such thing existing as one material being, or one single body that we know or can conceive. Therefore, if matter were the eternal first cogitative being, instead of there being just one eternal infinite cogitative being there would be infinitely many eternal finite cogitative beings, independent one of another, of limited force and separate thoughts, which could never produce that order, harmony and beauty that are to be found in nature.

Since therefore whatever is the first eternal being must be cogitative; and since whatever is first of all things must actually have all the perfections that can ever after exist (because it can never give to something else any perfection that it doesn’t have itself, either actually or in a higher degree), it necessarily follows that the first eternal being can’t be matter.

11. Just as it is evident that something must exist from eternity, it is equally evident that this ‘something’ must be a cogitative being. For it is as impossible that incogitative matter should produce a cogitative being as that nothing, or the negation of all being, should produce a positive being or matter.

12. This discovery of the necessary existence of an eternal mind sufficiently leads us into the knowledge of God: it implies that all other knowing beings that have a beginning must depend on him, and have only such ways of knowledge and kinds of power as he gives them; and therefore that he made not only those knowing beings but also the less excellent (inanimate) pieces of this universe; and this establishes his omniscience, power, and providence—and all his other attributes necessarily follow. Still, to clear this up a little further, let us see what doubts can be raised against it.

13. First, perhaps it will be said that though it is as clear as demonstration can make it that there must be an eternal being, which must knowing, it doesn’t follow that this thinking being isn’t also material. Let it be so—·that is, suppose that it is made of matter·—it still follows that there is a God. For if there is an eternal, omniscient, omnipotent being, it is certain that there is a God, whether you imagine that being to be material or no.

Still, I think there is something dangerous and deceptive in the supposition of God as composed of matter, as follows. Because there is no way to avoid the demonstration that there is an eternal knowing being, people who are devoted to matter would be glad to have it granted that this knowing being is material; and then, letting slide out of their minds the proof that an eternal knowing being necessarily exists, they would argue that everything is matter and be led by that to deny a God, that is, to deny that there is an eternal cogitative being. [The section concludes with a somewhat obscure argument that materialists whose minds move in that way ‘destroy their own hypothesis’. It seems to overlap the first half of section 15.]

14. But now let us see how they can satisfy themselves or others that this eternal thinking being is material.

First, I would ask them: Do you imagine that all matter, every particle of matter, thinks? They’ll hardly say Yes, I think, for then there would be as many eternal thinking beings as there are particles of matter, and so an infinity of gods. And yet if they won’t allow matter as matter, i.e. every

244

Essay IV John Locke Chapter x: knowledge of a god

particle of matter, to be cogitative as well as extended, they will find that making a cogitative being out of incogitative particles is as hard for them to make sense of as making an extended being out of unextended parts.

15. Secondly, if not all matter thinks I next ask whether it is only one atom that does so? This has as many absurdities as the preceding proposal, and here is why. Either this one ·thinking· atom of matter is the only eternal one or it isn’t. If it alone is eternal, then it alone must, through its powerful thought or will, have made all the rest of matter. And so we have the creation of matter by a powerful thought, which is just what the materialists object to. For if they suppose that one thinking atom produced all the rest of matter, they must suppose that it was able to do this because of its thinking, since this is the only supposed difference between it and the rest of matter. (Even if they suppose it to have come about in some other way that is above our conception, it would still be creation, and these ·materialist· men must give up their great maxim that Nothing is made out of nothing.) ‘Perhaps all the rest of matter is eternal along with that thinking atom—this would have to be said by someone who is irresponsibly determined to say something, however absurd; for to suppose that all matter is eternal and yet one small particle is infinitely above all the rest in knowledge and power is to say something that hasn’t the faintest chance of being supported by a respectable theory [Locke wrote: ‘is without any the least appearance of reason to frame any hypothesis’]. Every particle of matter, as matter, is capable of all the same shapes and movements as any other; and I challenge anyone, in his thoughts, to add anything else to one particle in preference to another.

16. Thirdly, given that this eternal thinking being isn’t •one special atom alone, and isn’t •all matter as matter, i.e. every particle of matter, the only remaining possibility ·if it is to be made of matter somehow· is for it to be •a certain system of matter suitably put together. Those who think of God as a material being are most likely to have this view of him, because it’s the view most readily suggested to them by their ordinary view of themselves and of other men, whom they take to be material thinking beings. But however much more natural this view is, it is no less absurd than the others; for to suppose the eternal thinking being to be nothing but a composition of particles of matter each of which is incogitative is to ascribe all the wisdom and knowledge of that eternal being only to how its parts are put together; and nothing can be more absurd than that. Putting unthinking particles of matter together, however it is done, can’t add anything to them except new spatial relations, and it is impossible that those should give them thought and knowledge.

17. Furthermore, either •this corporeal system has all its parts at rest, or •its thinking consists in a certain motion of its parts. If •it is completely at rest, it is simply one lump, and so can have no privileges above one atom.

If •its thinking depends on the motion of its parts, all the thoughts there must be unavoidably accidental and limited. Here is why. Each of the particles whose movements ·supposedly· cause thought is itself without thought, so it can’t regulate its own movements; nor can it be regulated by the thought of the whole system, because that thought •results from the movements of the particles and so can’t •cause them. ·In the absence of any regulation, then· freedom, power, choice, and all rational and wise thinking or acting will be quite taken away. Such a thinking being will be no better or wiser than mere blind matter; because bringing everything down to

245

Essay IV John Locke Chapter x: knowledge of a god

•thought depending on unguided motions of blind matter

is the same as bringing it down to

•accidental unguided motions of blind matter.

Not to mention the narrowness of any thoughts and knowledge that depend on the movements of such parts. But I needn’t go through any more absurdities and impossibilities in this hypothesis (however full of them it may be); the one I have presented is enough. Whether this thinking system is a part of the matter in the universe or is all of it, no one particle ·in it· can possibly know its own movements or those of any other particle; nor can the whole thing know the motion of every particle and so regulate its own thoughts or motions, or indeed have any thought resulting from such motion.

18. Others hold that matter is eternal, although they also allow an eternal, cogitative, immaterial being. Let us consider this a little: it doesn’t take away the existence of a God, but it denies the first great piece of his workmanship, namely the creation. Matter—·they say·—must be conceded to be eternal. Why? Because you can’t conceive how it can be made out of nothing; ·then· why do you not also think that you are eternal? You may answer ‘Because about twenty or forty years ago I began to be’. But if I ask ‘What is this you that came into existence at that time?’ you can hardly tell me. The matter of which you are made didn’t begin to exist at that time, for if it did then it isn’t eternal. So what happened then was that the matter of which you are made began to be put together in such a way as to constitute your body; but that construct of particles isn’t you, it doesn’t constitute the thinking thing that you are. (I am now arguing with someone who, while holding that unthinking matter is eternal, allows that there is an eternal, immaterial thinking being ·and so presumably doesn’t hold that any thinking being is material·.) Well, then, when did that thinking thing begin to exist? If it never began to exist, then have you been a thinking thing from eternity! I needn’t argue for the absurdity of that until I meet someone who is stupid enough to assert it. If therefore you allow that •a thinking thing might be made out of nothing (as all things that aren’t eternal must be), why can’t you also allow that •a material being might be made out of nothing, by an equal power? Is it just that you have had experience of the former ·in the coming into existence of human beings·, and no experience of the latter? Actually, when we think about it we find that the creation of a spirit requires as much power as the creation of matter. Indeed, if we were to free ourselves from everyday notions, and raise our thoughts as far as possible to a closer contemplation of things, we might be able to aim at some dim and seeming conception of how matter might at first be made, how it might begin to exist by the power of the eternal first being; whereas to bring a spirit into existence would turn out to be a more inconceivable effect of omnipotent power....

19. ‘But’, you will say, ‘isn’t it impossible to suppose that something should be made out of nothing, since we can’t possibly conceive it?’ I answer, No, because it isn’t reasonable to deny the power of an infinite being merely because we can’t understand its operations. We don’t deny other effects because we can’t conceive how they are brought about. We can’t conceive how a body can be moved by anything other than the impact of another body, but that isn’t a good enough reason for us to deny that it is possible—·especially· given our constant experience of our own voluntary movements, which are produced in us purely by the free action or thought of our own minds. Such a movement can’t be an effect of the impact of blind matter on our own bodies or of movements of such matter within our bodies; for then it couldn’t be

246

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xi: knowledge of other things

in our power or choice to alter it. My right hand writes, while my left hand is still: what causes movement in one, and rest in the other? Nothing but my will, a thought of my mind. With a change in my thought and nothing else, the right hand rests and the left hand moves. This is a matter of fact that cannot be denied: Explain this and make it intelligible, and then the next step will be to understand creation! Some people explain voluntary motion in terms of alterations in the movements of the animal spirits, but this doesn’t solve the problem; it merely pushes it back to the question of what causes the changes in the movements of the animal spirits.... [Locke followed Descartes and others in believing that animal physiology involves the movements of ‘animal spirits’, conceived as an extremely rarefied and fast-moving fluid.]

Anyway, it is an overvaluing of ourselves to reduce everything to the narrow measure of our capacities, and to conclude that whatever we can’t understand is impossible. Limit •what God can do to •what we can conceive of his doing and you either make our understanding infinite or make God finite! If you don’t understand the •operations of your own finite mind, don’t be surprised that you can’t understand •the operations of the eternal infinite mind who made and governs all things and whom the heaven of heavens cannot contain.

Chapter xi: knowledge of the existence of other things

1. We know of our own existence by intuition, and our certain knowledge that a God exists comes through reason, ·i.e. by demonstration·, as I have shown.

We can know of the existence of other things only by sensation. No idea you have in your mind has any necessary connection with any real existence; and your existence has no necessary connection with the existence of anything except God. Therefore the only way you can know that anything else exists is through its actually operating on you, making itself perceived by you. Merely having the idea of a thing in your mind no more proves its existence than the picture of a man is evidence of his existence in the world, or than the visions of a dream make a true history.

2. The fact that we get ideas from outside ourselves is what informs us of the existence of other things; it tells us that at that time something external to us exists and causes those ideas in us, though we may not know—or even give any thought to—how it does that. The certainty of our senses and of the ideas we receive through them is not lessened by our not knowing how the ideas are produced. For example, while I write these words something produces in my mind—through the effects of the paper on my eyes—an idea that leads me to call white whatever object causes it; and from this I know that on this occasion some object outside me has the quality whose appearance before my eyes always causes that kind of idea. The best assurance I can have, the best my faculties are capable of, is the testimony of my eyes; they are the proper and sole judges of this thing. I have reason to rely on their testimony as being so certain that I

247

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xi: knowledge of other things

can no more •doubt that while I write this I see white and black and something really exists that causes that sensation in me, than I can •doubt that I write or that I move my hand. This is a certainty as great as human nature is capable of concerning the existence of anything except oneself and God.

3. The information that our senses give us concerning the existence of things outside us, although it isn’t quite as certain as our intuitive knowledge, or as what we know through deductive reasoning using our own clear abstract ideas, is still secure enough to deserve to be called ‘knowledge’. If we convince ourselves that our faculties inform us truthfully about the existence of the objects that affect them, this can’t be regarded as an unjustified confidence. Nobody, I think, can genuinely be so sceptical as to be uncertain of the existence of the things that he sees and feels; and if anyone can doubt as much as that, he will never have any controversy with me, for he can never be sure I say anything that he disagrees with ·because he can’t even be sure that I exist·. As for myself, I think God has given me assurance enough of the existence of things outside me: I know which ways of relating to them will bring me pleasure and which will bring me pain, and that is a matter of great concern to me here on earth. We certainly can’t have better evidence than we do that our faculties don’t deceive us about the existence of material beings, for we can’t do anything except through our faculties—indeed, we can’t even talk of knowledge except with the help of those faculties that enable us to understand what knowledge is.

Furthermore, besides the assurance we have from our senses themselves that they don’t err in what they tell us about the existence of things outside us when we are affected by them, we have other, confirming reasons for the same conclusion.

4. First, it is obvious that those perceptions ·that we think are produced by outer things· are produced in us by exterior causes affecting our senses, because people who lack the organs of one of the senses can never have the ideas belonging to that sense produced in their minds. This is too obvious to be doubted. So we can be sure that those perceptions reach our minds through the organs of that sense ·from something external to those organs·. Clearly, the organs themselves don’t produce such ideas, for if they did then the eyes of a man in the dark would produce colours and his nose would smell roses in the winter, whereas in fact nobody experiences the taste of a pineapple till he goes to the ·West· Indies where it is, and tastes it.

5. Secondly, sometimes I find that I can’t avoid having those ideas produced in my mind. When my eyes are shut, I can choose to recall to my mind the ideas of light or the sun that former sensations have lodged in my memory, or choose to set such ideas aside and instead take into my ·imaginative· view the idea of the smell of a rose or the taste of sugar. But if at noon I turn my eyes towards the sun, I can’t avoid the ideas that the light or sun then produces in me. So there is a clear difference between •the ideas stored in my memory (over which, if they were only in my memory, I would always have the same power to call them up or set them aside as I choose) and •those that force themselves on me and that I can’t avoid having. The latter ideas—the ones I have whether I want them or not—must be produced in my mind by some exterior cause, and the brisk acting of some external objects whose power I can’t resist. Besides, everybody can see the difference in himself between having a memory of how the sun looks and actually looking at it. His perceptions of these two are so unalike that few of his ideas are easier to tell apart. This gives him certain knowledge that they are not

248

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xi: knowledge of other things

both memory or products purely of his mind, and that actual seeing has an external cause.

6. Thirdly, many ideas that are painful to have in the first instance can be remembered afterwards without the least distress. Thus the pain of heat or cold doesn’t upset us when the idea of it is revived in our minds ·in memory·, although it was very troublesome when we originally felt it, and troubles us again when it is actually repeated through the disorder that the external object causes in our bodies when it acts on them. Again, we remember the pains of hunger, thirst, or headache without any pain at all: if these were nothing but ideas floating in our minds, without the real existence of things affecting us from outside ourselves, we would either •never suffer from them or else always do so whenever we thought of them. The same holds for the pleasure that accompanies many of our actual sensations....

7. Fourthly, our senses often confirm each other’s reports concerning the existence of perceptible things outside us. If you see a fire, you may doubt whether it is anything but a mere fancy; but then you can feel it too, and be convinced by putting your hand into it. Your hand certainly could never be given such agonizing pain by a mere idea or imagined fancy, unless the pain is a fancy too! When your burn has healed, you can’t make the pain of it return merely by raising the idea of it in your memory or imagination.

·Here is an example of how the different senses confirm one another·. I see while I am writing this that I can change the appearance of the paper; and by planning what to write I can tell in advance what new idea the paper will exhibit the very next moment merely through my drawing my pen over it. Those new ·visual· ideas won’t appear—however hard my imagination works—if my hands remain still or if I move my pen but keep my eyes shut. Also, once those letters have been put onto the paper, I have no choice about afterwards seeing them as they are—that is, having the ideas of the letters I have actually written. This shows clearly that those ideas aren’t merely playthings of my imagination. The letters ·were made as a result of my mental decision to make them, so they· were made at the bidding of my own thoughts; but ·once they have come into existence· they don’t then obey my thoughts: they don’t cease to exist whenever I shall fancy it, but instead continue to affect my senses constantly and regularly according to the shapes that I put down on the page. A further point: the •sight of those written letters will draw from someone who reads them ·aloud· the very •sounds that I planned them to stand for; and that leaves little reason for doubt that the words I write really do exist outside me. ·The sounds that they cause me to hear couldn’t come from my imagination or my memory·. The letters will cause a long series of regular sounds to affect my ears—too long for my memory to be able to retain them in the right order; and ·because the sounds come to me whether I want them or not·, they couldn’t be the effect of my imagination.

8. After all this, will anyone be so sceptical as to distrust his senses, and to affirm that all we see and hear, feel and taste, think and do, during our whole lifetime is nothing but a long dream with no reality in it? If so, I ask such a person—who questions the existence of all things or our knowledge of anything—to consider that if everything is a dream then he is only dreaming that he is raising this question, so that it doesn’t matter much that he should be answered by someone who is awake. However, he may if he likes dream that I answer him as follows. The testimony of our senses that there are things existing in nature gives us as much assurance of this as we are capable of, and as much as we need. For our faculties are not suited to

249

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xi: knowledge of other things

the entire range of what is the case, or to a perfect, clear, comprehensive knowledge of things, free from all doubts and worries. But they are suited to the preservation of us whose faculties they are; they are serviceable enough for everyday purposes, because they let us know for sure which things can help and which can hurt us. Someone who sees a candle burning, and has experienced the force of its flame by putting his finger in it, will have little doubt that this is something existing outside him that harms and greatly hurts him; and that is assurance enough, for no man requires greater certainty to govern his actions by than what is as certain as his actions themselves. ·I can be as sure that if I move thus and so I will feel pain as I can be that I shall move thus and so. We can’t need more certainty about what our actions will •lead to than we have about what our actions will •be·. If our dreamer wonders whether the glowing heat of a glass furnace is merely a wandering imagination in a drowsy man’s fancy, he can test this by putting his hand into it. If he does, he will be wakened into a certainty—a greater one than he would wish!—that it is something more than mere imagination. So we have all the assurance that we can want—enough to enable us to steer our course in relation to pleasure and pain, i.e. happiness and misery; and these are all we need be concerned about in theory or in practice. Such an assurance of the existence of things outside us is sufficient to direct us in the attaining the good and avoiding the evil that is caused by them; and this is what really matters to us in our acquaintance with them.

9. In brief, when our senses bring an idea into our understandings, we can’t help being confident that at that time something really exists outside us—something that affects our senses, and through them alerts us to its existence by producing the idea that we perceive. We can’t distrust the testimony of our senses so far as to doubt that such collections of simple ideas [here = ‘qualities’] as we have observed to be united together really do exist together. But this knowledge doesn’t extend beyond the present testimony of our senses regarding particular objects that are affecting them now. If one minute ago I saw a collection of simple ideas of the sort usually called ‘a man’ existing together, and if I am now alone, I can’t be certain that the same man exists now, since his existence a minute ago doesn’t necessitate his existing now. In any of a thousand ways he could have ceased to exist since I had the testimony of my senses for his existence. And if I can’t be certain that the man I last saw earlier today still exists, still less can I be certain of the present existence of one I haven’t seen since yesterday or since last year—let alone one that I never saw. I conclude that although it is highly probable that millions of men now exist, yet while I am alone in my study writing this I am not certain enough of this to say that I know it to be so. It is so likely to be the case that I have no doubt of it, and I can reasonably act on my confidence that there are men in the world (and indeed some whom I know, and with whom I have various relations); but still this is only ·very high· probability, not knowledge.

10. This shows how foolish and pointless it is for a man who doesn’t know much, but who has been given the faculty of reason to judge how probable things are and to be swayed accordingly, to expect demonstration and certainty in things that aren’t capable of it, and to refuse assent to very reasonable propositions and act contrary to very plain and clear truths, simply because they can’t be made so evident as to surmount every the least (I won’t say •reason, but) •pretence of doubting. If anyone brought that attitude to the ordinary affairs of life, accepting nothing that hadn’t been plainly demonstrated, he would be sure of nothing in this

250

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xi: knowledge of other things

world except an early death. The wholesomeness of his meat or drink wouldn’t give him reason to risk it. What indeed could he do on grounds that were capable of no doubt, no objection?

11. Just as when our senses are actually employed on any object we know that it exists, so also by our memory we may be assured that things that affected our senses in the past have existed. In this way we have knowledge of the past existence of various things of which, our senses having informed us of them, our memories still retain the ideas; and we are past all doubt about this so long as we remember well. But this knowledge reaches no further than our senses have formerly assured us. Thus seeing water right now it is an unquestionable truth to me that water now exists; and remembering that I saw it yesterday it will also be always true that water existed on the 10th of July, 1688, and as long as my memory retains this it will always be an undoubted proposition to me. Just as it will also be equally true that a certain number of very fine colours existed which at the same time I saw on a bubble of that water. But, being now out of sight both the water and the bubbles, it is no more certainly known to me that the water now exists than that the colours or the bubbles do. For it is no more necessary that water should exist today because it existed yesterday than that the colours or bubbles exist today because they existed yesterday; though the former is ever so much more probable, because water has been observed to stay in existence for a long time whereas bubbles and the colours on them quickly cease to be.

12. I have already shown what ideas we have of spirits [= ‘minds’], and how we come to have them. But though we have those ideas in our minds and know we have them there, merely having ideas of spirits doesn’t make us know that any such things exist outside us, or that there are any finite spirits or any other spiritual beings in addition to the eternal God. We can no more know that finite spirits really exist purely through having the idea we have of them in our minds than we could come to know that there really are fairies or centaurs purely through having ideas of them. Divine revelation and other reasons entitle me to be sure that God has created finite spirits ·other than myself·; but I am not able to know what particular spirits there are, because my senses can’t pick them out.

Concerning the existence of finite spirits, therefore, as well as many other things, we must be content with the evidence of faith; we can never establish for certain any universal propositions on this topic. It might be true that (for instance) all the thinking spirits that God ever created still exist, but this can never be something we know for certain. We can assent to propositions like that as highly probable, but I am afraid that in our earthly state we cannot know them. So we shouldn’t demand (of others or of ourselves) conclusive proofs or universal certainty in these matters about which we can have only such knowledge as our senses give us in this or that particular case.

13. So it turns out that there are two sorts of propositions. 1 One sort says that there exists something that conforms to such and such an idea. When I have the idea of an elephant, a phoenix, motion, or an angel in my mind, I naturally want to know: Does such a thing exist anywhere? This knowledge is only about particulars. Our senses give us all the information we can have about the existence of things outside us, with the sole exception of God ·whose existence I have proved·. 2 The other sort of proposition expresses relations amongst our abstract ideas—how they agree with one another or depend on one another. Propositions of this

251

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xi: knowledge of other things

kind may be universal and certain. For example, having the ideas of •God and •myself, and of •fear and •obedience, I can’t help being sure that God is to be feared and obeyed by me; and this proposition will hold for certain regarding all men—that is, all men who belong to the species (of which I am a member) that is defined by my abstract idea of humanity. Still, this proposition that men ought to fear and obey God, however certain I may be of it, doesn’t prove to me that there are any men in the world; the proposition is simply true of all the men that there are, whenever they exist, ·so that it could be true even if there were no men·. What makes such general propositions certain is the agreement or disagreement we can find amongst the abstract ideas that they involve ·and not any facts about particular things to which those ideas apply·.

14. With 1 the former kind of proposition, our knowledge is the consequence of the existence of things that produce ideas in our minds through our senses. With 2 the latter, knowledge results from the production in our minds of general certain propositions by our ideas (whatever they may be). Many of these are called ‘eternal truths’, and all of them indeed are eternally true, ·but let us be careful about why that is so·. It is not that all of them—or indeed that any of them—were written in the minds of all men, or that any of them were propositions in anyone’s mind until he had acquired the relevant abstract ideas and joined or separated them by affirmation or negation. Rather, ·they are eternal truths because· wherever we can suppose that such a creature as man exists, endowed with faculties that men have and provided by those faculties with ideas such as we have, we must conclude that when that creature applies his thoughts to his ideas he must know the truth of certain propositions that will arise from the agreement or disagreement he will perceive in his own ideas. Such propositions are therefore called ‘eternal truths’, not because they are eternal propositions that were actually formed in advance of anyone’s having them in his thought, nor because they are imprinted on the mind from patterns that already existed outside the mind, but because if such a proposition is made about abstract ideas in such a way as to be true, it is always actually true when, at any earlier or later time, someone has those same ideas and makes that same proposition. For names being supposed to stand perpetually for the same ideas, and the same ideas having unchangingly the same relations one to another, a proposition concerning abstract ideas must be eternally true if it is ever true.

252

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xii: Improvement of knowledge

Chapter xii: The improvement of our knowledge

1. Among men of letters it has been the standard view that maxims are the foundation of all knowledge, and that every science [= ‘branch of knowledge’] is built on certain praecognita [= ‘things known in advance’] which give the understanding its first lift and by which it is to conduct itself in its enquiries. That is why the standard practice of the schools has been to lay down in the beginning one or more general propositions, as foundations on which to build the knowledge that can be had in the science concerned. These doctrines, thus laid down as foundations for a science, were called ‘principles’, because they were supposed to be the •beginnings from which we must set out, looking no further backwards in our enquiries. [The word ‘principle’ comes from Latin meaning •‘first’.]

2. This approach seemed to succeed in mathematics. It was seen that in these sciences a great certainty of knowledge was achieved, which is why they came to be dignified with the title ‘Mathemata’ [Locke gives it in Greek], meaning learning, or things learned, thoroughly learned, because these have greater certainty, clearness, and self-evidentness than any other science. This success may have encouraged the ‘principles’ approach in other sciences as well.

3. But if you look into this I think you’ll find that the great advancement and certainty of real knowledge that men achieved in the mathematical sciences was not due to the influence of these principles, or derived from any special advantage the mathematicians got from two or three general maxims laid down in the beginning. Rather, it came from the clear, distinct, complete ideas that their thoughts were engaged with, and from the fact that the relations of ‘equals’ and ‘greater than’ between some pairs of them were so clear that the mathematicians knew them intuitively, which gave them a way to discover such relations between other pairs ·by demonstration·—all this being done without the help of maxims. I ask you: can’t a young lad know that his whole body is bigger than his little finger without help from the axiom that the whole is bigger than a part? Can’t a country girl know that when she has received a shilling from someone who owes her three, and a shilling from someone else who also owes her three, the remaining debts are equal? To know this must she rely on the maxim that if you take equals from equals, the remainder will be equals, which she may never have heard or thought of? On the basis of what I have said earlier—·in vii.4 and 11·—ask yourself: which is known first and most clearly by most people, the particular instance or the general rule? Which of these gives life and birth to the other? [The section then repeats things Locke has said earlier about how the mind starts with particulars and gradually works towards general ideas and general propositions. It concludes:] When he has acquired these names, how is he more certain that •his body is a whole and his little finger a part than he could have been, before he learnt those terms, that •his body was bigger than his little finger? It is as reasonable to question whether your little finger is a part of your body as that it is smaller than your body; and someone who doubts the latter is sure to doubt the former as well. So the maxim The whole is bigger than a part can never be used to prove that the little finger is smaller than the body except when it is useless, being used to convince someone of a truth that he knows already....

[In section 4 Locke begins by saying, in effect: Pretend to be satisfied that mathematics has achieved its success through

253

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xii: Improvement of knowledge

starting with maxims, because mathematicians have had the good luck or good judgment to use only maxims that are self-evident and undeniable. Still the question arises whether this (supposed) fact about mathematics makes it safe for us to] take the principles that are laid down in any other branch of knowledge as unquestionable truths, to accept them without examination, and stick to them without allowing them to be called in to question. ·The answer is that it is not safe·. If we proceed in this way, who knows what will get accepted as truths in morality or as ‘proved’ in physics!

Let the principle of some of the ancient philosophers that All is matter, and there is nothing else be accepted as certain and indubitable, and you can easily see from the writings of some who have revived it in our day what consequences it will lead us into! Let anyone equate God with the world (Polemo), with the ether or the sun (the stoics), or with the air (Anaximenes), and what a divinity, religion and worship we shall end up with! Nothing is as dangerous as principles taken up uncritically, especially when they concern morality, influence men’s lives and shape all their actions. [Then some examples of differing philosophical views that could be expected to lead to different kinds of conduct.]

5. So if we take propositions that are not certain and treat them as principles on the basis of nothing but our blind assent, we are liable to be misled by them; and instead of being guided into truth we shall only be confirmed in error,

6. The knowledge of the certainty of principles, as well as of all other truths, depends purely on our perception of the agreement or disagreement of our ideas; so the way to improve our knowledge is not to receive and swallow principles blindly and with an implicit faith; but it is, rather, to get and fix in our minds as many clear, distinct, and complete ideas as we can, and to give each of them its own constant name. Just by considering those perfect ideas, and finding their agreements and disagreements and their various intrinsic natures and relations to one another, we shall get more clear knowledge than by taking up ·second-hand· principles and thereby putting our minds at the disposal of others.

7. If we want to proceed as reason advises, therefore, we must adapt our methods of enquiry to the nature of the ideas we are examining and the truth we are searching for. General and certain truths are based purely on the natures and relations of abstract ideas; our only way to learn such truths is by judiciously and methodically applying our thoughts to finding out these relations. We can learn how to go about this from the mathematicians: from very plain and easy beginnings they proceed, gradually and through a continued chain of reasonings, to the discovery and demonstration of truths that at first sight seem beyond human capacity. What has carried them so far, and produced such wonderful and unexpected discoveries, is the art of finding proofs, and the admirable methods they have invented for finding and ordering the intermediate ideas that demonstratively show the equality or inequality of quantities that can’t be directly related to one another. I shan’t discuss whether something like this may eventually be found to be possible with other ideas, ones that are not quantitative. But I will say this much: if other ideas that are the real as well as the nominal essences of their species were pursued in the way familiar to mathematicians, they would carry our thoughts further, with results that are more evident and clearer, than we are apt to imagine.

8. This gave me the confidence to advance my conjecture (in chapter iii) that morality is open to demonstration, as well as mathematics. For the ideas that ethics deals with ·are all

254

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xii: Improvement of knowledge

ideas of mixed modes, and so· are all real essences, and such as I imagine have discoverable connections and agreements with one another; so that as far as we can find their natures and relations so far we shall come to know truths that are certain, real, and general. I am sure that if a right method were adopted a great part of morality might be made out with such clearness that a thoughtful person would have no more reason to doubt it than he could have to doubt of the truth of demonstrated propositions in mathematics.

9. In our search for knowledge of substances we have to use a quite different method, because we don’t have ideas ·of substances· that are suitable for the way of proceeding that I have just described. In the latter (where our abstract ideas are real as well as nominal essences), we advance by contemplating our ideas and attending to their relations and correspondences with one another; but that gives us very little help with substances, for the reasons that I explain in detail elsewhere. So I think it is evident that substances can’t be the subjects of much general knowledge, and that merely thinking about their abstract ideas will take us only a very little way in the search for truth and certainty. Then how are we to add to our knowledge of substantial beings? Here we must take a quite contrary course; the lack of ideas of the real essences of substances sends us from our own thoughts to the things themselves as they exist. Experience here must teach me what reason can’t: it is only by testing that I can know for sure what other qualities co-exist with those of my complex idea—for example, whether the yellow, heavy, fusible body that I call ‘gold’ is malleable. And the answer that experience gives in a particular case doesn’t make me certain that it will be the same for any yellow, heavy, fusible bodies that I haven’t yet tested. My complex idea of gold gives me no help with that: the combination of that colour, weight, and fusibility in a body does not visibly imply or rule out malleability. [Locke goes on to say that if we become confident that all gold is malleable, we may include malleability in our nominal definition of gold; but that still won’t help us to establish with certainty any truths stating that further qualities—ones not included in the newly enriched nominal definition—are possessed by all samples of gold.]

10. I don’t deny that a man who is accustomed to rational and regular experiments will be able to see further into the nature of bodies, and guess more accurately their yet unknown properties, than one who is a stranger to them. But yet, as I have said ·in vi.13·, this is only judgment and opinion, not knowledge and certainty. This way of getting and improving our knowledge of substances, purely through experience and history, is all that the weakness of our faculties can attain to; and it makes me suspect that natural philosophy [= ‘physics’] isn’t capable of being made a science [= ‘a highly organized system with a disciplined structure’]....

11.....Since our faculties are not fitted to penetrate into the internal structure and real essences of bodies, but clearly do show us the existence of a God and give us enough knowledge of ourselves to lead us into a full and clear discovery of our duty and of what matters most to us, it is appropriate for us as rational creatures to employ our faculties on what they are best adapted to, and follow the direction of nature where it seems to show us the way. For it is reasonable to conclude that we ought to pursue the sort of knowledge that is most suited to our natural capacities, and carries with it our greatest interest, i.e. our means to achieving eternal life. From which I conclude that morality is the proper science and business of mankind in general; just as various studies regarding various parts of nature are

255

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xii: Improvement of knowledge

suitable for the special talents of particular men, for the common use of human life and for their own survival in this world. [The section continues by presenting an example of how important the knowledge of ‘one natural body’ can be to human life. Although America abounds in natural goods, and its native inhabitants are naturally as able as Europeans are, the level of their lives is much lower than that of people in more developed countries; and this difference is largely due to their not having the use of iron. The section concludes:] So that he who first made known the use of that humble mineral may be truly styled the father of arts and author of prosperity. [In this sentence ‘arts’ covers every kind of craft, mechanical skill, technique of manufacture, and so on.]

12. So don’t think that I want to discourage the study of nature. I readily agree that contemplating God’s works can lead us to admire, revere, and glorify him. (And if this is done properly it can be of greater benefit to mankind than the expensive and conspicuous charitable efforts of those who found hospitals and shelters for the homeless. He who first invented printing, discovered the use of the compass, or made public the powers of quinine and the right way to use it, did more to propagate knowledge, to supply and increase useful commodities, and to save people from the grave, than those who built colleges, work-houses, and hospitals.) My point is just that •we shouldn’t be too confident in claiming to have knowledge, or in expecting to get it, in areas where it cannot be had, or not by the ways we are following. And that •we shouldn’t take doubtful systems to be complete sciences, or unintelligible notions to be disciplined demonstrations. In the knowledge of bodies, we must be content to glean what we can from particular experiments, because we don’t know the real essences that would enable us (if we knew them) to pick up whole sheaves of bodies at a time, and understand the nature and properties of whole species together, in bundles. Where our enquiry concerns co-existence or impossibility of co-existence, which we can’t discover by studying our ideas, there experience, observation, and natural history must give us through our senses an insight into corporeal substances, taken one a time. The knowledge of •bodies we must get by our senses, using them alertly in observing bodies’ qualities and operations on one another. As for our knowledge of •unembodied Spirits in this world, I think we must look to revelation for that. When you consider the record of general maxims, precarious principles, and hypotheses laid down at pleasure—how little they have, through the ages, advanced men’s progress towards knowledge in natural science—you will think we have reason to thank those who in this latter age have marked out another path to us, not an easier way to learned ignorance but a surer way to profitable knowledge.

13. This isn’t to deny that we can explain natural phenomena by making use of any probable hypothesis whatever. Hypotheses, if they are well made, are great helps to the memory, and they often direct us to new discoveries. My point is just that when we want to penetrate into the causes of things and have principles to rely on, we are very apt to adopt an hypothesis too hastily, before thoroughly examining particular instances and making various experiments with the thing we are trying to explain by our hypothesis, in order to see whether it agrees with them all. The question is whether our ‘principle’—·which is what we may call our hypothesis·—will carry us the whole way through, rather than seeming to accommodate and explain one phenomenon of nature while being inconsistent with another. At least we should take care that the name ‘principle’ doesn’t deceive us or impose on us, by making us accept as an unquestionable truth something that is really, at best, only a very doubtful

256

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xii: Improvement of knowledge

conjecture. That is what most (I almost said ‘all’) of the hypotheses in natural science are.

14. But whether or not natural science is capable of certainty, there seem to me to be just two ways to increase our knowledge, as far as we can do so at all.

The first is to get and settle in our minds determinate ideas of all the things for which we have general or specific names—or anyway all that we want to think about, know more about, or reason about. And if they are specific ideas of substances, we should try to make them as complete as we can, putting together as many simple ideas as are constantly observed to co-exist and can perfectly pick out the species. And each of the simple ideas that are the ingredients of our complex ones should be clear and distinct in our minds. Obviously our knowledge can’t outrun our ideas; so as far as they are either imperfect, confused, or obscure, we can’t expect to have certain, perfect, or clear knowledge.

The second is the art of finding out intermediate ideas that can show us the agreement or mutual inconsistency of other ideas that can’t be immediately inter-related.

15. These two (and not reliance on maxims and inference from general propositions) are the right methods of increasing our knowledge involving the ideas of •non-quantitative modes. We learn this from considering mathematical knowledge, ·which involves ideas of •quantitative modes·. It is in mathematics that we first find that ·knowledge requires good ideas; for example, that· someone who doesn’t have perfect and clear ideas of the angles or figures that he wants to investigate is thereby made utterly incapable of any knowledge about them.... Furthermore, what led the masters of that science into the wonderful discoveries they have made was obviously not the influence of the maxims that are taken to be principles in mathematics. Suppose that an intelligent man has a perfect knowledge of all the maxims that are generally used in mathematics, and that he thinks about them and their consequences as much as he pleases: I don’t think that this will lead him to know that the square on the hypotenuse of a right-angled triangle is equal to ·the sum of· the squares on the two other sides! The knowledge that The whole is equal to ·the sum of· all its parts and If you take equals from equals, the remainders will be equal won’t help him to this demonstration; and I don’t think that any amount of poring over those axioms would add a scrap to one’s knowledge of mathematical truths.... When people first got knowledge of truths in mathematics, their minds were aiming at things other than—aiming in a direction different from—maxims. Anyone who is well acquainted with those received axioms ·or maxims·, but ignorant of the methods first used to demonstrate mathematical truths, are astonished by the results that the mathematicians have achieved. Algebra easily finds out ideas of quantities to measure other quantities by—ones whose equality or proportion we might never be able to know without the help of algebra. Well, who knows what methods for increasing our knowledge in other parts of science may some day be invented, corresponding to the method of algebra in mathematics?

257

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xiii: Other points about knowledge

Chapter xiii: Some other considerations concerning our knowledge

1. Our knowledge is like our sight in several respects, including this: it is neither wholly •necessary nor wholly •voluntary. If our knowledge were altogether •necessary, not only would all men’s knowledge be alike, but every man would know all that is knowable; and if it were wholly •voluntary, some men—the ones who put little value on it—would have extremely little or none at all. Men that have senses can’t help receiving some ideas through them; and if they have memory they can’t help retaining some of them; and if they have any distinguishing faculty, they can’t help perceiving the agreement or disagreement of some ideas with one another. Similarly, if a sighted person opens his eyes by day he can’t help seeing some objects, and perceiving differences amongst them. But there are certain objects that he may choose whether to look at; there may be within reach a book containing pictures and text that he may never decide to open.

2. Here is another thing in a man’s power: when he turns his eyes towards an object, he can choose whether he will look at it intently, trying to observe accurately all that is visible in it. But what he does see, he can’t see otherwise than he does. It’s not for him to decide to see as black something that appears yellow, and he can’t convince himself that what actually scalds him feels cold.... That’s how it is with our understanding: we voluntarily choose whether to employ our faculties on this topic rather than that, and whether to make a more or a less accurate survey of it. But when they are being employed, our will has no power to affect the knowledge of the mind one way or another; that is done only by the objects themselves, as far as they are clearly revealed. And therefore, as far as men’s senses are engaged on external objects, the mind has to receive the ideas that are presented by them, and be informed of the existence of things outside it. And so far as men’s thoughts are engaged on their own determined ideas, they can’t help observing to some extent the agreements and disagreements that are to be found amongst some of them—and that, as far as it goes, is knowledge. And if they have names for the ideas that they have thus considered, they can’t help being assured of the truth of the propositions that express the agreement or disagreement they perceive in them. For what a man sees, he cannot but see; and what he perceives, he cannot but know that he perceives.

3. Thus someone who has the ideas of numbers, and has taken the trouble to compare one, two, and three to six, can’t help knowing that they are equal. Someone who has acquired the idea of a triangle, and found the ways to measure its angles, is certain that its three angles are equal to two right ones, and can no more be in doubt about that than about this truth, that It is impossible for the same thing to be and not to be.

And someone who has the idea of

•a thinking but frail and weak being, made by and depending on •someone else who is eternal, omnipotent, perfectly wise and good

will know that •man is to honour, fear, and obey •God as certainly as he knows when the sun shines that he sees it. For if he has the ideas of two such beings in his mind, and consents to turn his thoughts onto them, he will as certainly find that the inferior, finite and dependent is under an obligation to obey the supreme and infinite as he is certain to find that three, four, and seven are less than fifteen if he

258

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xiii: Other points about knowledge

chooses to compute those numbers. Nor can he be surer on a clear morning that the sun has risen, if he chooses to open his eyes and turn them that way. Still, he may be ignorant of either or all of these truths—certain and clear as they are—if he doesn’t take the trouble to employ his faculties, as he should, to inform himself about them.

259

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xiv: Judgment

Chapter xiv: Judgment

1. The understanding faculties were given to man not merely for the pursuit of true theories but also for the conduct of his life. He would be at a great loss ·in his life· if he had nothing to direct him except certain knowledge. For that is very scanty, as we have seen: he would often be utterly in the dark, and in most of the actions of his life he would be brought to a halt, if he had nothing to guide him in the absence of clear and certain knowledge. Someone who refuses to eat until he can prove rigorously that the food will nourish him, who won’t move until he infallibly knows that his project will succeed, will have little to do except to sit still and die.

2. God has put some things in •broad daylight, giving us some certain knowledge, so that we have a taste of what thinking creatures are capable of (they are probably capable of ever so much more), intending this to make us want and try to be in a better state. But for most of our concerns he has allowed us only the •twilight (so to speak) of probability. This is suitable for the state—neither high nor low, and only provisional—that God has been pleased to place us in here. He has wanted to restrain our over-confidence and presumption, letting every day’s experience make us conscious of how short-sighted we are and how liable to error. That should be a constant warning to us that we should devote our present life on earth to trying hard and carefully to find and then follow the way that might lead us to a state of greater perfection. For even if revelation were silent about this, it would be highly rational to think that to the extent that men employ the talents God has given them here ·on earth·, they will be correspondingly rewarded at the close of the day, when their sun sets and night brings their labours to an end.

3. The faculty that God has given to man, to make up for the lack of clear and certain knowledge iwhere that can’t be had, is judgment. Using this, the mind takes its ideas to agree or disagree—that is, takes a proposition to be true or false—without proofs that it perceives as demonstratively selfevident. The mind employs judgment •sometimes because it must, where demonstrative proofs and certain knowledge are not to be had; and •sometimes out of laziness, lack of skill, or haste, in cases where demonstrative and certain proofs are to be had. Men often fail to take the time needed to examine the agreement or disagreement of two ideas that interest them. Either they are incapable of the attention needed for a long train of argument, or they are merely impatient; either way, they skim through the proof or even ignore it entirely, and settle for whatever conclusion—holding that the ideas agree or that they disagree—on the basis of what, from the quick look they have had, seems to them most likely. When this faculty of the mind is exercised immediately about things, it is called judgment; when exercised about things that are said it is most commonly called assent or dissent. As the latter is the most usual way in which the mind has occasion to employ this faculty, I shall discuss it in terms of ‘assent’ and ‘dissent’....

4. Thus the mind has two faculties having to do with truth and falsehood.

First, knowledge, whereby it certainly perceives and is satisfied beyond doubt of the agreement or disagreement of any ideas.

Secondly, judgment, which is putting together or separat-

260

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xv: Probability

ing ideas in the mind when their agreement or disagreement isn’t perceived but is presumed to be so—taken to be so before its truth certainly appears, as the word implies [‘presume’ comes from Latin meaning ‘take before’]. And if it unites or separates them in accordance with how things are in reality, it is right judgment.

Chapter xv: Probability

1. •Demonstration is showing the agreement or disagreement of two ideas by the intervention of one or more proofs, ·the separate links of· which have a constant, unchangeable, and visible connection with one another; and •probability is nothing but the appearance of such an agreement or disagreement, by the intervention of proofs whose connection isn’t perceived to be constant and unchangeable, but is or appears for the most part to be so, sufficiently to induce the mind to judge the proposition to be true or to be false. [Locke now sketches what happens when someone follows a demonstration of a geometrical theorem. Then:] But another man, who never took the trouble to follow the demonstration, hearing a respected mathematician affirm that the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles assents to this, i.e. accepts it as true. The foundation of his assent is the probability of the thing, on evidence of a kind that is usually reliable; because the man whose word he takes for it isn’t accustomed to affirm things that he doesn’t know to be true, especially in matters of this kind. So that what causes the other man’s assent to the proposition that the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles—what makes him take these ideas to agree, without knowing that they do so—is the usual truthfulness of the speaker in other cases, or his supposed truthfulness in this.

2. Our knowledge, as I have shown, is very narrow, and we are not so lucky as to find certain truth in everything we happen to think about; most of the propositions that we think with, reason with, use in discourse, and indeed act on, are ones of whose truth we can’t have undoubted knowledge. Yet some of them come so close to certainty that we have no doubt about them, and assent to them as firmly, and act (on that assent) as resolutely, as if they were infallibly demonstrated and our knowledge of them were perfect and certain. But here there are degrees ·of •confidence· from the very neighbourhood of certainty and demonstration right down to improbability and unlikelihood of truth, and down further to the brink of impossibility; and also degrees •of assent from full assurance and confidence right down to conjecture, doubt, and distrust. So now, following up my account of the limits of human knowledge and certainty, I shall discuss the various degrees and grounds of probability, and assent or faith.

3. Probability is likelihood of truth, and the etymological sense of the word signifies a proposition for which there are good enough arguments or proofs for it to be accepted as true. [The Latin source of ‘probable’ is probare = ‘prove’.] The mind’s acceptance of this sort of proposition is called ‘belief’,

261

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xvi: Degrees of assent

‘assent’, or ‘opinion’, ·or ‘faith’·, which is the receiving of a proposition as true on the strength of arguments or proofs that are persuasive but don’t give certain knowledge. The difference between •probability and •certainty, between •faith and •knowledge, is that in all the parts of knowledge there is intuition: each step involves a visible and certain connection; in belief ·or faith·, not so. What makes me believe is something extraneous to the thing I believe—something that doesn’t clearly show the agreement or disagreement of the ideas in question.

4. ....The grounds of probability are the two following. First, the conformity of something with our own knowledge, observation, and experience. Secondly, the testimony of others, vouching for something on the strength of their observation and experience. In ·evaluating· the testimony of others, we have to consider •how many of them there are, •whether they are honest, •whether they are intelligent, •what the author of the book from which the testimony is taken is up to, •whether the parts and circumstances of the testimony hang together, and •what contrary testimonies there are.

[In section 5 Locke says that judgments of probability should be based on all the evidence on each side. He brings out the element of subjectivity in this by contrasting two evaluations of the testimony ‘I have seen a man walking on the surface of water hardened by cold’—that of someone who has seen such things himself, and that of someone who lives in the tropics and has never experienced or before heard of ice.]

[Section 6 sums up the chapter, adding a warning against the common practice of judging something to be probable because many people accept it. The section concludes:] If the opinions of others whom we know and think well of constitute a ground of assent, men have reason to be heathens in Japan, Moslems in Turkey, Papists in Spain, Protestants in England, and Lutherans in Sweden. I shall say more about this wrong ground of assent later.

Chapter xvi: The degrees of assent

1. The grounds of probability laid down in the preceding chapter serve not only as the basis on which to decide whether to assent ·to a proposition· but also as the measure of how strongly we should assent. Bear in mind, though, that whatever grounds of probability there may be, they will operate on the truth-seeking mind only to the extent that they appear to it in its first judgment or its first look into the matter. I admit that in the opinions that men have and firmly stick to, their assent is not always based on a present view of the reasons that at first won them over; for in most cases it is hard—and in many almost impossible—for people, even ones with admirable memories, to retain all the proofs that initially made them embrace that side of the question. It suffices that they did once carefully and fairly sift the matter as far as they could, and that they have searched into everything that they can imagine might throw light on the question, and done

262

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xvi: Degrees of assent

their best to evaluate the evidence as a whole; and having thus once found on which side the probability appeared to them, after as full and exact an enquiry as they can make, they store the conclusion in their memories as a truth they have learned; and for the future they remain satisfied with the testimony of their memories that they have seen evidence for this opinion that entitles it to the degree of their assent that they are now giving to it.

2. This is all that most men are capable of doing, in regulating their opinions and judgments. ·And it is all we can ask them to do, because the only two alternatives are impossible·. •We could demand that a person retain clearly in his memory all the proofs concerning anything he finds probable, maintaining them in the same order and regular deduction of consequences in which he formerly placed them or saw them (and on one single question that might be enough to fill a book!). Or •we could require a man, for every opinion that he embraces, to re-examine the proofs every day. Both are impossible. So inevitably memory has to be relied on in these matters, and men are bound to have various confident opinions whose proofs are not at that moment in their thoughts—and perhaps whose proofs they can’t recall right then....

3. I have to admit that men’s sticking to their past judgments and adhering firmly to conclusions formerly made often leads them to be obstinate in maintaining errors and mistakes. But their fault is not that they rely on their memories for what they previously judged well, but that they judged before they had examined well. Can’t we find many men (perhaps even most men) who think they have formed right judgments on various matters, having no reason for this except that they never thought otherwise? Men who imagine themselves to have judged rightly only because they never questioned or examined their own opinions? Which amounts to saying that they think they judged rightly because they never judged at all. Yet these are just the ones who hold their opinions with the greatest stiffness, because in general those who are the most fierce and firm in their tenets are those who have least examined them. Once we know something, we are certain it is so; and we can rest assured that our knowledge won’t be overturned or called into doubt by lurking proofs that haven’t yet been discovered. But in matters of probability we can’t always be sure that we have taken account of everything that might be relevant to the question, and that there is no evidence still to be found which could turn the probability-scales the other way, and outweigh everything that now seems to us to carry the most weight. Who has the leisure, patience, and means to collect together all the proofs concerning most of the opinions he has, so as safely to conclude that he has a clear and full view, and that there’s nothing else that might come to light to change his mind? And yet we are forced to settle for one side or the other. The conduct of our lives and the management of our great concerns won’t allow delay....

4. So it is unavoidable, for most if not all men, to have various opinions without certain and indubitable proofs of their truth; and it would look like ignorance, lightness, or folly if men were always to give up their former beliefs the moment they are shown a counter-argument that they can’t immediately refute. This, I think, indicates that we in our diversity of opinions should all maintain peace and the ordinary procedures of humanity and friendship; for we can’t reasonably expect that anyone should promptly and humbly drop his own opinion and embrace ours with a blind resignation to an authority that he doesn’t acknowledge as an authority. However often the understanding goes wrong,

263

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xvi: Degrees of assent

it can’t accept any guide except reason, and can’t blindly submit to the will and dictates of another. If the person you want to win over to your opinions is •one who examines before he assents, you must allow him time to go over the account again, to recall points favouring his own side—ones he has currently forgotten—and to see on which side the advantage lies. And if he doesn’t think your arguments are good enough to indicate that he should take all that trouble reconsidering the matter, this is only what you often do in similar cases; and you wouldn’t like it if others told to you what points you should study. And if he is •one who takes his opinions on trust, how can we expect him to renounce the tenets that time and custom have so settled in his mind that he thinks them self-evident, or takes them to be things he was told by God himself or by God’s messengers? How can we expect that opinions that are settled in that way should be surrendered to the arguments or authority of a stranger or an adversary; especially if there is any suspicion that the adversary is up to something, as there always is when men think themselves ill treated? We should sympathize with one anothers’ ignorance and try to remove it by all the gentle and fair methods of instruction; and not instantly ill-treat others as obstinate and perverse because they won’t renounce their own opinions and accept the ones we are trying to force on them, when it is more than probable that we are at least as obstinate in not accepting some of theirs! For where is the man who has incontestable evidence of the truth of all his beliefs or of the falsehood of all the beliefs he condemns, or can say that he has examined to the bottom all his own opinions and everyone else’s? ·In our life· on this earth we are in a fleeting state of action and blindness, which requires us to •believe without •knowing, often indeed on very slight grounds; and this should make us work harder and more carefully to inform ourselves than to constrain others. At least those who haven’t thoroughly examined to the bottom all their own beliefs should admit that they are unfit to prescribe to others.... Those who have fairly and truly examined ·the grounds for their beliefs·, and have been brought by this beyond doubt about the doctrines they profess and live by, would have a fairer claim to require others to follow them. But there are so few of these, and they find so little reason to be dogmatic in their opinions, that nothing insolent and bullying is to be expected from them; and there is reason to think that ·in general· if men were better instructed themselves they wouldn’t push others around so much.

5. Returning now to the grounds of assent, and to the different degrees of it: the propositions we accept as probable are of two sorts. There are •propositions concerning some particular existence—usually called ‘matter of fact’—that could be observed and so admit of support from human testimony; and there are •ones concerning things that cannot have such support because they are beyond the discovery of our senses. ·I shall discuss the former in sections 6–11, and the latter in section 12·.

6. Concerning the first of these, namely particular matters of fact, ·I distinguish three kinds of case, to which I give a section each·. First, when something that fits with the constant observation of ourselves and others in similar cases is supported by reports of all who mention it, we accept it as easily and build on it as firmly as if it were certain knowledge; and we reason and act on it with as little doubt as if we had a perfect demonstration of it. Thus, if all Englishmen who have occasion to mention it were to affirm that it froze in England last winter, or that there were swallows seen there in the summer, I think one could hardly doubt this more than one does that seven and four

264

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xvi: Degrees of assent

are eleven. Thus, the first and highest degree of probability occurs when the general consent of all men in all ages, as far as it can be known, fits one’s own constant and never-failing experience in similar cases. Into this category come all the generally agreed constitutions and properties of bodies, and the regular proceedings of causes and effects in the ordinary course of nature. We call this an argument from the nature of things themselves. When our own and other men’s constant observation has found something always to go the same way, we with reason conclude that it is the effect of steady and regular causes, though we don’t outright know them. Thus, that

fire warmed a man, made lead fluid, and changed the colour or consistency in wood or charcoal;

iron sank in water, and floated in quicksilver

—when such propositions as these about particular facts fit with our constant experience, are generally spoken of in the same way by others, and therefore are not so much as questioned by anybody, we are left with no doubt of the truth of a narrative affirming such a thing to have happened, or of an assertion that it will happen again in the same way. These probabilities rise so near to certainty that they govern our thoughts as absolutely, and influence all our actions as fully, as the most evident demonstration; and in our practical concerns we hardly, if at all, distinguish them from certain knowledge. belief, with such a basis for it, rises to assurance.

7. Secondly, the next degree of probability occurs when I find—by my own experience and the agreement of everyone else who mentions it—that something is for the most part thus and so, and a particular instance of it is reported by many trustworthy witnesses. For example, history’s account of men in all ages, and my own experience as far as it goes, confirm that most men prefer their private advantage to the public good; so if all historians that write about Tiberius say that he had that preference, it is extremely probable that he did. In this case our assent is well enough based to raise itself to a degree that we may call confidence.

8. Thirdly, in things that could easily go either way—a bird flies this way or that, there is thunder on my right or my left, etc.—when a particular matter of fact is vouched for by the testimony of witnesses whom we have no reason to suspect, our assent is unavoidable. Thus, that there is in Italy such a city as Rome, that about 1700 hundred years ago there lived in it a man named Julius Caesar, that he was a general who won a battle against someone named Pompey—all this, although in the nature of the thing there is nothing for or against it, because it is reported by credible historians and contradicted by no-one, a man can’t avoid believing it and can no more doubt it than he does the existence and actions of his own acquaintances, of which he himself is a witness.

9. Up to here the matter is straightforward. Probability on such grounds—·i.e. those discussed in sections 6–8·—carries so much convincingness with it that it naturally determines the judgment and leaves us with no freedom whether to believe or disbelieve, just as a demonstration leaves us with no freedom whether to know or remain ignorant. Things become harder when testimonies contradict common experience, and the reports of history and witnesses clash with the ordinary course of nature or with one another. When that happens we need to use diligence, attention, and exactness if we are to form a right judgment, and to proportion our assent to the credibility and probability of the thing. The probability of a proposition rises and falls depending on whether it is favoured or contradicted by those two foundations of credibility, namely •common observation in similar cases, and

265

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xvi: Degrees of assent

•particular reports with regard to that particular instance. The former of these allow of so much variety of •contrary observations, circumstances, and reports; and the latter are so much affected by different •qualifications of the reporters, and differences in their characters, purposes, and level of care; that it’s impossible to devise precise rules governing the various degrees to which men give their assent. The only general thing to be said is this: as the arguments and proofs, for and against, appear to us—after due examination, attending to the detail of every particular circumstance—to weigh more or less heavily on one side of the other, so they should produce in the mind such different attitudes as we call belief, conjecture, guess, doubt, wavering, distrust, disbelief, etc.

[Sections 10–11 concern probability and testimony. Their main point is that if we know only that one person reports that another person reports that P, this is less good evidence for P than having the original report. ‘So that the more hands a tradition has successively passed through, the •less strength and convincingness it receives from them.’ Locke offers this as a corrective to some people’s belief that traditions are made •more credible by having been passed along for centuries. In section 11 he says that he doesn’t intend to demean history, but offers warnings about how it should be practised.]

12. The probabilities I have mentioned up to here have all concerned matters of fact, and things that can be reported on the basis of observation. There remains the other sort of probability—·the second of the two mentioned at the end of section 5·—·relating to matters· concerning which men differ in their opinions although the things don’t fall within reach of our senses and so aren’t capable of eye-witness reports. ·These can be sorted into two large groups. Here is the first·:

•The existence, nature, and operations of finite immaterial beings other than ourselves—e.g. Spirits, angels, devils, etc.

•The existence of material things that our senses can’t take notice of because they are either too small or too far away—e.g. whether there are any plants, animals, and thinking inhabitants of the planets and other mansions of this vast universe.

·The second category contains propositions· about the manner of operation of most parts of the works of nature. We see the perceptible effects, but their causes are unknown—we don’t perceive how they are produced. We see that animals are generated, nourished, and move, that the magnet attracts iron, and that the parts of a candle turn into flame as they melt, giving us both light and heat. These and their like we see and know; but their causes we can only guess at, conjecturing with probability. They don’t come under scrutiny by the human senses, so nobody can examine them and testify to them; and therefore ·a proposition about them· can appear more or less probable only by the standard of how well it agrees to truths that are established in our minds, and how well it stands comparison with things that we do know and observe. The only help we have in these matters is analogy; it is our only source for judgments of probability ·of this kind. Here are three examples·: 1 Observing that merely rubbing two bodies violently together produces heat, and very often fire, we have reason to think that what we call heat and fire consists in a violent agitation of the tiny imperceptible parts of the burning matter. 2 Observing that the different refractions of transparent bodies produce in our eyes the different appearances of various colours, and that the same effect can be produced by looking from different angles at velvet, watered silk, etc., we think it probable that the colour and shining of bodies is nothing

266

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xvi: Degrees of assent

but the different arrangement and refraction of their minute and imperceptible parts. 3 Finding in all the observable parts of the creation that there is a gradual connection of one thing with another, with no large or discernible gaps between,....we have reason to believe that ·quite generally· things ascend in degrees of perfection by such gentle steps. It is hard to say where sensing and thinking begin, and where non-sensing and non-thinking end; and who is quick-sighted enough to determine precisely which is the lowest species of living things and which the highest of those that have no life? Things, as far as we can observe, lessen and increase ·continuously·, like the diameters of cross-sections of a regular cone: there is a clear difference in size between two diameters that are far apart, but the difference between the upper and lower of two cross-sections that touch one another is hardly discernible. There is a vast difference between some men and some lower animals; but there are other man/brute pairs where the differences in understanding and abilities are so small that it will be hard to say that the man’s endowments are either clearer or larger than the brute’s. Observing, I say, such gradual and gentle descents downwards in those parts of the creation that are beneath man, the rule of analogy may make it probable that it is so also in things above us and above our observation; and that there are many kinds of thinking beings that surpass us in various degrees of perfection, ascending upwards towards the infinite perfection of the Creator by gentle steps and differences of which each is at no great distance from the next.

This sort of probability, which is the best guide for rational experiments and the formation of hypotheses, also has its use and influence; and cautious reasoning from analogy often leads us into the discovery of truths and useful productions that would otherwise lie concealed.

13. Though common experience and the ordinary course of things rightly have a tremendous influence on the minds of men, leading them to give or refuse belief to things that are put to them, there is one case where the strangeness of the ·reported· fact does not make men less prone to accept a fair testimony that is given of it. Where such ·reported· supernatural events are suitable to the purposes of God, who has the power to change the course of nature, reports of them may be more fit to be believed the more they go beyond ordinary observation or are contrary to it. This is a special feature of miracles....

14. There is also one sort of proposition that demands our highest degree of assent just from its being asserted, whether or not what it says agrees with common experience and the ordinary course of things. This is the testimony of someone who can’t deceive or be deceived, namely God. This kind of testimony has a special name of its own, namely ‘revelation’, and our assent to it is called ‘faith’. This matches outright knowledge in how totally it takes command of our minds, and how completely it excludes all wavering. We may as well doubt our own existence as doubt that any revelation from God is true. Thus, faith is a settled and sure principle of assent and assurance, leaving no room for doubt or hesitation. But we must be sure that it is a divine revelation, and that we understand it correctly; for if we have faith and assurance in what is not divine revelation we shall be open to all the extravagance of fanaticism and all the error of wrong principles. In such cases, therefore, our assent can’t rationally be higher than the evidence that this is indeed a revelation, and that this is what it means. If it’s merely probable that it is a revelation, or that this is its true sense, our assent should reach no higher than an assurance or distrust depending on how high or low the probability is.

267

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xvii: Reason

In chapter xviii I shall say more about faith, and the priority it ought to have over other arguments of persuasion. My topic there will be faith as against reason, though really faith is just assent founded on the highest reason.

Chapter xvii: Reason

1. The word ‘reason’ has different meanings in the English language. Sometimes it refers to true and clear •principles, sometimes to clear and fair •deductions from those principles, and sometimes to •a cause, and particularly a final cause [= ‘purpose’]. But my topic here is ‘reason’ in a different sense from any of those, namely: as the name of •the faculty that is supposed to distinguish man from the lower animals, and in which he obviously much surpasses them.

2. Given that general knowledge consists (as I have shown it does) in a •perception of the agreement or disagreement of our own ideas, and given also that knowledge of the existence of anything outside us (except for God, whose existence every man can demonstrate to himself from his own existence) can be had only through •our senses, what room is there for the use of any other faculty in addition to •inner perception and •outer sense? What need do we have for reason? A great need, both for enlarging our knowledge and for regulating our assent. For reason is involved both in knowledge and in opinion, and is a necessary aid to all our other intellectual faculties—and indeed two of those faculties are contained wthin reason, namely sagacity and illation. By sagacity it finds out intermediate ideas to create a chain linking two ideas, and by illation it orders the intermediate ideas so as to reveal what connection there is in each link of the chain that holds the premises together with the conclusion. We call this ‘illation’ or ‘inference’; it consists simply in perceiving the connection between the ideas at each step of the deduction, through which the mind comes to see either the •certain agreement or disagreement of a pair of ideas, as in demonstration yielding knowledge, or their •probable connection, on the basis of which the mind gives or withholds its assent, as in opinion. Sense and intuition reach only a very little way. Most of our knowledge depends on deductions and intermediate ideas; and in cases where we have to settle for assent rather than knowledge, and accept propositions as true without being certain that they are so, we need to find out, examine, and compare the grounds of their probability.

In both these cases—·that is, •certain agreement and •probable connection·—the faculty that discovers the intermediate items and applies them correctly to reveal certainty in the one (knowledge) and probability in the other (assent) is what we call reason. Just as reason perceives •the necessary and indubitable connection of all the ideas or proofs to one another in each step of a demonstration that produces knowledge, so also it perceives •the probable connection of all the ideas or proofs to one another in every step of a discourse that it will think it right to assent to. This is the

268

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xvii: Reason

lowest degree of what can be truly called ‘reason’. For where the mind doesn’t perceive this probable connection, where it doesn’t discern whether there is any such connection, there men’s opinions are not the product of judgment or the consequence of reason, but the effects of chance and hazard, of a mind floating at random without choice and without direction.

3. So we can distinguish four levels in reason, in descending order: 1 the discovering and finding out of truths, 2 sorting them out and laying them in a clear order that will make it easy to see plainly their connection and force, 3 perceiving their connection, and 4 coming to a correct conclusion. Reason can be seen at work at all these levels in any mathematical demonstration: it is one thing to 3 perceive the connection of each part when examining a demonstration that someone else has constructed; it’s another thing 4 to perceive the dependence of the conclusion on all the parts; and it’s yet something else again 2 construct a demonstration clearly and neatly oneself; and something else again 1 to have first found out these intermediate ideas or proofs by which it is made.

[Section 4 is a nine-page attack on the view that the only or best or proper use of reason is in constructing and following syllogisms. This is widely regarded as one of the weakest things in the Essay (Leibniz in his New Essays sharply and competently sorts it out), and its topic is of little interest today. It does include the memorable, if unfair, joke: ‘God hasn’t been so sparing to men as to make them merely two-legged creatures, leaving it to Aristotle to make them rational.’ A little later Locke adds:] I don’t say all this to lessen Aristotle, whom I look on as one of the greatest men amongst the ancients. Few have equalled his breadth of view, acuteness, penetration of thought, and strength of judgment. In this very invention of ·syllogistic· forms of argumentation, through which conclusions can be shown to be rightly inferred, he did great service against those who were not ashamed to deny anything. [The conclusion of the section is also worthy of note:] I’m not in favour of taking away anything that can help the understanding to attain knowledge. If men skilled and practised in syllogisms find them helpful to their reason in the discovery of truth, I think they ought to use them. My point is just that they shouldn’t ascribe more to those forms than they are entitled to, thinking that men who don’t employ syllogisms are deprived of all or some of the use of their reasoning faculty. Some eyes need spectacles to see things clearly and distinctly; but those who use them shouldn’t say that nobody can see clearly without them. Those who do so may have been genuinely helped by the artifice of syllogism, but they will be thought to favour this too much, and to discredit or undervalue nature ·in the form of natural reason·. Reason, by its own penetration where it is strong and is exercised, usually sees more quickly and clearly without syllogism. If ·a particular person’s· use of those spectacles has so dimmed ·his· reason’s sight that without them he can’t see whether an argument is valid or not, I’m not so unreasonable as to oppose his using them. Everyone knows what best fits his own sight. But let him not conclude from his experience that everyone is in the dark who doesn’t use just the same helps that he finds a need for!

[Sections 5–6 continue the attack on syllogisms. The point in 5 is just that, however little syllogism helps us to get knowledge, ‘it is of far less or no use at all in probabilities’. The theme of 6 is that syllogism is at best a way of setting out arguments that have already been discovered, and is useless as a means to discovering arguments in the first place. Locke

269

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xvii: Reason

unfavourably contrasts formal scholastic syllogistic reasoning with what can be done by ‘native rustic reason’—another echo of the contrast between art and nature.]

7. I don’t doubt, however, that ways can be found to assist our reason in this most useful part ·of its activity, namely the discovery of new knowledge·. I am encouraged to say this by the judicious Hooker, who in his Ecclesiastical Polity I.i.6 writes:

If we could add ·to our repertoire· the right helps of true art and learning,....there would undoubtedly be almost as much difference in maturity of judgment between •men who had those helps and •men as they now are as there is between •the latter and •little children.

I don’t claim to have invented or discovered here any of those ‘right helps’ that this great and profound thinker mentions; but obviously he wasn’t thinking of syllogism and the logic now in use, because those were as well known at his time as they are now. I will be satisfied if my discussion leads others to cast about for new discoveries, and to seek in their own thoughts for those ‘right helps of art’, which I’m afraid won’t be found by those who slavishly confine themselves to the rules and dictates of others. (·I at any rate haven’t done that·. My discussion of this topic is, so far as I am concerned, wholly new and unborrowed.).... I venture to say that this age is adorned with some men whose strength of judgment and breadth of understanding are such that if they were willling to employ their thoughts on this subject, they could open new and undiscovered ways to the advancement of knowledge.

8.....Before leaving this subject I want to take notice of one obvious mistake in the rules of syllogism, namely the rule that no syllogistic reasoning can be valid unless it has at least one general proposition in it. As if we couldn’t reason and have knowledge about particulars! The fact is that the immediate object of all our reasoning and knowledge is nothing but particulars. Every man’s reasoning and knowledge is only about the ideas existing in his own mind, which are truly—every one of them—particular existences; and our knowledge and reasoning about other things depends on their corresponding with our particular ideas. Thus the perception of the agreement or disagreement of our particular ideas is all there is to our knowledge. Universality is only accidental to it, and consists only in the fact that a particular idea....can correspond to and represent more than one particular thing. But the perception of the agreement or disagreement of any two ideas—and consequently the knowledge arising from that—is equally clear and certain, whether either, or both, or neither of those ideas can represent more than one real thing. [Locke ends the section with a proposed change in the conventional order in which the premises of a syllogism are written down.]

9. Reason, though it penetrates into the depths of the sea and earth, elevates our thoughts as high as the stars, and leads us through the vast spaces and large rooms of this mighty universe, still comes far short of the real extent of ·what there is to be known about things·, even corporeal things. There are many circumstances in which it fails us. ·I shall list five, giving them a section each·.

First, it completely fails us when our ideas fail. It doesn’t and can’t extend itself further than they do; and so whenever we have no ideas, our reasoning stops and we are at an end of our calculation. And if at any time we reason about words that don’t stand for any ideas, it is only about those sounds and nothing else.

270

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xvii: Reason

10. Secondly, our reason is often puzzled and at a loss because of the obscurity, confusion, or imperfection of the ideas it is engaged with; and then we are involved in difficulties and contradictions. For example, not having any perfect idea of 1 the least extension of matter or of 2 infinity, we are at a loss about the divisibility of matter. ·The former lack 1 blocks us from saying that some portions of matter have the ‘least extension’ and so are indivisible; the latter lack 2 blocks us from saying that all portions of matter are divisible, i.e. that matter is infinitely divisible·. In contrast with that, we have perfect, clear, and distinct ideas of number, so our reason meets with none of those inextricable difficulties in respect of numbers, and doesn’t find itself involved in contradictions about them. Again, we have only imperfect ideas of the operations of our minds, and of how the mind produces motion in our bodies or thoughts in our minds, and even more imperfect ideas of the operation of God; so we run into great difficulties about free created agents, difficulties from which reason can’t thoroughly extricate itself.

11. Thirdly, our reason is often brought to a stand-still because it doesn’t perceive the ideas that could serve to show the certain or probable agreement or disagreement of some pair of ideas. In this respect some men’s faculties far outstrip those of others. Until that great instrument and example of human sagacity algebra was discovered, men looked with amazement at some of the demonstrations of ancient mathematicians, and could hardly help thinking that the discovery of some of those proofs was a superhuman achievement.

12. Fourthly, the mind often proceeds on false principles, and that gets it into absurdities and difficulties, dilemmas and contradictions, without knowing how to free itself; and in that case it’s no use pleading for help from reason, except perhaps to reveal the falsehood and reject the influence of the wrong principles. Reason is so far from clearing up the difficulties that a man gets into by building on false foundations that if he pushes on his reason will entangle him all the more, and deepen his perplexities.

13. Fifthly, just as obscure and imperfect •ideas often get our reason into difficulties, so for the same reason do dubious •words. It often happens in discourses and arguings that uncertain signs, when not warily attended to, puzzle men’s reason and bring them to a halt. But these defects in ideas and meanings are our fault, not that of reason. Their consequences are nevertheless obvious, and the perplexities or errors they fill men’s minds with are everywhere observable.

[Sections 14–18 repeat things Locke has already said, about intutition, demonstration, and probability. He repeats an earlier conjecture about the intellectual capacities of ‘angels, and the Spirits of just men made perfect’. He emphasizes the risk of forgetting some of the steps in a long demonstration, or suspecting that one has forgotten them.]

19. Before we leave this subject, it may be worth our while to reflect a little on four sorts of arguments that men commonly use when reasoning with others—either to win the others’ assent or to awe them into silence.

The first is 1 to bring forward the opinions of men whose skills, learning, eminence, power, or some other cause has made them famous and given them some kind of authority in people’s minds. ·This often succeeds, because· a man is thought to be unduly proud if he doesn’t readily yield to the judgment of approved authors, which is customarily received with respect and submission by others.... Someone who backs his position with such authorities thinks they ought to win the argument for him, and if anyone stands out against them he will call such a person impudent. This, I think, may

271

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xvii: Reason

be called argumentum ad verecundiam—‘argument aimed at ·producing· deference ·in one’s opponent·’.

20. Another means that men commonly use to force others to submit their judgments and accept the opinion under discussion is 2 to require the adversary to accept what they bring forward as a proof or to offer a better ·proof of the contrary position·. This I call argumentum ad ignorantiam [= ‘argument] aimed at ignorance’.

21. A third tactic is 3 to press a man with consequences drawn from his own principles or concessions. This is already known under the name of argumentum ad hominem [= ‘argument] aimed at the man’.

22. The fourth is 4 the use of proofs drawn from any of the foundations of knowledge or probability. This I call argumentum ad judicium [= ‘argument aimed at controlled judgment’]. This is the only one of the four that brings true instruction with it, and advances us towards knowledge. [Locke now elegantly contrasts this with the other three, twice.] It doesn’t 1 argue that another man’s opinion is right because I out of respect—or for any other reason except conviction—will not contradict him. It doesn’t 2 prove another man to be on the right path and that I ought to follow him along it because I don’t know a better one. Nor does it 3 argue that another man is right because he has shown me that I am in the wrong. I may be 1 modest, and therefore not oppose another man’s opinion; I may be 2 ignorant, and not be able to produce a better proof: I may be 3 in an error, and someone may show me that I am so. All or any of these may dispose me, perhaps, for the reception of truth, but they don’t help me to reach it; that help must come from proofs and arguments and light arising from the nature of things themselves, and not from my shame-facedness, ignorance, or error.

23. From what I have said about reason, we may be able to guess at the distinction of things into those that are according to, above, and contrary to reason. •According to reason are propositions whose truth we can discover by examining and tracing ideas that we have from sensation and reflection, and by natural deduction find the proposition to be true or probable. •Above reason are propositions whose truth or probability we can’t derive through reason from those principles. •Contrary to reason are propositions that are inconsistent with our clear and distinct ideas. Thus the existence of one God is according to reason; the existence of more than one God, contrary to reason; the resurrection of the dead, above reason. ‘Above reason’ may be taken in a double sense, either as meaning ‘above probability’ or as meaning ‘above certainty’; and I suppose that ‘contrary to reason’ is also sometimes taken in that broader way.

24. There is another use of the word ‘reason’, in which it is opposed to faith. It is very improper, but common use has so authorized it that it would be folly to oppose it or to hope to remedy it. Still, it should be noted that faith is nothing but a firm assent of the mind; and if it is guided as it ought to be, one won’t have faith in anything except for good reasons; so it can’t be opposite to reason. Someone who believes without having any reason for believing may be in love with his own fancies; but he doesn’t seek truth as he ought, nor is he obedient to his Maker, who wants him to use the discerning faculties he has given him to keep him out of mistake and error. He who doesn’t do this to the best of his ability may sometimes happen on the truth; but he is right only by chance, and I don’t know whether that lucky outcome will excuse the irregularity of his way of reaching it. This at least is certain, that he will be accountable for whatever mistakes he makes; whereas someone who makes

272

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xviii: Faith and reason

use of the faculties God has given him, and seeks sincerely to discover truth through the abilities that he has, can have the satisfaction of knowing that even if he misses the truth he will have the reward of having done his duty as a rational creature.... But since some people do oppose reason to faith, we will look at them in the following chapter.

Chapter xviii: Faith and reason, and their distinct provinces

1. I have shown •that where we lack ideas we are inevitably ignorant, and lack knowledge of all sorts, •that where we lack proofs we are ignorant and lack rational knowledge, •that insofar as we lack clear and determined specific ideas we lack knowledge and certainty, and •that we lack probability to guide our assent in matters where we have neither knowledge of our own nor testimony of others on which to base our reason.

Starting from these things, I think we can mark out the boundaries between faith and reason. The lack of such marking may have been the cause, if not of violence, at least of great disputes and perhaps also mistakes. Until it is settled how far we should be guided by reason, and how far by faith, it will be pointless for us to dispute and try to convince one another in matters of religion.

2. I find that every sect will gladly make use of reason when it will help them, and when it fails them they cry out It is a matter of faith, and above reason. I don’t see how they can argue with anyone, or ever convince an opponent who uses the same plea, without setting down strict boundaries between faith and reason. That ought to be the first point established in any debate where faith comes into it.

In this context, where reason is being distinguished from faith, I take reason to be the discovery of the certainty or probability of propositions or truths that the mind arrives at by inference from ideas that it has acquired by the use of its natural faculties, that is, by sensation or reflection.

Faith on the other hand is the assent to a proposition that is not made out by the inferences of reason, but upon the credit of the proposer, as coming from God in some extraordinary way of communication. [The second half of that sentence (but upon... etc.) is given in Locke’s exact words.] This way of revealing truths to men we call ‘revelation’. ·Using the terms in these ways, I have three main points to make, one in section 3, one in sections 4–6, the third in section 7·.

3. First, I say that no man inspired by God can by any revelation communicate to others any new simple ideas—ones that they hadn’t previously acquired from sensation or reflection. Whatever impressions the inspired person may have from the immediate hand of God, if this revelation is of new simple ideas then it can’t be conveyed to anyone else by words or by any other signs. [The section continues with a statement of reasons for this, based on Locke’s views about how we can get simple ideas. He also remarks that after Paul of Tarsus had been taken up into the third heaven, he could only report that there are such things ‘as eye has

273

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xviii: Faith and reason

not seen, nor ear heard, nor has it entered into the heart of man to conceive’. The section concludes:] For our simple ideas, then, which are the foundation and only raw material of all our notions and knowledge, we must depend wholly on our reason, by which I mean our natural faculties. There is no way we can get any such ideas from 1 traditional revelation—as distinct from 2 original revelation. By 1 I mean •impressions passed on to others in words and in other ordinary ways of conveying our conceptions to one another; by 2 I mean •that first impression which is made immediately by God on the mind of any man—we can’t set any limit to that.

4. Secondly, I say that truths that we can discover by reason, using ideas that we naturally have, can also be revealed and conveyed to us through revelation. So God might by revelation tell us the truth of a proposition in Euclid which men can also discover for themselves through the natural use of their faculties. In all things of this kind there is little need for revelation, because God has equipped us with natural and surer means to arrive at the knowledge of them: any truth that we learn from the contemplation of our own ideas will be more certain to us than any conveyed to us by traditional revelation. That is because our knowledge that this revelation did come at first from God can never be as sure as the knowledge we have from the clear and distinct perception of the agreement or disagreement of our own ideas. For example, if it were revealed centuries ago that the three angles of a triangle were equal to two right ones, I might assent to the truth of that proposition on the strength of the tradition that it was revealed; but that would never reach to the level of certainty of the knowledge of it that comes from comparing and measuring my own ideas of two right angles and of the three angles of a triangle. The same holds for matters of fact that are knowable by our senses. For example, the history of the great flood is conveyed to us by writings that originally came from revelation. But I don’t think you will say that your knowledge of the flood is as certain and clear as that of Noah, who saw it; or as you yourself would have had if you had been alive then and seen it. Your senses give you a great assurance that the story of the flood is written in the book supposedly written by Moses when he was inspired; but you have less assurance that Moses did write that book than you would have if you saw Moses write it. So your assurance of its being a revelation is less still than the assurance of your senses.

5. Thus, for propositions whose certainty is built on intuition or demonstration we don’t need the help of revelation to introduce them into our minds and to gain our assent; because the natural ways of knowledge could or already did settle them there, and that is the greatest assurance we can have of anything that isn’t immediately revealed to us by God. And even there our assurance can be no greater than our knowledge that it is a revelation from God. Nothing can, under the title of ‘revelation’, shake or over-rule plain knowledge or rationally lead any man to accept it as true when it directly contradicts the clear evidence of his own understanding. The faculties through which we receive such ·supposed· revelations can’t produce a stronger conviction than comes from the certainty of our intuitive knowledge; so we can never accept as true anything directly contrary to our clear and distinct knowledge. For example, the ideas of one body and one place so clearly agree, and the mind has so clear a perception of their agreement, that we can never assent to a proposition affirming that a single body is in two distant places at one time, however strongly it lays claim to the authority of a divine revelation. That is because we can

274

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xviii: Faith and reason

never be as strongly convinced

that •we are right in ascribing it to God, and

that •we understand it correctly,

as we are by our own intuitive knowledge that •one body cannot be in two places at once. And therefore no proposition can be accepted as divine revelation, or given the assent that all divine revelations deserve, if it contradicts our clear intuitive knowledge. [In the remainder of this long section Locke elaborates this position, arguing in effect that the contrary view would bring chaos into epistemology as well as implying theological absurdities—God wouldn’t have given us intuition and demonstration if he hadn’t intend us to rely on them.]

6. The argument up to here has shown this: even in the case of an ·alleged· immediate and original revelation which is supposed to have been made just to you, you have the use of reason and should listen to what it says. As for those who don’t claim to have received any immediate revelation, but are required to accept and obey truths ·supposedly· revealed to others and passed along in an oral or written tradition, in their case reason has a much larger role, and is the only basis on which we can be induced to accept such revelations. In this context we are equating •matters of faith with •propositions accepted as divinely revealed. Now, the question

Was proposition P divinely revealed?

is not itself a matter of faith. If it were, that would be because

It was divinely revealed to us that it was divinely revealed to us that P.

Unless it is revealed to us that proposition P was communicated by divine inspiration, the question of whether to believe that P has divine authority is to be settled not by faith but by reason....

7. Thirdly, there are •many things of which we have very imperfect notions or none at all, and •other things of whose past, present, or future existence we can have no knowledge through the natural use of our faculties; and all these are, when revealed, the proper matter of faith. That some of the angels rebelled against God and thereby lost their first happy state, and that the dead shall rise and live again—these and their like are beyond the discovery of reason, which makes them purely matters of faith, with which reason has nothing directly to do.

8. But when God gave us the light of reason, he wasn’t tying his own hands: he can still give us, when he thinks fit, the light of revelation in matters where our natural faculties can give ·only· a probable answer. So revelation, where God has been pleased to give it, must win out against the probable conjectures of reason. When the mind is not certain of the truth of a proposition and inclines to accept it only because it appears probable, it is bound to give it up in the face of contrary testimony that comes (the mind is satisfied) from someone who cannot err and won’t deceive. But it is still for reason to judge •whether it is a revelation, and •what the words in it mean....

9. ·Summing up: there are two situations in which it is appropriate to believe something as a matter of faith·. First, when a proposition is revealed to us whose truth our mind can’t judge by its natural faculties and notions, that is purely •a matter of faith, and above reason.

Secondly, when reason provides the mind with only probable grounds for believing P, grounds that allow for the possibility that not-P without this doing violence to the mind’s own certain knowledge or overturning the principles of all reason, then an evident revelation that not-P ought to settle the matter even against probability. In such a

275

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xix: Enthusiasm

case,....reason can reach no higher than probability, so faith gives an answer where reason fell short, and revelation showed on which side the truth lay.

[Section 10 repeats the doctrines of sections 6, 8 and 9.]

11. If the domains of faith and reason are not kept distinct by these boundaries, there will be no room for reason at all in matters of religion; and those extravagant opinions and ceremonies that are to be found in various religions of the world won’t merit blame. I think that this vaunting of faith in opposition to reason is a primary source of the absurdities that fill almost all the religions that possess and divide mankind. For men who are indoctrinated with the view that they mustn’t consult reason in the things of religion, however much they seem to contradict common sense and the very principles of all their knowledge, have let loose their imaginations and natural superstition which have led them into strange opinions and extravagant practices in religion. So strange and extravagant that a thoughtful man can’t but stand amazed at their follies, and judge them as being so far from acceptable to the great and wise God that he can’t avoid thinking them ridiculous and offensive to a sober good man. The upshot is that religion, which should most distinguish us from lower animals and ought most specially to elevate us as rational creatures above the others, is just the thing in which men often appear most irrational and more senseless than the lower animals themselves. Credo, quia impossibile est, ‘I believe, because it is impossible’, might in a good man pass for a slogan expressing his zeal; but it would be a dreadful rule for men to choose their opinions or religion by.

Chapter xix: Enthusiasm

[= ‘intense, fanatical confidence that one is hearing from God’]

1. Anyone wanting to engage seriously in the search for truth ought first to prepare his mind with a love of it. Someone who doesn’t love truth won’t take much trouble to get it, or be much concerned when he misses it. Everyone in the commonwealth of learning professes himself to be a lover of truth, and every rational creature would be offended if it were thought that he is not. And yet it’s true to say that very few people love truth for its own sake, even among those who persuade themselves that they do. How can anyone know whether he is seriously a lover of truth? I think there is one unerring mark of it, namely that one doesn’t accept any proposition with greater assurance than is justified by the proofs one has for it. If someone goes beyond this measure of assent, it is clear that he values truth not for its own sake but for some other hidden purpose. For the love of truth can no more

•carry my assent to a proposition above the evidence that I have for its truth

than it can

•make me assent to a proposition because of the evidence that there isn’t for its truth!

The latter would amount to: loving it as a truth because it possibly or probably isn’t one! For the evidence that a

276

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xix: Enthusiasm

proposition is true (unless it is self-evident) lies only in the proofs a man has of it; so if he assents to it with a level of assurance that goes beyond that evidence, what is drawing him into that excess of assurance is something in him other than the love of truth. Whatever credit we give to a proposition, above what it gets from the principles and proofs that support it, comes from inclinations in that direction, and detracts from the love of truth as such....

2. This bias and corruption of our judgments is regularly accompanied by a dictatorial attitude to the beliefs of others, a readiness to tell them what they ought to believe. ·This is to be expected·, because someone who has already imposed on his own belief is almost certain to be ready to impose on the beliefs of others. Who can reasonably expect arguments and conviction, in dealing with others, on the part of someone whose understanding isn’t accustomed to them in his dealing with himself? This is someone who does violence to his own faculties, tyrannizes over his own mind, and grabs the privilege that really belongs to truth alone, which is to command assent purely by its own authority, i.e. by and in proportion to the degree of evidentness that it carries with it.

3. I shall take this opportunity to discuss a third ground of assent, which for some men has the same authority and is as confidently relied on as either faith or reason. It is enthusiasm, which lays reason aside and appeals to revelation without help from reason. This amounts to taking away both reason and revelation, replacing them by the ungrounded fancies of a man’s own brain and making these a foundation of both opinion and conduct.

4. Reason is natural revelation, through which ·God·, the eternal father of light and fountain of all knowledge, communicates to mankind that portion of truth that he has put within the reach of their natural faculties. Revelation is

natural reason enlarged by a new set of discoveries communicated immediately by God, the truth of which is supported by reason through the testimony and proofs it gives that they do come from God.

Thus, someone who takes away reason to make way for revelation puts out the light of both—like persuading a man to put out his eyes so that he can better to receive the remote light of an invisible star through a telescope!

5. Immediate revelation is a much easier way for men to establish their opinions and regulate their conduct than the boring and not always successful labour of strict reasoning. So it is no wonder that some people have claimed to have received revelations, and have persuaded themselves that they are under the special guidance of heaven in their actions and opinions, especially in opinions that they can’t account for by the ordinary methods of knowledge and principles of reason. Thus we see that in all ages men in whom melancholy has mixed with devotion, or whose self-importance has led them to think they have a greater familiarity with God than others and are more favoured by him than others are, have often flattered themselves with the conviction that they are in immediate communication with the Deity and receive frequent messages from the Divine Spirit. It must be admitted that God can enlighten the understanding by a ray darted into the mind immediately from the fountain of light; those people think he has promised to do that; and so—·their thought goes·—who has a better right to expect it than those who are his special people, chosen by him and depending on him?

6. Once their minds have been prepared in this way, any baseless opinion that comes to settle itself strongly on their imaginations is ·taken by them to be· an illumination from the spirit of God. And when they find themselves strongly

277

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xix: Enthusiasm

inclined to perform some strange action, they conclude that this impulse is a call or direction from heaven, and must be obeyed.

7. This is what I take enthusiasm to be, when properly understood. Although it is based neither on reason nor on divine revelation, but arises from the fancies of an overheated or arrogant brain, once it gets going it works on men’s thoughts and deeds more powerfully than either of those two and than both together. The impulses that men are readiest to obey are the ones they receive from themselves; and the whole man is sure to act more vigorously when the whole man is carried along by a natural motion. For a fanciful notion is irresistible when it is placed above common sense and neither •restrained by reason nor •checked by reflection; our mood and our wishes raise it to the level of a divine authority!

8. The odd opinions and extravagant actions that men are led into by enthusiasm provide a sufficient warning against it; but many men ·ignore the warning, and· once they have started to think they are receiving immediate revelation— •illumination without search, and •certainty without proof or examination—it is hard to cure them of this. That is because their love of something extraordinary, the sense of ease and triumph they get from having an access to knowledge that is superior to the natural access that most people have, is soothing to their laziness, ignorance, and vanity. Reason is lost on them; they are above it, ·they think. Their account of their situation runs as follows·.

I see the light that shines through my understanding, and cannot be mistaken; it is clear and visible there, like the light of bright sunshine; it shows itself, and needs no proof except its own evidentness. I feel the hand of God and the impulses of the spirit moving within me, and I can’t be mistaken in what I feel.

Thus they support themselves, and are sure that reason has nothing to do with what they see and feel in themselves.

Something that I experience through my senses admits no doubt, needs no proof. Wouldn’t it be ridiculous for someone to demand proof that the light shines and that he sees it? It is its own proof, and can’t have any other. When the spirit brings light into my mind it dispels darkness. I see it as I do the light of the sun at noon, and have no need for the twilight of reason to show it to me. This light from heaven is strong, clear, and pure carries its own demonstration with it; to examine this celestial ray by our dim candle, reason, would make as much sense as using a glow-worm to help us to discover the sun.

9. This is how these men talk. Stripped of the metaphors of ‘seeing’ and ‘feeling’, what they say amounts only to this: •they are sure because they are sure, and •their convictions are right because they hold them strongly! But the metaphor so imposes on them that they equate it with certainty in themselves and demonstration for others.

10. Let us calmly examine a little this ‘internal light’ and this ‘feeling’ on which they build so much. These men say they have clear light, and that they see; they have awakened senses, and they feel; they are sure that this can’t be disputed, for when a man says he sees or feels, nobody can deny that he does so. But here let me ask: is this seeing

a perception •that the proposition is true or

a perception •that it is a revelation from God?

Is this feeling

a perception of •an inclination or wish to do something, or

278

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xix: Enthusiasm

a perception of •the spirit of God causing that inclination?

These are two very different perceptions ·in each case·, and they must be carefully distinguished if we are not to mislead ourselves. I may perceive the truth of a proposition—for example a proposition in Euclid—without perceiving that it is an immediate revelation from God, and without its being so. Indeed, I may perceive that I didn’t come by some knowledge in a natural way, and so conclude that it has been revealed to me, without perceiving that it is a revelation from God; because there may be Spirits that can, without being told to by God, arouse those ideas in me and set them out in such an order before my mind that I can perceive their connection. So if •the knowledge of ·the truth of· a proposition comes into my mind and I don’t know how, that’s not the same as perceiving that it comes from God. Much less is •a strong conviction of its truth a perception that it is from God, or even a perception that it is true.

The enthusiasts may call it ‘light’ and ‘seeing’, but I think it is merely belief and assurance. And the proposition they think has been revealed to them is not something they •know to be true, but merely something they •accept as true. When a proposition is known to be true, there is no need for revelation; it is hard to conceive how there can be a revelation to someone of what he already knows. So if it is a proposition that they are sure—but don’t know—to be true, then what they have, whatever they may call it, is not seeing but believing. These are two wholly distinct ways by which truth comes into the mind: what I see I know to be so by the evidence of the thing itself; what I believe I take to be so upon the testimony of someone else. But I must know that this testimony has been given, for otherwise what ground have I for believing? I must see that it is God that reveals this to me, or else I see nothing. So the question is this: how do I know that God is the revealer of this to me? How do I know that this impression is made on my mind by his Holy Spirit, and that therefore I ought to obey it? If I don’t know this, my assurance—however great it is—is groundless; whatever light I claim to have is mere enthusiasm. Whether •the ‘revealed’ proposition is

in itself obviously true, or

clearly probable, or

not decidable by the natural ways of knowledge,

there is a different proposition which has to be well grounded and manifestly true. It is •the proposition that God is the revealer of the former proposition, and that what I take to be a revelation is certainly something put into my mind by him and not an illusion dropped there by some other spirit, or created by my own imagination. These men accept a certain proposition as true because they presume that God revealed it. So oughtn’t they to examine what grounds they have for presuming that? If they don’t, their confidence is only presumption, and this ‘light’ they are so dazzled with is nothing but a will-o’-the-wisp that leads them constantly round in this circle: it is a revelation because they firmly believe it, and they believe it because it is a revelation.

11. In any matter of divine revelation the only proof we need is that it is an inspiration from God. For he can neither deceive nor be deceived. But how can we know that a proposition in our minds is a truth put there by God—a truth that he declares to us and which we ought therefore to believe? This is where enthusiasm fails. For the enthusiasts boast of a light by which they say they are enlightened and brought into the knowledge of this or that truth. But if they know it to be a truth, they must know this either through its being self-evident to natural reason or through rational proofs that show it to be true. If they see and know it to be a

279

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xix: Enthusiasm

truth in either of these two ways, it is pointless for them to suppose it to be a revelation; for they know it to be true the same way that any other man naturally can know that it is so without the help of revelation.... If they say they know it to be true because it is a revelation from God, that is a good reason; but then we should ask how they know it to be a revelation from God. If they say ‘By the light it brings with it, which shines brightly in my mind and I can’t resist’, I ask them to consider whether this amounts to anything more than ‘It is a revelation, because I strongly believe it to be true’. For the ‘light’ they speak of is only their strong though baseless conviction that it is a truth.... What easier way can there be to run ourselves into the most extravagant errors and miscarriages than in this way to take fancy for our only guide, and to believe any proposition to be true, any action to be right, simply because we believe it to be so? The strength of our convictions is no evidence at all of their own correctness; crooked things can be as stiff and inflexible as straight ones, and men can be as positive and peremptory in error as in truth. [The section closes with more about strongly held errors, as evidenced by conflicting sects of enthusiasts.]

[Section 12 adds the example of Paul of Tarsus, who was sure he was acting rightly when he persecuted Christians.]

13. Light, true light, in the mind can only be the evidentness of the truth of a proposition; and if the proposition isn’t self-evident, the only light it can have is what comes from the clearness and validity of the proofs that lead one to accept it. To talk of any other ‘light’ in the understanding is to put ourselves in the dark—or in the power of the Prince of darkness!—and voluntarily to delude ourselves in order to believe a lie. For if •strength of persuasion is •the light by which we must be guided, how are we to distinguish the delusions of Satan from the inspirations of the Holy Ghost? Satan can transform himself into an angel of light. And those who are led by that son of the morning are as fully satisfied with the light they are getting—i.e. are as strongly persuaded that they are being enlightened by the spirit of God—as anyone who actually is so. They accept and rejoice in it, act on the basis of it, and are as sure as anyone could be (letting their own strong belief be the judge) that they are right. [In the background: ‘How art thou fallen from heaven, O Lucifer, son of the morning! how art thou cut down to the ground, which didst weaken the nations!’ Isaiah 14:12.]

14. So if you don’t want to give yourself up to all the extravagances of delusion and error, you must make critical use of this guide of your light within. God, when he makes the prophet, doesn’t unmake the man. He leaves all his faculties in their natural state so that he can judge whether his inspirations are of divine origin. When he illuminates the mind with •supernatural light, he doesn’t extinguish •the light that is natural. If he wants us to assent to the truth of a proposition, he either makes its truth evident by the usual methods of natural reason, or else makes it known to be a truth which wants us to assent to because of his authority, and convinces us that it is from him by some marks that reason can’t be mistaken about. Reason must be our last judge and guide in everything. I don’t mean that we must •consult reason and •·use it to· examine whether a proposition revealed from God can be justified by natural principles and •reject it if it can’t. But we must •consult it and •use it to examine whether the proposition in question is a revelation from God. And if reason finds that it is revealed by God, reason then declares in its favour as much as it does for any other truth, and makes it one of her own dictates. If we have nothing by which to judge our opinions except the

280

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xx: Error

strength with which we have them, every thought thrown up by a heated imagination will count as an inspiration. If reason can’t examine their truth of our opinions by some external standard, inspirations will have the same measure as delusions, and truth the same as falsehood, and there will be no way to distinguish one from the other.

[In section 15 Locke writes of Old Testament prophets to whom God spoke directly, and who wanted and received extra evidence that it was inded God who was speaking. His chief example:] Moses saw the bush burn without being consumed, and heard a voice coming out of it. This was different from merely finding that he very much wanted to go to Pharaoh so as to bring his countrymen out of Egypt. Yet he didn’t think that this was enough to authorize him to go ·to Pharaoh· with that message, until God had assured him of a power to carry it through by another miracle—turning his rod into a serpent—which he repeated in the presence of those to whom Moses was to testify....

16. In what I have said I am far from denying that God sometimes enlightens men’s minds with certain •truths, or arouses them to good •actions, through the immediate influence and assistance of the Holy Spirit and without any extraordinary signs accompanying it. But in these cases too we have reason and scripture, unerring rules to know whether something comes from God. Where the •truth in question conforms to the revelation in the written word of God, or the •action in question conforms to the dictates of right reason or holy writ, we can be sure that we run no risk in treating it as such. Even if it isn’t an immediate revelation from God operating on our minds in an extraordinary manner, we are sure it is warranted by the revelation that he has given us of truth. But that warrant that it is a •light or •motion from heaven doesn’t come from the strength of our private conviction; it has to come from something public, namely the written word of God or the standard of reason that we share with all men. When reason or scripture expressly supports an •opinion or •action, we may accept it as having divine authority; but it doesn’t get that stamp of approval from the mere strength of our own conviction....

Chapter xx: Wrong assent, or error

1. Knowledge can be had only of visible and certain truth. So error isn’t a fault of our knowledge, but a mistake of our judgment when it gives assent to something that isn’t true. But if assent is based on likelihood, if what assent especially aims at is probability, and if probability is what I said it is in chapters xv and xvi, you will want to know how it comes about that men sometimes accept propositions that are not probable. For there’s nothing more common than contrariety of opinions; nothing more obvious than that one man wholly disbelieves what another only doubts of and a third firmly believes. The reasons for this may be very various, but I think they all come down to these four:

281

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xx: Error

1 Lack of proofs, ·to be discussed in sections 2–4·.

2 Lack of ability to use them, ·section 5·.

3 Lack of will to use them. ·section 6·.

4 Wrong measures of probability, ·sections 7–17·.

2. In the first category I include not only the lack of proofs that •don’t exist anywhere and so can’t be had, but also the lack of proofs that •do exist or could be procured. Men lack proofs ·in the second way· when they don’t have the means or opportunity to make their own experiments and observations relating to some proposition, or the means to gather the testimonies of others. That is how most of mankind are situated: they are given up to labour, and enslaved to the necessities of their low status in life—their lives are worn out in merely providing for their livelihood. These men’s opportunities for knowledge and enquiry are commonly as narrow as their fortunes; and their minds are not much enriched when all their waking hours and all their effort is devoted to stilling the rumbling of their own bellies, or the cries of their children. It isn’t to be expected that a man who drudges all his life in a laborious trade should know more about the variety of things done in the world than a pack-horse that is repeatedly driven to and from market along the same narrow lane knows about the geography of the country. [The remainder of the section elaborates on this theme.]

3. What shall we say then? Are most of mankind subjected by the necessities of bare subsistence to unavoidable ignorance about the things that are of greatest importance to them? (·I mean: about what they must do in order to go to heaven and avoid hell.·) Have the bulk of mankind no guide except accident and blind chance to lead them to their happiness or misery? Are the current opinions and licensed guides of each man’s country sufficient evidence and security for him to base on them his great concerns (indeed, his everlasting happiness or misery)? Can those who teach one thing in Christendom and another in Turkey be the certain and infallible oracles and standards of truth? Shall a poor peasant be eternally happy because he chanced to be born in Italy, and a day-labourer be damned eternally because he had the bad luck to be born in England? I shan’t discuss the question of how willing some men may be to say some of these things, but I am sure of this: that you must allow one or other of them to be true (take your pick) or else grant that God has equipped men with faculties sufficient to show them what to do, if only they will seriously employ them to that end when their daily tasks allow them the leisure. No man is so wholly taken up with earning a livelihood that he has no spare time at all to think of his soul and inform himself in matters of religion. Any man could find many spare moments in which to develop his knowledge of such matters, if he cared as much about this as men do about less important matters. No-one is too enslaved to the necessities of life for that.

4. As well as people whose hard way of life narrows their routes to education and knowledge, there are others who are quite rich enough to own books and other devices for removing doubts and discovering truth. But they are hemmed in by the laws of their countries, and the strict guard over them by the authorities who have an interest in keeping them ignorant, for fear that if they knew more they would have less faith in the authorities. These are actually further from the freedom and opportunities of a fair enquiry than are the poor and wretched labourers I have just spoken of. And however high and great they may seem, they are confined to narrowness of thought and enslaved in what should be the freest part of a man, their understandings.

282

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xx: Error

This is generally the case of all those who live in countries where care is taken to propagate ·what the authorities think is· truth, without knowledge; where men are forced to be of the religion of the country, and must therefore swallow down opinions, as simple people swallow quack doctors’ pills, without knowing what they are made of or how they will work, and having to settle for believing that they will effect the cure. But the men I am speaking of are in this respect much more miserable than the patients of the quack, because they aren’t free to refuse to swallow something they would rather leave alone, or to choose the physician to whom they will entrust themselves.

5. Secondly ·in the section 1 list of causes of men’s believing against probability·, there are those who lack the skill to use the evidence they have regarding probabilities. People who can’t carry a chain of consequences in their heads, or estimate exactly the relative weights of conflicting proofs and testimonies, making a due allowance for every factor, can easily be misled into accepting propositions that are not probable. There are one-syllogism men, and two-syllogism ones, and others that can go only one step beyond that. These can’t always tell which side has the stronger support, can’t constantly follow the opinion that is in itself the more probable one. Anybody who has had any conversation with other people—even if he has never been in Westminster hall or the Exchange (at one end of the spectrum) and has never visited shelters for the homeless or madhouses (at the other)—will agree that men do differ greatly in their understandings. I shan’t here go into the question of the source of this great difference in men’s intellects: whether it arises from •a defect in the bodily organs that are specially adapted to thinking, or from •a lack of use of the intellectual faculties, making them dull and sluggish, or from •the natural differences in men’s souls themselves; or from •some or all of these together. It is evident that the levels of men’s understandings, apprehensions, and reasonings differ so much that one may, without insulting mankind, affirm that there is a greater intellectual distance between some men and others than between some men and some lower animals. How this comes about is a question of great importance, but not for my present purpose.

6. Thirdly, there are other people who lack proofs not because they are out of reach but because they won’t use them. These are people who have riches and leisure enough, and are not lacking in skill or in other helps, yet get no advantage from all this. •Their hot pursuit of pleasure, or constant drudgery in business, engages their thoughts elsewhere. •General laziness and negligence, or an aversion to books, study and meditation in particular, keep others from any serious thoughts. •Yet others, out of fear that an impartial enquiry would not favour the opinions that best suit their prejudices, lives, and plans, are satisfied with taking on trust, without examination, whatever they find convenient and in fashion. Thus most men, even of those who could do otherwise, pass their lives without encountering—let alone giving a rational assent to—probabilities they need to know, even when those probabilities lie so much within their view that they have only turn their eyes in that direction to be convinced of them. We know some men won’t read a letter that they think brings bad news; many men refuse to keep their accounts up to date, or even to think about their estates, when they have reason to fear that their affairs are in poor shape. How can men whose plentiful fortunes allow them leisure to improve their understandings satisfy themselves with lazy ignorance? I don’t know. But I think that a man must have a low opinion of his soul if he lays out all his

283

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xx: Error

income in provisions for his body, using none of it to procure the means and helps of knowledge; if he takes great care to appear always in a neat and splendid outside, and would be ashamed to be seen in coarse clothes or a patched coat, yet contentedly allows his mind to appear out of doors in a piebald costume of coarse patches and borrowed shreds such as it has been clothed in by chance or by his country-tailor (I mean the common opinion of those he has conversed with).... Those who call themselves gentlemen should reflect on the fact that however sure they are that their birth and fortune entitle them to credit, respect, power and authority, they will find all these carried away from them by men of lower condition who surpass them in knowledge. Those who are blind will always be led by those who see, or else fall into the ditch. And the most enslaved person is the one who isn’t free in his understanding.

I have shown some of the causes of wrong assent, and how it happens that probable doctrines are not always received with an assent proportional to the reasons that can be had for their probability. But so far I have discussed only cases where the proofs do exist but don’t appear to the person who embraces the error.

7. Fourthly, there remains the last sort ·of belief contrary to probability·, which occurs when people who have the real probabilities plainly laid before them nevertheless don’t accept the conclusion, and instead either suspend their assent or give it to the less probable opinion. This is the danger that threatens those who adopt wrong measures of probability. These wrong measures are:

1 Propositions that are not in themselves certain and evident, but doubtful and false, accepted as principles; ·discussed in sections 8–10·.

2 Received hypotheses; ·section 11·.

3 Predominant passions or inclinations; ·sections 12–16·.

4 Authority; ·section 17·.

8. The first and firmest ground of probability is the conformity something has to our own knowledge, especially the part of our knowledge that we have made our own and continue to regard as principles. These have so much influence on our opinions that it is usually by them that we judge concerning truth, and we measure probability in terms of them so strictly that if something is inconsistent with them—that is, with our ‘principles’—we count it not merely as improbable but as impossible. The reverence we give to these principles is so great, and their authority so supreme, that the testimony of other men and even the evidence of our own senses are often rejected when they threaten to testify to something contrary to these established rules. (I shan’t here discuss how far this is due to the doctrine of innate principles, and the doctrine that principles are not to be proved or questioned.) I freely grant that one truth can’t contradict another; but I venture to warn that everyone ought to be very careful about anything he accepts as a principle, examining it strictly and seeing whether he certainly knows it to be true through its own evidentness or whether he merely strongly believes it to be true on the authority of others. Anyone who swallows wrong principles, blindly giving himself up to the authority of some opinion that isn’t in itself evidently true, puts into his understanding a strong bias that will inevitably lead his assent astray.

9. Children commonly receive propositions into their minds (especially propositions about religious matters) from their parents, nurses, or those around them; and when these have worked their way into the child’s unwary and unbiassed understanding and held on there ever more tightly, they gradually come to be riveted there by long habit and upbringing,

284

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xx: Error

so that eventually they are fixed beyond any possibility of being pulled out again. And this holds, whether they are true or false. When the child has become an adult, he has no memory of acquiring these beliefs and doesn’t know how he came by them. When he reflects on his opinions, he finds that these early-fixed ‘principles’ go as far back in ·the history of· his mind as does his memory; and so he is apt to revere them as sacred things, and not to allow them to be profaned, touched, or questioned. He regards them as sacred oracles set up in his mind immediately by God himself, to be the great and unerring deciders of truth and falsehood, and the judges to which he should appeal in controversies of any sort.

10. When someone has arrived at this view of his principles (any principles), it is easy to imagined how he will react to any proposition—however clearly it has been proved—that invalidates their authority, or in any way conflicts with these internal oracles; whereas the grossest absurdities and improbabilities, as long as they are agreeable to such principles, are smoothly swallowed and easily digested. [The section continues with colourful remarks about errors and conflicts that arise from this attitude. Locke uses the example of the ‘intelligent Romanist’ who, because of childhood indoctrination, can ‘easily swallow the doctrine of transubstantiation—not only against all probability, but even against the clear evidence of his senses—and believe to be flesh something that he sees to be bread’. He adds that it is impossible to argue such a person into true beliefs unless he can be ‘persuaded to examine even those very principles’.]

11. Secondly, we come to people whose •minds have been moulded by a received hypothesis so that •they have exactly its size and shape. Unlike the previous group, these people will admit the matters of fact that their opponents bring against them, differing from the opponents only in how they explain the matters of fact. They don’t openly defy their senses, as the former group do. They can bring themselves to listen to opposing information a little more patiently; but they won’t incorporate it in their explanations of things, and they give no weight to probabilities that tend to show that things did not come about in exactly the way they have insisted they did. A learned professor would find it intolerable—a shame that his scarlet ·gown· would blush at—to have his authority of forty years’ standing, carved out of hard rock Greek and Latin with much expense of time and candle, and confirmed by general tradition and a reverend beard, overturned in an instant by an upstart innovator! Can we expect him to admit that what he taught his pupils thirty years ago was all error and mistake, and that he sold them hard words and ignorance at a very high price? Who will ever be prevailed on by cogent arguments to strip himself of all his old opinions and claims to knowledge and learning, and turn himself out stark naked, looking for new notions? The only arguments that can be used will lead such a person to treat his doctrines in the way a cold wind leads a traveller to treat his cloak—wrapping them around him all the tighter!

We can include under this ‘wrong hypothesis’ heading the errors that arise when a true hypothesis, or right principle, isn’t rightly understood. There is nothing more familiar than this. The instances of men contending for different opinions that they all derive from the infallible truth of the scripture, are an undeniable proof of it....

12. Thirdly, probabilities that go against men’s appetites and prevailing passions encounter the same fate. Let ever so much probability hang on one side of a greedy man’s reasoning, and money on the other—it is easy to foresee which way the balance will swing! Earthly minds, like mud-

285

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xx: Error

walls, resist the strongest cannons; and though perhaps sometimes the force of a clear argument may make some impression, yet they nevertheless stand firm and keep out the enemy truth that would capture or disturb them. Tell a man who is passionately in love that his mistress has been unfaithful to him, confront him with a score of witnesses to her falsehood, and it is ten to one that three kind words of hers will ·in his mind· outweigh all their testimonies, What suits our wishes is easily believed—as I think everyone has more than once experienced. Men can’t always openly defy or resist the force of manifest probabilities that go against them, yet they don’t yield to the argument. Although it is the nature of the understanding constantly to settle for the more probable side, a man has a power to suspend and restrain its enquiries, and not permit a full and satisfactory examination; and until such an examination is made, there will always be two ways left of evading the most apparent probabilities.

13. The arguments are mostly put forward in words, and the first evasive tactic is to allege that there may be a fallacy latent in them, and—when the argument is very long—that some of the stages in it may be incoherent. Very few discourses are so short, clear and consistent that one can’t plausibly enough raise this doubt about fallacy and incoherence. When it can be raised the doubter can, without being accused of dishonesty or unreasonableness, set himself free ·from the force of the prevailing probability·, using the old reply, ‘Though I can’t answer, I won’t yield’.

14. The second tactic for evading manifest probabilities is to withhold assent on the grounds that: ‘I don’t yet know everything that can be said on the contrary side. So although I am beaten I don’t have to yield, because I don’t know what forces there are in reserve behind.’ This is such a wide open refuge against conviction that it is hard to determine when a man is quite out of reach of it.

15. Still, there are limits to it; and when a man has carefully enquired into all the grounds of probability and unlikeliness, done his best to inform himself of all the relevant details, and done the calculation on each side, he can in most cases come to acknowledge on which side the greater over-all probability lies. ·And in some cases he will find that· he can’t refuse his assent. I think we can conclude that when there are sufficient grounds to suspect either that there is a verbal or logical fallacy in the proof of some proposition, or that there are equally good proofs on the contrary side, one can voluntarily choose between assent, suspense of judgment, and dissent. But •where the proofs make the proposition highly probable, and there isn’t sufficient ground to suspect either that there is discoverable fallacy of words or that equally valid though still undiscovered proofs are latent on the other side—then, I think, a man who has weighed the proofs can hardly refuse his assent to the side on which the greater probability appears. Is it probable that a random jumble of printing letters should often fall into an order such that they would print onto a page a coherent paragraph? Or that a group of atoms driven by blind chance and not guided by an understanding agent should frequently constitute the bodies of some species of animals? Nobody who thinks about questions like these can have a moment’s hesitation in answering, or answer with less than total confidence. Again, •when something is attested to by witnesses and is in its own nature neither probable nor improbable, and when there is no room for the supposition that there is equally strong testimony against it—for example whether there was 1700 years ago such a man in Rome as Julius Caesar—in all such cases, I think, it isn’t in any rational man’s power

286

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xx: Error

to refuse his assent; and his assent necessarily follows and accepts such probabilities. In other less clear cases, I think it is in man’s power to suspend his assent, and perhaps be satisfied with the proofs that he has, if they favour the opinion that suits his inclination or interest, and so stop from further search. But that a man should assent to the side that appears to him to be the less probable seems to me utterly out of the question; he can no more do that than he can believe the same thing to be probable and improbable at the same time.

16. Just as knowledge is no more a matter of choice than perception is, so also, I think, assent is no more up to us than knowledge is. When the agreement of a pair of ideas appears to my mind, whether immediately or with the help of reason, I can no more refuse to perceive it—no more avoid knowing it—than I can avoid seeing the objects that I turn my open eyes towards in daylight. And I can’t deny my assent to what on full examination I find to be the most probable. But though we can’t •hold back our knowledge once the agreement has been perceived, or •withhold our assent once the probability has clearly appeared through careful thought about all aspects of it, still we can hold back both knowledge and assent by •stopping our enquiry and not employing our faculties in the search of truth. If we didn’t have this power, there would never be anything to blame in ignorance, error, or infidelity.

We can, then, sometimes prevent or suspend our assent; but no-one who is well read in modern and ancient history can doubt that there is such a place as Rome or that there was such a man as Julius Caesar. Indeed there are millions of truths that don’t matter to a man, or that he thinks don’t matter to him: Was our king Richard III hunch-backed? Was Roger Bacon a mathematician or a magician? With questions like these, where the assent one way or the other is of no importance to the interests of anyone, it isn’t surprising that the mind gives itself up to the common opinion, or surrenders to the first comer. Opinions such as these are of so little weight and significance that, like dust in a sunbeam, their influence is rarely noticed. They are there by chance, as it were, and the mind lets them float freely. But when the mind judges that a given proposition is important, where the difference between assenting and not assenting has a great deal riding on it, then the mind sets itself seriously to enquire and examine the probability; and then, I think, it is not for us to choose which side to accept if the probabilities clearly favour one. The greater probability in that case will determine the assent; and a man can no more •avoid taking it to be true where he perceives the greater probability than he can •avoid knowing it to be true where he perceives the agreement or disagreement of two ideas.....

17. The fourth and last wrong measure of probability that I shall discuss keeps more people in ignorance or error than do the other three combined. I mentioned it in the foregoing chapter: it is the practice of giving our assent to the common received opinions of our friends, our party, our neighbourhood, or our country. How many men have no other ground for their beliefs than the supposed honesty or learning or number of members of their profession? As if honest or bookish men couldn’t err, or truth should be established by majority vote! Yet most men are satisfied with this. ‘The tenet has had the support of reverend antiquity, it comes to me with the passport of former ages, so I can safely accept it. Other men have been and are of the same opinion, so it is reasonable for me to embrace it too.’ To settle one’s opinions in such a way as this is worse than settling them by tossing a coin! All men are liable to error, and most

287

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xxi: Classifying the sciences

men are tempted to it by passion or interest. If we could see the secret motives that influence the men of reputation and learning in the world, and the leaders of parties, we wouldn’t always find that they were led to their favoured doctrines by embracing truth for its own sake! This at least is certain: there is no opinion so absurd that no-one has accepted it on this ground. There is no error that hasn’t had its supporters....

18. Despite the great noise that is made about errors and opinions, I must be fair to mankind and say: There aren’t so many men with errors and wrong opinions as is commonly supposed. I’m not thinking here of men who embrace the truth, but rather of ones who have no thought, no opinion at all, regarding the doctrines they make such a fuss about. For if we were to interrogate most partisans of most sects, so far from finding evidence that they acquired their opinions on the basis of examining arguments and the appearance of probability, we wouldn’t even find that they have any opinions of their own on the matters they are so zealous about! They are determined to stick to a party that they have been drawn to by upbringing or self-interest; and once they are in it they will, like the common soldiers of an army, show their courage and ardour as their leaders tell them to, without ever examining or even knowing the cause they are defending. If a man’s life shows that he has no serious regard for religion, why should we think that he racks his brains about the opinions of his church, and troubles himself to examine the grounds for this or that doctrine? It is enough for him to obey his leaders, to have his hand and his tongue ready for the support of the common cause, in this way winning the approval of those who can give him credit, promotion, or protection in that society. Thus men become supporters of, and combatants for, opinions that they were never convinced of—indeed, ones that they never even had floating in their heads! I’m not playing down how many improbable or erroneous opinions there are out there in the world; but I am saying that there are fewer people that actually assent to them, and mistake them for truths, than there are generally thought to be.

Chapter xxi: The division of the sciences

1. All that can fall within the range of human understanding is in three categories. 1 The nature of things as they are in themselves, their relations, and their manner of operation. 2 What man himself ought to do, as a thinking and willing agent, for the attainment of any end, especially happiness. 3 The ways and means by which the knowledge of each of those two is attained and communicated. I think that science [= ‘high-level disciplined knowledge’] can properly be divided into these three sorts.

2. First, the knowledge of things as they are in their own beings—their constitution, properties and operations. I am including here not only matter and body, but also spirits, which also have their proper natures, constitutions, and

288

Essay IV John Locke Chapter xxi: Classifying the sciences

operations. This, in a slightly enlarged sense of the word, I call physike [Locke gives it in Greek], or natural philosophy. This aims at bare speculative truth [= ‘truth about •what is in fact the case’, as distinct from •what it would be good to do and from •what must be the case], and anything that can give the mind of man any such truth belongs to natural philosophy, whether it concern God himself, angels, spirits, bodies, or any of their states or qualities.

3. Secondly, praktike [Greek again], the skill of applying our own powers and actions in the right way for the attainment of things that are good and useful. The most considerable branch of this is ethics, which is the seeking out of the rules and measures of human actions that lead lead to happiness, and of the means to practise them. This does not aim at •mere speculation and knowledge of truth, but rather at •right and the conduct suitable to it.

4. The third branch of science may be called semiotike [Greek], or the doctrine of signs. Because these are mostly words, this part of science is aptly enough termed also ‘logic’. [Locke gives the word in Greek; it comes from logos, which can mean ‘word’.] The business of this is to study the nature of the signs that the mind makes use of for understanding things and for conveying its knowledge to others. None of the things the mind contemplates is present to the understanding (except itself); so it must have present to it something that functions as a sign or representation of the thing it is thinking about; and this is an idea. Because the scene of ideas that makes one man’s thoughts can’t be laid open to the immediate view of anyone else, or stored anywhere but in the memory which isn’t a very secure repository, we need signs for our ideas so as to communicate our thoughts to one another and record them for our own use. The signs that men have found most convenient, and therefore generally make use of, are articulate sounds. So the study of ideas and words, as the great instruments of knowledge, makes an honourable part of the agenda of those who want to command a view of human knowledge across its whole extent. If they were carefully weighed, and studied as they deserve, words and ideas might present us with a sort of logic and criticism different from what we have encountered up to now.

5. This seems to me the first and most general division of the objects of our understanding, and the most natural. For a man can employ his thoughts about nothing but •the contemplation of things themselves, for the discovery of truth, and •the things in his own power, namely his own actions, for the attainment of his own ends, and •the signs the mind makes use of in both of the foregoing, and the right way to order them to achieve clarity. These three—things as they are in themselves knowable, actions as they depend on us for our happiness, and the right use of signs in pursuing knowledge—are utterly different from one another. So they have seemed to me to be the three great provinces of the intellectual world, wholly separate and distinct one from another.

289